<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance of His Sacred Royal Majesty of Sweden, unfolding the grounds and causes whereby His said Majesty was constrained to continue the war brought on by the king and Kingdom of Denmark, after the peace was ratified at Roskild, but neither pursu'd nor duly observ'd by the Danes· Anno 1658.</title>
            <author>Coyet, Peter Julius, 1618-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 252 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08850</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6734A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922425</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80922425</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08850)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2892:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance of His Sacred Royal Majesty of Sweden, unfolding the grounds and causes whereby His said Majesty was constrained to continue the war brought on by the king and Kingdom of Denmark, after the peace was ratified at Roskild, but neither pursu'd nor duly observ'd by the Danes· Anno 1658.</title>
                  <author>Coyet, Peter Julius, 1618-1667.</author>
                  <author>Karl X, Gustaf, king of Sweden, 1622-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 91 [i.e. 97] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Wood for D. Pakeman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Attributed erroneously to Karl X, Gustaf, King of Sweden.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sutro Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  X Gustav, --  King of Sweden, 1622-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dano-Swedish Wars, 1657-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE OF HIS Sacred Royal Majeſty OF SWEDEN, Unfolding the GROUNDS and CAUSES whereby His ſaid Majeſty was conſtrained to continue the WAR brought on him by the King and Kingdom of DENMARK, After the PEACE was ratified at <hi>Roskild,</hi> But neither Purſu'd nor duly Obſerv'd by the DANES. Anno 1658.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Wood</hi> for <hi>D. Pakeman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Sign of the Rain-bow in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:191851:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191851:2"/>
            <head>HIS MAJESTY OF SWEDENS Remonſtrance, Declaring the Reaſons that forc'd him to continue the WAR with DENMARK after the Treaty at <hi>Roskild.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are principally two things which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but affect any man with wonder, that ſhall without partiality weigh and obſerve the courſe and carriage of this War betwixt the Swedes and Danes, to wit, the ſingular moderation, which his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> to his Princely Renown, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and approved to the World: and on the other ſide, the extreme Ingratitude, whereby the Nation of <hi>Denmark</hi> hath deſervedly contracted a foul and laſting infamy.</p>
            <p>For when the moſt Serene his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Daniſh practices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sweden.</note> was by mature and weighty Reaſons drawn forth to a War againſt <hi>Poland,</hi> and that he fail'd not of ſuch ſucceſs as uſually accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany juſt undertakings, the Danes grew ſtreightwayes malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191851:3"/>affected to our Victories, deeming our Acquiſts to be their loſs and detriment: nor could they contain or forbear to publiſh theſe envious Paſſions, but they muſt be practiſing with the the States of <hi>Holland</hi> to give ſome check to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Swede in <hi>Pruſſia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">with Holland,</note> at leaſt they readily granted a free paſſage to the States Fleet through the Sound, contrary to their Faith given to us, and alſo joyn'd with them as many of their own men of War as they had in readineſs, and that to no other purpoſe, but onely to ſecond the croſs and ſiniſter Deſigns of the Dantzickers,<note place="margin">with the Dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zickers,</note> and to heighten and embitter the Pole againſt the Swede.</p>
            <p>And though this might have ſerv'd for a ſufficient teſtimony of their meaning to us, yet they held it too ſcant, unleſs they had alſo urg'd the Muſcovite to make a War on the Swedes,<note place="margin">and with the Muſcovites.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the goodlieſt Chriſtian Provinces as a booty, to the exquiſite Cruelties of barbarous Nations. Nor was the Play acted under a mask, as by men aſham'd to own their parts, but they ſent a pompous Embaſſy to congratulate the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Muſcovite into <hi>Liefland;</hi> ſolemnly exhorting him conſtantly to ſtick to, and effectually to proſecute ſo worthy a Deſign.</p>
            <p>His moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> having been duly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardful to that Amity,<note place="margin">The Swediſh dealing with the Dane to prevent a breach.</note> which his Neighborhood and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with the Danes required, to prevent any perverſe opinion that might be raiſed on his preparation for War, had in due ſeaſon directed his Reſident in the Daniſh Court to unfold his Majeſties purpoſe, and for what reaſons he was conſtrain'd to take up Ams againſt the Poles.</p>
            <p>Which Reaſons appear'd ſo ſufficient and juſt to the Daniſh King,<note place="margin">He acquaints him with his enterprize a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Poland, and propoſeth a Treaty for the Confirma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of ancient Leagues by his Reſident as Plenipotentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</note> that he profeſs'd never to impede or thwart his Deſign, but rather he ſeem'd to wiſh the Expedition proſperous.</p>
            <p>And for aſ much as it ſeem'd for the behoof of theſe Northern Kingdoms to joyn in a ſtraiter bond of Friendſhip, his Majeſty hath on his part neglected nothing that might conduce to the effecting and eſtabliſhing thereof: which ſeemed alſo fully prepar'd and ripe, when the Danes purpoſing nothing leſs then the confirmation of it, objected certain Grievances firſt to be removed. Which, when the Swediſh Plenipotentiary ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191851:3"/>nothing, deſired them to propound:<note place="margin">Which the Dane diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points,</note> after many delayes they retrive their old complaints of Injuries committed by the Subjects of <hi>Sweden</hi> to the prejudice of their Cuſtoms of the Sound. But when he had eaſily demonſtrated the groundleſs vanity of this, and what elſe was alledg'd, the Danes could no longer hold, but laying aſide the vizor, plainly urg'd to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd of the Covenants made at <hi>Bromſebroe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">by endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make void the treaty Bromſebroe.</note> The Swediſh Commiſſioner after ſo many fruitleſs Demonſtrations and Proteſtations being tyr'd with their jugling, and perceiving that the Danes had precluded all means of confirming the League,<note place="margin">Whereupon the Swediſh Reſident re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires.</note> took his leave of the King and moſt of the Peers of the Kingdom, and departed, referring the Debate of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Grievances to a meeting of the Senators of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, then ſhortly to be held on the Borders, according to the cuſtom of thoſe Northen People.</p>
            <p>He was ſcarce departed <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Danes ſeize upon Swediſh ſhips.</note> when three Swediſh ſhips coming from <hi>Portugal</hi> were detain'd, and made prize by the Danes in the Sound; and preſently after the Inhabitants of <hi>Breme</hi> and <hi>Pomerania</hi> are ſollicited to renounce their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, hood-wink'd with a ſpecious promiſe of Liberty,<note place="margin">Sollicit <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merania</hi> to Rebellion.</note> as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their impiety. Immediately after War was denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and an herald to that purpoſe ſent into <hi>Sweden,</hi> but one whoſe (otherwiſe) ſacred adminiſtration was profan'd by a Libell,<note place="margin">And denounce War.</note> which declaring ſuch frivolous and foul Cauſes of the ſaid War, in ſo virulent a ſtrain as never before was known to paſs betwixt Kings, rendred thoſe Cauſes yet more weak and contemptible.</p>
            <p>Indeed he received his deſerv'd cenſure by publique Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and the Danes themſelves ſome time after, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the ſhamefulneſs of the thing, ſo that in the Treaty at <hi>Roſchild</hi> they condemned it; but whereas it holds out the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the Swediſh Commiſſioner from <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> as the occaſion of the enſuing War, therein they add foul Impudence to Malice.<note place="margin">Which was contrived long before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> For the Papers of <hi>Andr. Bille</hi> chief Generall to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> which came to our hands on the poſſeſſing of <hi>Fredericks Ode,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Fuhnen,</hi> are more then ſufficient proof, how long before his departure this War was decreed, and that they were moſt ſtudious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191851:4"/>to contrive meanes of haſtening his departure.</p>
            <p>This publique Invective againſt the Swedes Nation was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by private calumny, the Peers of <hi>Denmark</hi> reckoning it great glory and merit to abound in tart Reproaches, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for a maſtery in ſcurrility with their poor and fordid eloquence. So great a matter it ſeems it was to unſheath a pen againſt the Swedes, and he that was the beſt proficient in ſcoffing and detraction, thereby preſum'd himſelf to be the worthieſt Patriot.</p>
            <p>The were the Daniſh Soldiers powr'd into the Countreys of <hi>Sweden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And ſoon after broke out.</note> diſcovering every where much impotent rage, eſpecially in the <hi>Dukall</hi> part of <hi>Holſtein</hi> and <hi>Breme,</hi> which, together with the reſt of <hi>Sweden,</hi> they had long ſince ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in hopes: but Divine Vengeance ſtaid not long, but ſtroak ſuch terror and dread into them, that ſome of them durſt not abide the approach of our men coming from the farther part of <hi>Lettow,</hi> but betook themſelves for ſhelter to adjacent Iſlands;<note place="margin">But were ſoon repulſed by the Swedes from <hi>Bremen</hi> and the <hi>Dukall Holſtein,</hi>
               </note> others received the wages of their raſh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, being in a few dayes time utterly expelled the Dutchy of <hi>Breme,</hi> excepting onely the Caſtle of <hi>Bremerford.</hi> Soon after all <hi>Jutland</hi> ſubmitted to the Swede, ſave that new built Fort of <hi>Fredericks Ode,</hi> which was at firſt ſtifly maintained by a conſiderable party of the Danes. But the valiant Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Wrangle</hi> encourag'd by his Majeſties influence and his own valour, after he had begirt it a few weeks, won it, without any great loſs of his own men, and having made great ſlaughter of the Enemy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>And</hi> Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks Ode <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
               </note> carried with him two thouſand Priſoners; amongſt whom were the chief General of <hi>Denmark</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Senator.</p>
            <p>His moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> did not forget in the current of theſe Victories his regard to Peace; Major General <hi>Jephſon</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Meadowes</hi> Agents for his Highneſs the Lord Protector of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the mean time Sweden offers terms of accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh publique Miniſters.</note> promoting it with all diligence; of which the former then reſided in the Swediſh Court, the latter in the Daniſh, to ſettle a Peace betwixt them. But how was this receiv'd by the Danes? They vouchſaf'd an Anſwer indeed three ſeveral times to thoſe things Sir <hi>Philip Meadowes</hi> had declar'd concerning this Buſineſſe, but with all they ſought
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191851:4"/>with ſuch arrogancy and height to impoſe Laws on the Swedes,<note place="margin">Which the Dane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns,</note> that it might thence be eaſily diſcern'd, what ſmall affection they had to Peace, notwithſtanding all that his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> could urge in his Declarations, to render them more calm and tractable. And that no man may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied in this Relation, we have here ſubjoyn'd the whole buſineſſe of the ſeveral Entercourſes under the Letters, <hi>A, B,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A, B, C, D, E, F &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>C, D, E, F.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Swedes perceiving themſelves to be onely born in hand with a counterfeit ſhew of Peace, and that the Danes did at the ſame time vigorouſly labour a Confederation with the Auſtrian, Pole, and Brandenburgh,<note place="margin">and makes Leagues with Auſtria, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Brandenburgh.</note> reſolved to infeſt them with War in their very lurking places, and ſince reaſon might not take place, to work them to it by force. Herein they found aſſiſtance from the extreme ſharpneſs of the Winter, which was ſuch that the whole Sea being frozen over, afforded paſſage, beyond all Record of example, for the whole Army of the Swedes into Fuhnen.<note place="margin">Whereupon the Swede marching over the Sea doth poſſeſs himſelf of <hi>Fuhnen.</hi>
               </note> On that Iſland abode the flower and choice of the Daniſh Souldiery, as alſo all the moſt hardy Commanders, who notwithſtanding being broken and put to flight, came into the power of the Swede, together with five Senatours of that Kingdom; ſo that it may well be affirm'd, that the Swediſh Affairs were by that dayes work much ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and that the very foundations of the Daniſh Kingdom began to totter: thus the Channell of the Sea was no ſufficient Mote to fortifie him, who aſſum'd to himſelf the Pride and Inſolence to oppreſſe others, who never had deſer'd any ſuch uſage at his hands.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty of <hi>Denmark</hi> being horribly ſurpriz'd with this News, and the more for that the Swedes had the ſame oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to paſſe into <hi>Zealand,</hi> began to adviſe with ſuch of his Peers, as he had about him, concerning a Peace,<note place="margin">And the Dane then deſires a Treaty of Peace.</note> deſiring the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Engliſh Agent, Sir <hi>Philip Meadowes,</hi> to mediate therein. Who, though he had found them deaf till then to all his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Peace, was very diligent and truſty to that charge, and ſending one of his Retinue to the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> then reſiding at <hi>Odenſea</hi> in <hi>Fuhnen,</hi> Letter G. adviſed him,<note place="margin">Letter G.</note> that the Danes were become inclinable to Peace. For that cold, which naturally doth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191851:5"/>harden,<note place="margin">Which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of by the Swedes. Letter H.</note> had now made the ſtony hearts of the Danes ſofter and more pliable then wax. To theſe Letters anſwer was made, Letter <hi>H.</hi> with great moderation, ſuch as could not be expected from a Prince in the height and heat of Conqueſt. The Meſſenger alſo return'd over the Ice into <hi>Zealand</hi> the ſame way he came, being inſtructed concerning the time and place of the Treaty.</p>
            <p>In the mean time his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> holding it unmeet to ſlight his opportunity, moved by the Iſlands, <hi>Langland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who marcheth over the Sea into Zealand.</note> 
               <hi>Laland,</hi> and <hi>Falſter,</hi> the way which Fates had open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with his victorious Army toward <hi>Zealand,</hi> and at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburg</hi> Caſtle met with the Engliſh Envoy Extraordinary, and ſome Daniſh Commiſſioners. There his Sacred Royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And a Treaty begins at Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburg.</note> underſtanding the Danes forwardneſſe to lay hold on a Peace, made no delay, but joyn'd Commiſſioners of his with them, who, for that it was for the behoof of each Party, to uſe diſpatch, might bring the matter to a ſpeedy iſſue.</p>
            <p>And doubtleſſe a Peace had then been concluded, (<hi>Monſieur Hugo Terlon</hi> the Embaſſadour in Ordinary from the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King of <hi>France</hi> to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Meadowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">But broken off by the Daniſh Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for default of Inſtructions</note> whom we have often occaſion to mention with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, much labouring therein) had not the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners pretended their Commiſſion was not large enough to make a Peace in the terms then propounded by the Swedes. For which cauſe they departed to <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> to return ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with further Commiſſion. In the mean time his moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that he might haſten the Peace, goeth on with his Army, and was approached even to the gates of <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> when the Daniſh Commiſſioners returning with the Engliſh Envoy extraordinary, were wonderous deſirous to conſummate the Agreement begun at <hi>Wordinburg.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon thoſe Honourable Perſons, who had mediated, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed at Toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trup, where the Articles were formed, Letter I.</note> gave meeting to the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of each Party at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> a Village near <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> where, having ſpent ſome dayes on the traverſe of Affairs, they reſolv'd on certain Articles to be ſhortly after enlarg'd and poliſh'd at <hi>Roskild,</hi> Letter <hi>I.</hi> for that it was impoſſible in ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191851:5"/>a huddle and ſpeed to give caution to all emergent diſputes and differences, that in tract of time might ariſe thereon. Which Articles,<note place="margin">And afterward confirmed at Rockild Letter K.</note> being prepar'd by the ſubſcriptions of thoſe Mediatours and the Commiſſioners were finally confirm'd and ratified by both the Kings, Letter <hi>K.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It might be eſteem'd almoſt miraculous, that his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> having been ſo much provok'd, and ſo ſet at naught by the Danes, ſhould ſo govern his courage and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, as to forbear the utter deſtruction of that Nation, that had ſo often threatned to root out him and his. Doubtleſs the Kingdom of the Danes had then been brought to a period, and <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> that onely remain'd, could have little avail'd them, being no otherwiſe defenſible, but by the naked bodies of men. There you might have ſeen King and Peers all in a confuſion, the Nobility at diſcord with the Citizens, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers mutining; and thoſe, who ſhould have been their guard and defence, powring out all manner of threats and menaces. Inſomuch, that thoſe that were moſt judicious, did moſt deſpair of the common ſafety, the wealthy Citizens imploring the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and protection of the Swedes. The Fortreſſes that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in <hi>Schonen,</hi> lay open to the enemy; not onely for that the Ice had made the paſſage eaſie, but alſo for that moſt of the Souldiers were drawn thence into <hi>Zealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the moſt Serene his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> wanted nothing but will to ruine the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> and thoſe, whom by force he might, he choſe rather to win by clemency, onely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Enemies that part of the Countrey, which had formerly been injuriouſly wreſted from the Swede; as alſo ſome places in Norway for his ſecurity, that though hereafter they would, they might not eaſily annoy him.</p>
            <p>Now who could imagine, that the Danes, who owe both their being and their dominion to be Swede, ſhould demonſtrate themſelves ſo utterly unworthy of thoſe benefits? For the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles at <hi>Toſtrup</hi> were ſcarce ſigned, and a Ceſſation of Arms on both ſides proclaim'd, when they took the boldneſs preſently to diſcover their malicious inclinations. It had been here decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red amongſt other things, that, before his Sacred Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> ſhould, for the better eaſe of the Countrey
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191851:6"/>diſpoſe of his Souldiers in their Quarters, untill it ſhould be agreeed upon the time of their departure out of <hi>Zealand</hi> in the meeting at <hi>Roskild,</hi> the Danes ſhould out of hand ſend in their promis'd aid of 2000.<note place="margin">But not duly kept on the Daniſh part.</note> Horſe. (For his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> had generouſly diſcharged them from ſending in the 2000 Foot, which by force of the Articles at <hi>Toſtrup</hi> they were bound to do, that he might expreſſe his affection to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who earneſtly beſought it, leſt he ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of all Foot Forces for the maintenance of his Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.) But mark what was here done. The Danes firſt took advice, as afterwards plainly appear'd, whether it were not wiſdom, under colour of ſending in aid, to ſet upon his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> at unawares, and to rid themſelves of the fear of an Enemy ſo near at hand. The contrivers of this Device had prevail'd, had it not received oppoſition from others, who did not ſo much deteſt the foulneſs of the Fact, as judiciouſly, diſcern, that thoſe Plots againſt ſo vigilant a King would hardly ſucceed. Yet, leſt they ſhould ſeem to deal too candidly with us,<note place="margin">The promiſed Horſe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent as was agreed.</note> inſtead of two thouſand German Horſe, after much balking they ſent us onely nine hundred thrity ſix, and thoſe in diſorder too, as if it had been none of their buſineſs; and of theſe the leaſt part Germans, or of any other Forreign Nations, but Danes born, in whom the Swedes could put little confidence; for that they knew it would be a grievous matter for them to bid adieu to their Countrey Pork and Peaſe; but rather, when the Swediſh Army ſhould march, they would ſlink away and forſake their Colours. Nor was it long ere it prov'd ſo, for of all that number there were onely four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſtaid, and thoſe Forreigners. Certainly his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden might juſtly have had rejected that patch'd and imperfect ſupply of Horſe, nor have admitted thoſe that were Danes by birth, much leſſe thoſe of <hi>Schonen,</hi> ſuch as were the Troups of <hi>Axell <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rop</hi> to come in and fill up the number. For they being appointed at the charge of the Miniſters and Bayliffs in <hi>Schonen,</hi> are to be concluded under the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with thoſe that ſet them out, and were before that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd by Covenants to pay Faith and Allegiance to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Sweden. But as his moſt Serene Majeſty of Sweden
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191851:6"/>had not onely paſſed over many things in thoſe Treaties, whereon he might have inſiſted, but alſo in others had receded much from his right in reference to what was promiſed; ſo in the buſineſſe of theſe Horſe,<note place="margin">Yet the Swede doth connive at this,</note> he was pleaſed to expreſs his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition, and to receive at the preſent ſuch as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of <hi>Denmark</hi> had been pleaſed to appoint him; yet on this condition, that the Remainder ſhould ſpeedily be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, all ſufficient and forreign Souldiers; at leaſt, if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that the Peace, which was drawn in ſhort at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Expecting due ſatisfaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the full ratification of the Treaty.</note> ſhould receive a finall confirmation at <hi>Roskild.</hi> Afterwards the Swedes Army was diſpers'd into their Quarters, being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to march out of <hi>Sealand,</hi> as ſoon as the buſineſs at <hi>Roskild</hi> ſhould be diſpatch'd.</p>
            <p>And though it be almoſt incredible, that the Danes being caſt upon thoſe extremities, ſhould delay the concluſion of an Agreement,<note place="margin">Yet the Danes do delay,</note> eſpecially ſince it was ſo much their concern to bring it to a ſpeedy iſſue; yet many dayes were trifled away at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and the whole matter ſpun out in hopes of ſome change of Affairs. For then the Swediſh army might be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated,<note place="margin">Hoping for a change of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</note> and <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> the better fortified againſt all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; and the Danes might have opportunity by Forreign Aids to make up their Breaches. But the fierceneſs of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the unwonted cold continued, contrary to the hopes of the Danes. His moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> who well enough perceiv'd the Danes drift, would not waſte time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pretence of Treaties, the loſs of which, as it is alwayes conſiderable, ſo then it was ineſtimable;<note place="margin">Which percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Swede, he threatens the attempting of <hi>Coppenhagen.</hi> Letter L.</note> but rather he enjoyn'd his Commiſſioners to urge the Danes, adding this commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that in caſe they continued to ſpin out longer delayes, he muſt of neceſſity make recourſe to his Warlike Power and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege <hi>Coppenhagen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon it was at length concluded, Letter <hi>L.</hi> and thoſe Gentlemen, which had mediated,<note place="margin">And then the Treaty was. fully ſubſcribed</note> ſubſcribed two Inſtruments drawn thereupon, together with the Commiſſioners of each part, and interchangeably delivered them, according to the cuſtome.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as the Danes ſuppoſed themſelves unable to ſuſtain a War, which might happen to them, having loſt ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191851:7"/>many Provinces, and which they were oblig'd to part with by the renouncing of all other Leagues,<note place="margin">And the Danes inſiſt upon a Treaty for a nearer League.</note> it was earneſtly ſought of the Swedes, not onely at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> but likewiſe at <hi>Roskild,</hi> that Commiſſioners of either Nation might ſuddenly be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the contracting of a ſtrait League between thoſe two Northern Countreys; whereof they gave them ſufficient hopes.</p>
            <p>Moreover ſome further Articles were conſented to,<note place="margin">And private Articles were agreed upon. Letter M.</note> Letter <hi>M.</hi> which were privately concluded, the Dane ſo deſiring it, yet were enforced with the like authority that the former had, by the ſubſciptions of thoſe honourable Mediatiours and the Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>We might obſerve the ſame candor in the Danes with the above noted, about the beginning of the Treaties at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> when in their Project they uſed for the moſt part ambiguous terms, onely to the end, that they might reſerve to themſelves matter ſufficient to wreſt them in the future, to a ſenſe injurious to us, in the mean time colourably affirming, that their ſenſe was the ſame with what the words of the Swedes Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners carried. But this appear'd yet more manifeſt at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and chiefly in that the Danes at the making of their Protocoll or Regiſtry were found guilty of that, which in the Cornelian Law de falſis is under a very ſharp penalty reſtrained. For when the Swediſh Commiſſioners in comparing the Projects of the Inſtrument of Peace,<note place="margin">Yet the Danes do falſifie the Articles.</note> had obſerved amongſt other things, that the Danes had not alwayes in perſpicuous terms expreſs'd the ſenſe of the Swediſh Projects, they not onely deſired upon that ambiguity the Danes expoſition, but alſo, that no ſtop might be put to the behoofful Work of Peace, they were content, upon condition their verball explication might for the better caution be inſerted in the Protocoll or Regiſtry, leſt by a different interpretation ſome controverſie might ariſe between theſe Northern Nations in ſucceeding times. Yea, to the end the certainty might be clear and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, the Swedes in many things of chiefeſt moment did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate to the Daniſh Pens the ſenſe of each party. Hence it was that the Swedes were the more facile, and were content to conform to the expreſſions of the Danes in many places of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191851:7"/>their Projects. Yet contrary to our hopes we afterwards found, that the Danes dealt very diſingenuouſly herein, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly depraving the Protocoll or Regiſtry, as ſhall in its proper place hereafter appear. But whatſoever there is of this, would ſignifie little, (ſince by vertue of the Peace made, all miſcarriages befor and in the Treaty were to be buried in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion) had they not after the Peace concluded renewed matter of jealouſie and diſtempers,<note place="margin">And give cauſe of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie after the peace conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> ſtifling that mutuall confidence that ſhould have been reviv'd and reſtor'd betwixt the two Kings. In the mean time his <hi>S. R. M.</hi> of <hi>Sweden</hi> underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Treaties at <hi>Roskild</hi> were in a manner drawn to a concluſion, commands part of his Army to march to <hi>Wordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> part to <hi>Corſoer,</hi> that they might paſs over into <hi>Jutland</hi> and <hi>Fuhnen</hi> before the ice was thaw'd;<note place="margin">When the Swede had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven order for a march out of Zealand.</note> Count <hi>Tot</hi> was ordered to prepare for his departure to <hi>Schonen,</hi> to take poſſeſſion in his Majeſties name of thoſe Towns and Caſtles, that were to be ſurrendred by the Danes.</p>
            <p>But the News had ſcarcely come to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> being yet at <hi>Ringſted</hi> of the finall concluſion of the Peace, when there poſted to him <hi>Owen Juull</hi> from <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> with Letters Credentiall from the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By reaſon that he refuſes to deliver the Forts in Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen according to agreement, offering onely Elſingburg an inconſiderable place.</note> informing amongſt other things, that the King could not render his Forts up in <hi>Schonen,</hi> ſo ſoon as was expected; for that it was impoſſible (by reaſon it began to thaw) to bring the Swediſh Army out of <hi>Sealand;</hi> yet that he was ready, to deliver up the Caſtle at <hi>Helſingburgh</hi> without delay for his ſecurity. And that they might the more cleanly impoſe upon the Swedes, he pretended, that the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> had not means enough to maintain thoſe Garriſon Souldiers in <hi>Schonen,</hi> whileſt the Swediſh Army remained in <hi>Sealand</hi> Nor would the ſaid <hi>Juul</hi> deſift from that pretence, although the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> undertook to make proviſion for thoſe Souldiers. Wherefore his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> diſmiſs'd the Agent with ſuch Anſwer, as ſuited with the preſent ſtate of Affairs, and was not a little moved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, it being eaſie to gueſs what the Danes then deſigned. For what ſecurity could he promiſe himſelf with his Army in an Iſland void of all defence, if thoſe Fortreſſes in <hi>Schonen</hi> were denied him? He had been wholly at the Danes diſpoſall, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191851:8"/>might have been brought to utmoſt extremities, if the Danes had found aid from abroad.</p>
            <p>And this was the ſuggeſtion of <hi>Beuningen,</hi> then Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour from the States of <hi>Holland</hi> into <hi>Denmark,</hi> who made them ſolemn promiſe,<note place="margin">At the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen</hi> upon aſſurance of ſupplies from <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </note> that, if the ſurrendry of thoſe Forts could be delay'd upon that pretence, they ſhould have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſupplies brought into <hi>Denmark</hi> for their relief, as ſoon as the ſea was navigable. Adding further, if they were diſtreſs'd for money, he would procure them a large ſupply, whereof alſo, as the report went, he gave them ſome earneſt, in lending them money at the preſent.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> recall'd his Army with all haſte, which was gone part to <hi>Wordinburgh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whereupon the Swede recalls his army, Then the Dane condeſcends to ſurrender <hi>Schonen.</hi> Letter N.</note> part to <hi>Corſoer,</hi> having ſent his Secretary <hi>Ehrenſtein</hi> to <hi>Roskild</hi> with ſtrict Injunction to the Commiſſioners, for preventing all occaſion the Danes might uſe to make deniall, that there ſhould be a particular Receſs appointed concerning the rendition of <hi>Schonen.</hi> Letter <hi>N.</hi> To which when the Daniſh Commiſſioners had eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, (for they had proceeded ſo far in words before) the Swediſh Army made ready once more to march away. But then the Froſt ſlackned,<note place="margin">And when the Swediſh Army was to march the ſecond time the weather ſlackens. Letter O.</note> and the Ice was not able to bear ſo great a weight, and the rather for that five or ſix dayes had elaps'd, in ſending and recalling the Army. And now his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> deſir'd to return into his Countrey, when Letters are brought him from the Daniſh King, Letter <hi>O.</hi> wherein was contained, not onely the confirmation of what hath been ſaid of the Rendition at <hi>Schonen,</hi> but alſo he himſelf was invited into the Caſtle of <hi>Fredericksburgh</hi> to a perſonall conference. Which latter part was alſo ſeconded by two of his chief Peers ſent to <hi>Roskild.</hi>
               <note place="margin">And the two Kings meet perſonally in great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> The King miſlik'd it not, and therefore came with a ſmall attendance. It was remarkable what great confidence each King had of the other; and hard to ſay, which of the two was moſt forward to give credit to the other: whether the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> were more confident, who adventur'd himſelf with ſo ſmall a guard among the Danes, that were more numerous; or the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who adventur'd his Perſon out of his Metropolis, whileſt the Swede was Maſter of the whole Countrey round about. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191851:8"/>whether the one or the other, this is certain, that thoſe two Kings ſpent there ſome dayes in ſuch brotherly amity and friendſhip, that any man would conclude all bitterneſſe and rancor was paſs'd over: Whereof this may ſerve for proof, that the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> amongſt other familiar diſcourſes made mention of that League we formerly ſpake of,<note place="margin">And the Dane doth inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a near uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> wherein he eſteem'd it neceſſary, that theſe two Northern Kingdoms ſhould he united, and deſired with great inſtance from the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that he would ſend his Ambaſſador into <hi>Denmark</hi> for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Thereupon his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> before his going to <hi>Got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinburgh,</hi> where he had commanded the Senatours of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Deputies of the three Orders to meet him, that he might diſcharge his faith and promiſe to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and moſt liberally perform all things,<note place="margin">Which the Swede readily puts in a way to be encount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> that tended to the amity of the Kingdoms, and the confirmation of the late con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Peace, gave Order for ſuch an Embaſſay at <hi>Malmoe</hi> in <hi>Schonen,</hi> with ample inſtructions, with all ſpeed to eſtabliſh the League the Dane had ſo earneſtly ſought, and he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd.</p>
            <p>The Lord Baron <hi>Stenot Bielcke,</hi> Senatour of the Kingdom, and Sir <hi>Peter Julius Coyet,</hi> Counſellour of State, who were deſign'd for that Embaſſay, chearfully undertook their charge;<note place="margin">Sending Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors,</note> and being ſet forwards on their Journey with all expedition, on the 19. day of <hi>March</hi> the ſame year they arriv'd at <hi>Coppenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen.</hi> There they were received in ſuch ſort,<note place="margin">Who were in appearance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with all integrity.</note> as was ſuitable to the honour of their Royall Maſters, being brought in and treated with ſuch great obſervancy of reſpect and reverence, that any one would thence ominate an happy event, and ſuch as was deſired to that Embaſſay. For the Senatours of the Kingdom were very large in expreſſing their fowardneſs and their ſincere deſire to maintain that mutuall correſpondence, not onely in the ſolemn admiſſion of our Ambaſſadours to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> but alſo in all private conferences; ſharply inveighing againſt the publique Miniſters of other States, who had entangled them in that War by ſeveral inſinuations and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. But how far different was the purpoſe of theſe Danes, 'twill be no hard matter for any man to gueſs, who ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191851:9"/>by the ſubſequent Narrative,<note place="margin">But not ſo in effect.</note> that the Danes in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe of a League had no other aim, but by their engines and devices, if not wholly to overthrow, yet for the moſt part to evacuate and defeat the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and by protracting the concluding of Peace, to gain time, and on the firſt occaſion that preſented it ſelf, by force and fraud to regain their loſt Provinces, the latter of which many of the Daniſh Nobility have not been aſham'd to talk of openly.</p>
            <p>'Twas a ſtrange thing, that the Daniſh Ambaſſadours, the Lord <hi>Axell <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rop,</hi> and <hi>Peter Reetzi,</hi> both Senatours of the Kingdom ſhould in their firſt meeting with the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours at <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> the 29. of <hi>March</hi> refuſe to draw up, as was their charge, any grounds and foundations of that League ſo much deſir'd firſt at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> then at <hi>Roskild,</hi> by the Daniſh Commiſſioners, and laſtly at <hi>Fredericksburgh</hi> by the King himfelf.<note place="margin">The Danes refuſing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the gounds of the League in writing.</note> Yet on the laſt day of the ſaid moneth of <hi>March</hi> they had another meeting and then after many delayes they pretended a form of that League in words, but would not exhibit it in writing, till the Swedes had firſt exhibited theirs.</p>
            <p>To ſay the truth, 'twas a matter of no great moment, and of little concern, which part ſhould firſt caſt their Articles into paper, but that there were hot coals cover'd under theſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. For what elſe did the Danes deſign, but to ſift out the meaning of the Swedes, and to rake together matter to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it, and render them odious to other Nations, as if they onely did eagerly purſue thoſe things, whereby other men might in any kinde ſuſtein loſs or prejudice. And that they might carry their Impoſture the more ſmoothly,<note place="margin">But at laſt done,</note> they deſired, that whatſoever paſs'd in word or writing in reference to the League,<note place="margin">Secrecy is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on both ſides,</note> ſhould be kept cloſe and ſecret from all the world. But they were moſt imprudently catch'd by their own Law, which they had deviſed to tye up others. For they acknowledg'd, that the Project,<note place="margin">But not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by the Danes.</note> which the Swedes had firſt drawn and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, was loſt, afault hardly to be excus'd in any ſervant, much leſs in ſuch Guardians of ſecrets, as they look upon themſelves to be. Yet this careleſſeneſs might be excus'd, had they not in a manner publiſhed to all men, what ever was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written or ſpoken,<note place="margin">Who revealed all to Beunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen the States Ambaſſador, who did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct all,</note> and eſpecially to <hi>Beuningen</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:191851:9"/>of the States of the united Provinces, by whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and counſell they ordered and managed ſtill their Deſignes and Determinations, inſomuch that he hath often boaſted, that he was the onely hinderance of the concluſion of the League betwixt the Swedes and Danes,<note place="margin">Letter P.</note> Letter <hi>P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the event will declare what profit hath accrewed to the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> or may for the future be expected by hearkening to ſo perverſe Councells; This is certain, that his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> had no other regard in this League,<note place="margin">Whereas the Swediſh whole aim was to to preſerve the Northern Kindoms in Peace. Letter Q.</note> but to ſecure the trade of the Baltick ſea, and preſerve the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> from the attempts of other Enemies. Which if ever, was then moſt neceſſary; and as all the Swedes Propoſalls in reference to the Leagne, ſo that laſt, Letter <hi>Q.</hi> do clearly manifeſt, that he had no other ſcope, but to preſerve thoſe Northern Kingdoms <hi>without the prejudice and detriment of any other,</hi> as the preciſe words in the Eleventh Article of the former approved Propoſalls being rad will diſcover.</p>
            <p>On the contrary the Danes had far different deſigns,<note place="margin">But the Daniſh deſign was to make the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at <hi>Roskild</hi> of none effect, as the dubious event of Wars might give the advantage.</note> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected all their craft, that under colour of contracting a ſtraiter League, they might ſhrink from the obligation of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and that by tying up the Swedes, they might ſuſpend the execution of very many of thoſe points upon the dubious event of Wars, wherein the Swedes muſt be immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved, not obſerving that the Treaty ſpake abſolutely, and took force immediately from the ratification of the Peace. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things might here be alledged touching the unreaſonable demands of the Danes, wherewith they had the confidence to urge the Swedes in their Projects, but becauſe they are part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (though but colourably) either mended or expunged in their laſt, Letter <hi>R.</hi> and are partly manifeſt by conferring the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh and Daniſh projects, we ſhall paſs them over,<note place="margin">Letter R,</note> onely reciting what was the main cauſe of breaking off that Treaty.</p>
            <p>In the Third Article of the tranſactions at <hi>Roskild,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The cauſe of the breaking off, of that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Treaty.</note> amongſt other things it was provided, that the Kingdoms of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> ſhould joyntly endeavour to impead the paſſage of any Fleet of War through the Sound itno the Baltick Sea,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:191851:10"/>to the end that the King and Kingdom of <hi>Sweden,</hi> together with the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> might preſerve their power and command, which they have alwayes joyntly held to this day, in the Baltick Sea, and from all preſcription have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined inviolate againſt all Oppoſers of what kinde, or under what pretence ſoever.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this caution, was not onely a negotiation ſome years ſince carried on by a Reſident of <hi>Poland</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> touching a League then to be made between the King of <hi>Poland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Danes having viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the former Treaties,</note> and the States of the united Provinces, of which this was one main drift, that a Dutch Fleet of War ſhould be equipped and ſent into the Baltick Sea; but alſo the Fleet that was ſent in the year 1656. contrary to the Priviledge of theſe Northern Kingdoms, though by conſent of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> as Joynt Commander, and that not onely ſent through the Sound to relieve and ſupply the enemies of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">by bringing in a forreign Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy into the Baltick Sea.</note> but alſo enforc'd by ſome of the Danes Men of War, contrary to the Faith both of his word and writing, to a great and generall miſchief. Which to prevent for the future, and to ſtop the claim of any other Nations, who might ſeek to ſend any Fleet into the Baltick Sea, pretending a conſent of one of the Joynt-Commanders of that Sea, the Swedes found it neceſſary moſt effectually to oblige the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> not onely from any ſuch conſent in the future, but alſo that whenſoever any Fleet ſhould endeavour to paſs in the diſlike of either of thoſe Kings, the other ſhould joyntly oppoſe their paſſage.<note place="margin">Which the Swede would prevent in time to come.</note> For it was the intent of his <hi>S. R. M.</hi> of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in caſe he ſhould at any time make War upon his Enemies, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure all things behinde him, and eſpecially Sea-ward, nor to permit, that any State by the like Attempts in future, ſhould challenge a paſſage by preſcription, in the wrong and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of thoſe Northern Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>But it is not materiall to diſcover at large that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Baltick Sea, and conſequently the power and right of prohibiting any Fleet of War, doth joyntly belong to theſe two Kingdoms, ſince there was never yet any diſpute thereof between the ſaid Kingdoms, neither have either of the Kings at any time interpoſed, when the other hath uſed or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191851:10"/>claimed his power againſt Intruders. We have an example of this in that Renowned King of Swedes the great <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> who was never controul'd or reſiſted, whileſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that Fleet, which the Duke of <hi>Fridland</hi> had provided in the Baltick Sea, under the Commiſſion of the German Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second. In the like manner, when <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth King of <hi>Denmark</hi> gave chaſe to a ſhip, which under Commiſſion from the King of <hi>Poland</hi> would have exacted Cuſtoms, near the City of <hi>Dantzick,</hi> the King of Swedes never expreſſed any diſlike. The ſame thing is likewiſe teſtified at large by the ſeverall writings of thoſe Kings then publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Sure it is, that the Swedes might yield to the Danes deſires, that the third Article of the tranſaction of <hi>Roskild,</hi> as alſo at <hi>Toſtrup</hi> was ſet down in this form: <hi>That no Enemy ſhould be permitted to ſend a Fleet of War into the Baltick Sea.</hi> But in this ſenſe, as the Daniſh Commiſſioners themſelves expounded it, that no forreign Fleet under what pretence ſoever ſhould paſs into the ſaid Sea, though not eſteem'd enemy to one of the Nations, and that in this caſe Forreign and Enemy were words Synonimous, and equivalent. Hence it was, that to make it the more apparent, in the ſaid third Article thoſe two appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions went together, chiefly becauſe the Danes pretended the word Enemy muſt therefore be added, leſt other States might thence apprehend matter of diſlike or ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>But indeed the Danes, who in their own Right, and alſo by vertue of the Agreement at <hi>Roskild,</hi> were oblig'd to jovn with his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in prohibiting all forreign Fleets from the Baltick Sea, to preſerve themſelves from a publique guilt of violating the Peace, ſteer'd a quite contrary courſe, and that they might put a ſtop upon the procedes of the Swedes ſucceſſes in War,<note place="margin">But the Danes ſeek to elude,</note> uſed all artifice to extricate and acquit themſelves from that obligation.</p>
            <p>Which to accompliſh they thought a fit opportunity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it ſelf in the debates of the League wherein they might ſlyly elude and change that abſolute Covenant of excluding forreign Fleets from the Baltick Sea into a Conditionall one; or to ſpeak plainly, to defer it to a day and time not at all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix'd.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191851:11"/>For although that often cited third Article of the tranſaction at <hi>Roskild</hi> doth clearly affirm, that either of theſe confederate Kings was bound, not onely by all means poſſible to hinder the paſſage of any Forreign Fleet of War by the Sound into the Baltick Sea, but alſo that no other Prince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſaid Kings, ſhould preſume to furniſh or uſe any Fleet of War in that Sea:<note place="margin">By limitting the third Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle at their pleaſure to have this ſenſe.</note> yet the Daniſh Commiſſioners had the confidence to limit that Obligation in their Projects, that it was to be underſtood, when thoſe Wars, the Swede was now engag'd in, ſhould be ended; and that not till then they were oblig'd to the performance, as it evidently appears by the fourth and fifth Article of the Daniſh Projects laſt by them produced.</p>
            <p>But this poſſibly might be paſs'd by, had they not abus'd the true and evident meaning, with forc'd interpretations. For whereas the Swediſh Ambaſſadours did plainly demonſtrate; that that added condition, or to ſpeak truly, the delaying of mutual aid was needleſs; for that there was no intent to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> in the Wars the Swedes then had in hand; but rather the promis'd Aſſiſtance was onely Naval, conſiſting in a certain definite number of ſhips ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed, which the Kingdom of Sweden could not ſtand in need of, neither againſt the Muſcovite, Pole, nor Emperour of Germany, (then King of Hungary and Bohemia) foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as none of theſe were powerful at Sea; and that the League had reference onely to thoſe, who being no neighbours to the Baltick Sea, ſhould attempt to infringe the juſt Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe Kings. To which the Danes gave this anſwer, That no Forreigner, during the Swedes Wars with the Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite, Pole, or the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> of the Imperial Line, would dare attempt to enter thoſe Seas with any Fleet,<note place="margin">That it ſhould be of no force till the preſent Wars ſhould be ended.</note> unleſs he were Friend or Confederate to one of thoſe forenamed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Swedes; and for that reaſon it would be no new War but the continuation of the preſent. The Danes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inſiſted upon that Clauſe, <hi>When the War ſhall be ended, which the Swedes have now in hand:</hi> adding further diverſe ſharp ſpeeches, which would be too long here to relate.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as that Treaty of the League did compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191851:11"/>matters of two kindes, to wit, the Conſequences of the Agreement at <hi>Roskild,</hi> which were therefore of perpetual Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation; and ſuch things as ſhould ariſe from that particular Convention, and were to be in force after the Peace was rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and therefore ought to be reſtrained to a time certain: the Swediſh Ambaſſadors, as the nature and condition of thoſe things required, alwayes carefully obſerved that difference in their Propoſals, as is very evident from the twelfth Article. But the Danes, who thought it a ſufficient diſcharge of their duty, if they did wilfully purſue their own method, though they were often adviſed of it, yet in the fourth, fifth, and tenth Article of their Propoſal, made mixture and confuſion of all things; intending that whatſoever was contained in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the League, was all to commence from the Ratification thereof, and would have it in force onely for the twelve Years following, not regarding that thoſe things which concern the defence of the Dominion in the Baltick Sea, did binde them to a perpetual obligation from the time of the Peace made, as the Covenants themſelves held it forth. That aid alſo, which was to be ſupplied by either Nation, for the excluding of Forreign Fleets of War out of the Baltick Sea, as was the tenor of the Agreement, fell under the ſame confuſion. For it was in all things couch'd under the ſame Qualifications with thoſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, which by vertue of the League to enſue, to wit, in caſe either King ſhould be aſſailed, the other was oblig'd to afford onely for twelve years following, and to the certain number often ſhips onely. Truly, it ſeems, they had no other ground herein, but that they thought the Swedes fit to be deluded with ſuch open Impoſtures, and out of a natural hatred to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſteemed them ſo ſtupid and ſottiſh, that they could not diſcover their Agreements to be fruſtrated and avoided by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and ſhifts. And, if we muſt be plain, it appears, that had not ſome of ours been too credulous, and truſted too much to the ingenuity of the Danes, the Swediſh Ambaſſadours had not perhaps been ſatisfied with that Expoſition the Danes made at <hi>Roskild,</hi> nor by their own eaſineſs had encourag'd them to attempt the ſame courſe at <hi>Coppenhagen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore when the Swediſh Ambaſſadours obſerv'd that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191851:12"/>the Danes endeavoured by thoſe forc'd limitations utterly to evacuate and render uſeleſs the enſuing League;<note place="margin">And the Swedes ſeeing their falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, are forced to break off.</note> and that thoſe ſiniſter ſuſpicions, which the bare name and report of a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all League between theſe Kingdoms might raiſe with forreign Nations, (for this Hobgoblin was almoſt daily produc'd like the Gorgon's Head) were onely colourably pretended, and that their heat and affection to the conforming of a League which they expreſs'd in words immediately after the Peace concluded, not onely grew Lac-warm, but was utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and that their labour was fruitleſs, they were unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be longer fed with vain hopes, eſpecially ſince they had manifeſtly diſcovered that other heads had influence upon, and acted the Daniſh Counſells. Therefore they themſelves were the firſt that brake off the Treaty, thinking it more ſafe and prudent, to expect a more ſerious return thereto, after the Wars, which the Swedes have now in hand, were ended, and that in the mean time what concerns the perfecting the Peace at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and the excluding Forreigners out of the Baltick Sea ſhould be inſerted into a particular Receſs, which they call de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative. But as the Daniſh Commiſſioners did with all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs embrace the former, ſo they utterly abandoned the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaying that it was to light a Candle to the Sun; if any man ſhould in this point endeavour to enlighten or unfold the Articles at <hi>Roskild.</hi> One might be here at a ſtand whether the Danes may more juſtly be taxed of ingratitude or of impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence but that it is certain that the former is never ſeen but in the worſt of men, the latter may ſometimes fall upon good and worthy perſons, and therefore is much more excuſable. For to endeavour to abuſe, and fraudulently to circumvent ſuch a King, to whom by Divine Providence, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous ſucceſs of his Forces, almoſt the whole Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> lay vanquiſh'd, and who might have ſacrific'd it to his revenge, if his juſt fury had ſet it on fire, and might have made the whole Nation Exiles and Caitiffes; after Peace grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and the greateſt part of their Territories, to the wonder of the whole world, reſtored; thus to requite ſuch a King is moſt foul and deteſtable Ingratitude. Neither is it leſs imprudence then to diſcover the vileneſs of their mindes,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191851:12"/>when he yet remained in the bowells of their Kingdom with a moſt powerfull Army, and might have taken ſuch vengeance on the violaters of Peace, as pleaſed him beſt. But as high and generous ſpirits are not eaſily provok'd to Revenge, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if there be hopes of amendment, without the utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the faulty; ſo his Sacred Royall Majeſty of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> choſe rather to make proof by any courſe,<note place="margin">And ſtanding to the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi> do publiſh it.</note> whether the Danes might by reaſon and without force be wrought to their juſt Devoir. To which he thought nothing more expedient, then by a clear Declaration to ſet out the Covenants agreed at <hi>Roskild.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon of producing and declaring this Treaty at <hi>Ros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild,</hi> as we ſaid before, was this, becauſe the Danes feigned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers complaints and grievances, accuſed the Swedes of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and violating the Peace lately concluded, made a ſenſe that could not at all ſtand with the Agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and quite contrary to the meaning of the Commiſſioners, and that beſides ſome things were mutually promiſed in that tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which by neceſſary and unavoidable conſequence concluded the alteration of the Agreements at <hi>Bromſebroe</hi> in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. To put a timely ſtop upon this, and as much as layes in the power of humane providence, utterly to extirpate and root out ſuch ſeeds of diviſion, his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> ſent Poſitive Orders to thoſe Ambaſſadours,<note place="margin">That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and Grievances wherewith the Danes did: blame the Swedes, might be removed.</note> which he had em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered to confirm the Peace, to uſe their eſpeciall care and endeavours herein. Nor did they in this omit any thing, but ſtill in performance of their duty, made it their onely aim and deſign to ſettle a laſting peace and quiet betwixt theſe Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Nations. To this purpoſe they met the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners very often, and they uſed all kinde of dexterity and prudence to lay open all thoſe things, which for the future might come into controverſie, on purpoſe to give the Danes an opportunity to gratifie themſelves. For what, pray, could have been more neceſſary for the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as their Affairs then ſtood if out of ſincerity of heart and a reall intention they had made a Peace? What more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God? What more glorious in the ſight of the whole world, then for two Neighbour Kingdoms, profeſſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191851:13"/>the ſame Religion, together and at the ſame time to ſettle a Peace, and remove all thoſe cauſes, that for the future might raiſe up any controverſie betwixt them? Yet, for all this, the Danes, as if they had been poſſeſs'd with a fatall blindeneſs, could never ſettle their mindes ſeriouſly to promote it. For though the Swediſh Ambaſſadours offered nothing, but what was juſt in it ſelf; and the Danes could not finde any thing to carp at, onely they ſaid, they ſpent their pains to no purpoſe in explaining of that, which was clear enough in it ſelf, and did plainly expreſs the meaning of the Commiſſioners: yet being urged, for the prevention of all miſtakes, to ſet down what ever both Parties mutually agreed upon in writing, they brought in another form, putting ſuch a ſenſe upon the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action at <hi>Roskild,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning the Swediſh ſhips paſſing through the Sound.</note> as might in part weaken and deſtroy all the accrewments ariſing out of the Swediſh Ships paſſing the Sound or Baltick Sea, in part much infringe their freedom from Cuſtoms, which they were of neceſſity to enjoy, by vertue of the Laws and Statutes of the Nation, but moſt eſpecially by reaſon of the Agreements made at <hi>Bromſebroe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man ſurely, unleſs byaſſed either by anger or malice, that knows the condition and commerce of theſe Northern Kingdoms, can perſwade himſelf, that the Swedes, who at that time might have acted their pleaſure upon the Danes, and had power enough to put Laws on their enemies, were ſo blinded as to make their condition worſe then it was formerly, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ſo nice a point at Paſſeports and Certificates are, the form, right, and validity of which had with ſuch care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence been ſettled at <hi>Bromſebroe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will ſcarcely too finde any, unleſs delighted to pick Cavils, that can put any other interpretation upon the fourth Article of the tranſaction at <hi>Roskild,</hi> eſpecially theſe words in the beginning; <hi>All and every Ship of</hi> Swethland, <hi>with what kinde of Merchandize ſoever they carry:</hi> but that all the ſhips of <hi>Sweden</hi> with their Merchandize of what ſort ſoever, and to whom ſoever belonging, ought to paſs freely, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying any Cuſtoms, ſo that they have with them their Paſs-ports, with the names of the Owners in them, if he well conſider the following words of the Article. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191851:13"/>ſtanding theſe things, the Daniſh Commiſſioners made a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion both of the one and the other, as alſo of many other things that concern the concluding of the Peace; and had the confidence to defend it againſt all likelihood of truth, reaſon, the credit of the Records, and their knowledge, who were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver abſent at that tranſaction at <hi>Roskild.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But any man may with good probability affirm,<note place="margin">And concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi>
               </note> that the Danes have not voluntarily performed in a manner any thing, to which they were oblig'd by the Agreement at <hi>Roskild,</hi> in that they put off moſt of them to a time not prefix'd; nor had ever performed them, had not the Affairs of his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> arm'd him both with power and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to have conſtrain'd them.</p>
            <p>It would be too large a ſtory, to relate all their crafty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, Pretences, Cavils, tedious Diverſions and Procraſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">The Danes defer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the news which are bruited againſt Sweden.</note> by which the Danes hop'd they might ſhift off the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Peace, and gain time till ſome emergent Wars or Troubles in other places might withdraw the Swediſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my out of <hi>Denmark.</hi> Therefore they fitted all their Treaties Executive to common Report and News, ſometimes protract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, as when it was reported that the Muſcovite was le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying a great Power, wherewith he would without doubt aſſail the Swedes in <hi>Finland</hi> and <hi>Leiſtand;</hi> or that the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks had concluded a Peace with the Poles, and therefore that the Swedes had ſmall hopes left them to compoſe their Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences there; or that the election of the then King of <hi>Hungary</hi> to be Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> could be no longer delayed, who together with the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> would undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raiſe Troubles on the Swedes, and draw them out of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark:</hi> on the other ſide, ſometimes poſting on their ſaid Treaties upon contrary reports. So that whoſoever ſhall compare the times of their Aſſemblies, according to the tenor of the Protocol, may obſerve, that the Danes made ſhew of intending the concluding of the Peace, and to ſtand to their promiſes, as the ſeverall reports came, either that the Electour of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> would not be oblig'd by the League made with the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> againſt the Swedes; or that the Swediſh Ambaſſadour in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> were reſtored again to liberty,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:191851:14"/>and a War probably to be commenced between the Muſcovite and the Pole: or that the election of the Emperour at <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furt</hi> was unexpectedly deferred; or that the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France</hi> together with the Lord Protector of <hi>England,</hi> had worſted the Spaniſh Army, with other matters of the like tendency.</p>
            <p>It was ſurely tedious enough to be thus born in hand with Treaties, but moſt tedious and offenſive, that the Danes ſought to clear themſelves of the cauſes of all thoſe delayes, giving out not onely in <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to lay the fault upon Sweden.</note> but in all parts abroad, that they had no ſooner removed any one obſtacle, but the Swede ſtill put in another, that they might never want a quarrell to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their Army in <hi>Denmark</hi> beyond the time agreed for their departure, to the utter waſting and ruine of their Countreys. But as all thoſe things are falſe and feign'd, ſo they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Danes to no other purpoſe, but that they might charge the Swedes with the fault of all their Procraſtinations, and as far as they could be believed, render the Swedes odious to the world.</p>
            <p>Thence alſo it was, that as ſoon as the Ambaſſadors came to <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> the Danes were not aſhamed to accuſe the Swedes, both by words and writing of not keeping the Peace, and renewed the ſame Complaints again not onely to them, but to his Sacred Royall Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> himſelf by <hi>Owen Juul</hi> at <hi>Gothenburgh,</hi> and that contrary to all reaſon, by wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conditions to their own advantage, directly contrary to the preciſe words and tenor of the Agreement, as hereafter ſhall more largely be diſcovered,</p>
            <p>Nor doth this ſeem to be done without ſome crafty intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Daniſh Commiſſioners having heard that the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Ambaſſadours did often alledge the authority of the Protocol,<note place="margin">Whereas they themſelves would not bring a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to keep the Protocoll.</note> and from thence did plainly demonſtrate the genuine ſenſe of the inſtrument of Peace, and the very verball explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Commiſſioners of either party, would not bring with them a man, who for the information of Poſterity might be wholy employed in this buſineſs, to inſert into the Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coll or Regiſtry all that was ſaid and done in the ſeveral meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. When they were put in minde of this by the Swediſh
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:191851:14"/>Commiſſioners, they excus'd the abſence of their Regiſter, being a Noble Man and one of their Chancellours, who about the beginning of the Treaties, had for a moneth diſcharg'd that Office, but was now abſent from the City: as if men fit for that employment were ſo ſcarce in <hi>Denmark,</hi> nor that a man in <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> could be found fit to ſupply his place.</p>
            <p>And this did not a little encreaſe our ſuſpicion,<note place="margin">Nor would they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh perſons with full-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to treat and conclude.</note> that the Daniſh Commiſſioners, though they were often advertis'd of it, could never be perſwaded to furniſh Perſons with a full power for the Executive Treaties. Indeed it cannot be denied, that at the firſt meeting for the making of this League, the Commiſſioners of either party were plenipotentiary delivering and changing each with other full and ſufficient Commiſſions of the ſame tenour: but thoſe did principally regard the League onely, and when that was over, being the principle mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they could be of no further force, as appears clearly out of the Plenipotentiary Commiſſions of the Swediſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, Letter <hi>S.</hi> Wherefore the Swediſh Ambaſſadours being inſtructed with new power from their King,<note place="margin">Letter S.</note> acquainted the Danes therewith, ſhewing them the Original and Authentick Commiſſions, and offering them to take Copies of them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly preſſing them, that they would be prepar'd with the like, that the ſolemnity of the whole tranſaction might be clear and manifeſt. But all this labour was fruitleſs; neither have the Danes to this day performed what they had ſo often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd.</p>
            <p>But it had been no hard matter for them to have procur'd the like ſufficient Commiſſions (which were the very foundation and eſſentiall part of the Treaties) when the Swede ſupplied them with the forms. Nor could they pretend forgetfulneſs, who had been ſo often put in minde of it. Nor was it a new and unuſual courſe in the beginning of any Treaty to exchange ſuch Commiſſions, for that a few weeks before, upon the firſt meeting about the League, the ſame ceremony had been uſed.</p>
            <p>Out of all which, as it is eaſie to collect what the Danes were working in their mindes, ſo it ſhall be yet more clearly diſcovered by a Narrative of ſome things concerning the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative and Executive Receſs.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:191851:15"/>
            <p>But before we deſcend to a full diſcourſe of them, it will not be unfit briefly to hint, how the Danes carried themſelves touching the ſatisfaction they promiſed to the Duke of <hi>Holſtein Gottorp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning the Duke of <hi>Holſtein.</hi>
               </note> There had been an ancient controverſie between the Houſe of <hi>Holſtein</hi> of the <hi>Gottorpian</hi> Line, and the Kings of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who are alſo Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> concerning the Chapter of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> and the Juriſdiction of <hi>Swabſted,</hi> of which the moiety by clear Right had belonged to the foreſaid Dukes of <hi>Holſtein</hi> for ſeventy years paſt. Nevertheleſſe the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> had taken to themſelves the whole Chapter and Juriſdiction,<note place="margin">The wrongs done unto him.</note> not regarding the frequent ſollicitations, by which the Dukes of <hi>Holſtein</hi> had endeavoured to have the matter decided by Arbitratours indifferently choſen for the conſideration of their right.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe at the beginning of this War, the Daniſh Souldiers had ſo grieved the Subjects of the forementioned Duke with continuall exactions, that worſe could ſcarce have been expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from an enemy, and that the condition of the moſt Serene Duke was worſe then thoſe of the Nobility, who by reaſon of the communion of Government were obnoxious to the power of the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe Territories had undergone the ſelf-ſame fate in the Wars, which <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth had wag'd firſt with <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the ſecond, Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and afterward with the King of Swedes, and the ſaid Duke was oppreſs'd with the charge of a War, which he had neither advis'd, nor as the Union of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> with the Dukes of <hi>Sleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> expreſly required, approved, and that onely under this pretence, that as he was Duke of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> he was a Vaſſall of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and that in the adminiſtration thereof, as alſo of the Dutchy of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> he took turns with the Kings of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereto may be added, that <hi>Bille</hi> General of <hi>Denmark,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been directed to that purpoſe by <hi>Gerſdorffe</hi> high Steward of the Kingdom, contriv'd plots for the gaining of the Dukes Forts, and thereby ſeiz'd the ſtrong Rampire of <hi>Stapelholme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore when the Duke found by ſad experience, that it was his lot to be underſervedly embroyl'd in all the Wars of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:191851:15"/>
               <hi>Denmark,</hi> and that, although he was poſſeſs'd of the Dutchy of <hi>Sleſwick</hi> in <hi>Franck Fee,</hi> yet he was made a common prey to both ſides, he bethought himſelf, as with juſtice he might, how to quit himſelf of the burthen of that Vaſſallage, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the Government of the Dutchies; and not onely to aſſert his right to the moiety of the Chapter of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> and Juriſdiction of <hi>Swabſted,</hi> together with ſo many years fruits, but to obtain due recompence for the wrong he had ſuſteined.</p>
            <p>For the more eaſie effecting whereof, his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> being thereto oblig'd both by the bonds of bloud and alliance, as alſo for that he had ſuffered much from the Danes out of the hatred they bare to the Swedes, offered his aſſiſtance,<note place="margin">Wherein the Swedes endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſee him righted.</note> ſtraitly enjoyning thoſe, who were ſent to conclude the Peace, that they ſhould have an eſpeciall regard to that buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Nor were the Swediſh Commiſſioners wanting in that charge, and they drew the whole matter to this head, that the Daniſh Commiſſioners conſented to thoſe three demands; to wit, of the Juriſdiction of <hi>Swabſted,</hi> and Chapter of <hi>Sleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> whereof they had claimed the one half in their own Right, the other in lieu of profits received, unleſs they would make ſatisfaction otherwiſe; likewiſe concerning the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging him from the burthen of Fealty,<note place="margin">Which the Danes having promiſed, do not perform.</note> and laſtly to the ſurceaſe of the communion in the government and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of thoſe Dutchies. And the Swediſh Commiſſioners were earneſtly urg'd by thoſe Gentlemen which had mediated, that they would acquieſce upon thoſe conceſſions. But when the Swediſh Commiſſioners did require of them to deliver into their hands the City of <hi>Rendsburgh</hi> in ſatisfaction of the wrong done, and alſo for future caution, that the Duke might be put to no further trouble, and the Danes preciſely and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily denied it; neither had the Swediſh Commiſſioners any power to diſpence with the rendry of the City to the Dukes prejudice, the diſpatch of the whole matter was referred to the coming of the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Holſtein</hi> who were expected every moment, yet ſo as that buſineſs ſhould make a peculiar Article in the Treaty of <hi>Roskild,</hi> by force whereof a juſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction was promiſed to be made to the ſaid Duke before the ſecond day of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:191851:16"/>
            <p>Indeed it cannot be denied that the words of the Article are generall, neither is the ſatisfaction reſtrein'd to thoſe four demands, on which the Swediſh Commiſſioners did inſiſt in the name of the ſaid Duke; yet ſince the Danes in the preſence of thoſe Mediatours had then already promis'd the three former, which might not be put in writing, onely becauſe the Danes were alwayes noſing the Swedes with the narrowneſs of the Dukes Commiſſion, it was ſcarely poſſible that any man ſhould harbour ſo hard a thought of the Danes, that they ſhould have the boldneſs to queſtion the truth of thoſe things, which had been done and declar'd in the preſence of ſo many witneſſes, perſons beyond all exception; and eſpecially when the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> himſelf had given manifeſt hopes to the Ambaſſadour of the French King to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding as ſoon as they came to <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> and began to treat about ſatisfaction with the delegates of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> the Danes there turn'd faces about, were quite of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other minde, and ſometimes by denying what they had promiſed at <hi>Roskild</hi> in the preſence of thoſe Gentlemen that mediated, ſometimes by ſeeking out new ſhifts and refuges, ſuffered the whole time to lapſe that was prefix'd them. And to diſcover themſelves the more, they intimated to Sir <hi>Philip Meadows</hi> the Engliſh Envoy Extraordinary a Proteſt,<note place="margin">Letter T.</note> Let. <hi>T.</hi> wherein they endeavored to lay all the blame on the delegates of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> for hindering the diſpatch of the affair, and declar'd their willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to refer that controverſie to Arbitratours, never conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that that way of compoſing of difference in this buſineſs had been ſo often made uſe of without the leaſt effect. Hence it is, that they can never make good their Proteſt to any, that do not take promiſe for performance. For the Danes being bound by the 22. Article of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi> in full and preciſe words to make ſatisfaction to the moſt Serene the Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> before the ſecond day of <hi>May;</hi> it was not enough for them to expreſs a willingneſs to ſubmit to thoſe things, which Arbitratours choſen by either party would have had adjudged; nor were they to be accounted to have given any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in it, in that they deſir'd onely to delay the Buſineſs by bare promiſes. Beſides the buſineſs of ſatisfaction ought
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:191851:16"/>not to have been agreed by Arbitratours, but by Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of either party, although that way too, had the Danes been willing to have had the controverſie decided, the matter might have been brought to a ſpeedy iſſue, and according to the Propoſalls of the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Sweden</hi> with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of thoſe of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> referred by both Parties to the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement of thoſe Gentlemen that were Mediatours. But this reliſh'd not well with the Danes, who made as great a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs about the narrowneſs of their Commiſſion, as if they had been to renew it in ſome forreign Countrey. The truth of it is, the Danes declin'd the putting of it to the Arbitration of thoſe Gentlemen that were Mediatours, becauſe they well knew, that they were privy to all the Promiſes they had made at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and therefore could expect no good ſucceſs in ſo bad a cauſe, where the Judges underſtood the whole matter. Nay, as if the Danes had accounted it ſome great ſin to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what they had engag'd their faith to, there were ſome amongſt them that would have the Peace broken under the pretence of the <hi>Holſtein</hi> buſineſs, and that there were ſuch kinde of Contrivances cheriſhed in the Daniſh Court, the French Ambaſſadour <hi>Monſieur Hugo Trelon</hi> informed his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Royall Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> his Ambaſſadours at <hi>Coppenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen.</hi> A thing indeed ſo much the more likely, in that they made uſe of <hi>Alfeld</hi> to compoſe the <hi>Holſtein</hi> Controverſies, being the ſame man that with his Colleges of his own name had uſed all his endeavours and artifices to perſwade, that the treaties with the Swedes might be brought at leaſt to give way for ſome entry for their Confederates. Hence it was, that both of them, who were deputed by the Danes for the buſineſs of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> inſtead of ſatisfaction preſumed to raiſe menaces againſt the moſt Serene Duke, ſpreading abroad that the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Army would not be there for ever, under whoſe counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance he might impoſe ſuch unjuſt things on the Danes. As if it were unjuſt for one to challenge that, which for ſeventy years paſt had contrary to all Law and Right been detein'd from him; or to ſhake off that yoak from his ſhoulders, which without the leaſt fault in him hath involv'd him thrice in a bloody War; or laſtly to deſire reparation for the loſs he had ſuſteined.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:191851:17"/>
            <p>At laſt after many long debates, the Swediſh Ambaſſadours told the Danes to their faces, that though they perform'd eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing elſe, yet if they did not this too, the Swediſh Army ſhould not march away, by which means that controverſie was laid aſide, though neither any time appointed, nor thoſe things gained, which had been heretofore promis'd at <hi>Roskild,</hi> And this by the way.</p>
            <p>When therefore, as we ſaid before, the Danes being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſuggeſtions of others, had fraudulently and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fram'd a form of the League, and given ſufficient cauſe to break up the Treaſties,<note place="margin">Nor would they conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, that there ſhould be a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority and Right in the Baltick Sea. Letter U.</note> the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Sweden</hi> inſerted into a particular Receſs that Article, that concern'd the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Superiority and Right in the Baltick Sea, as alſo other points that tended to the plainer declaration of the Third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild.</hi> For there was no reaſon, why the Danes ſhould refuſe to confirm it, foraſmuch as that Article, <hi>Letter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> was taken out of the Articles approv'd by the Commiſſioners of each Party when the League was drawn, with which it did in all things ſuit, as is ſufficiently evident by the comparing of thoſe Articles.</p>
            <p>But let us obſerve the carriage of the Danes herein. When they ſaw themſelves caſt into this neceſſity, either by admitting that point to abandon the opportunity, by which under ſome pretence and colour of Right they might quit themſelves from the Agreement at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and eſpecially from the obligation of the Third Article; or elſe by abrupt refuſall they muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their purpoſe hitherto conceal'd, which was not to be bound to a perpetuall obſervance of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi> they choſe the ſafer way, contending that the Treaty at <hi>Roskild</hi> as to this point was clear of it ſelf, and needed no other expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and that they did ſtick to the ſame meaning, which that point in the Swediſh Project did hold forth. At leaſt, to ſhun the ſuſpicion, which other Nations might thence apprehend, that they would not permit that that Article ſhould be ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſerted in a particular Receſs, as alſo they alwayes omitted it in their declarative Project.</p>
            <p>Hence it being obvious to the Swediſh Ambaſſadours, what a viper was here hatching, they did demonſtrate to the Danes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:191851:17"/>at ſeverall meetings, how neceſſary and behooffull it was not to omit that Article, for that it might be a means to prevent all indirect craft, which might be working in future times by the various interpretations upon that third point of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at <hi>Roskild:</hi> however that it was abſolutely neceſſary, that his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> ſhould be moſt clearly certified of the Danes ſincerity and true meaning towards him; neither was it a thing new and unheard oſ in matters of ſo great a moment, that though they ſeem clearly ſet down, yet they ſhould have the moſt plain and particular explication,<note place="margin">Nor that the explication of the words of the third Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild</hi> ſhould be made a ſecret Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</note> that nothing be left to ſubtle wits to wreſt and abuſe. But if they onely ſtuck at the ſuſpicion that might ariſe amongſt people of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there were divers wayes to remove that ſcruple. For that matter might either be comprehended in ſome ſecret Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, or that verball expoſition of the Daniſh Commiſſioners might by their conſent be inſerted into the Protocoll or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and ſubſcribed by each party for future information, that it might be impoſſible hereafter to raiſe any doubt of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſenſe of the Article, or of the meaning of thoſe that made it. But as they did onely make uſe of the ſuſpicion of other Nations, to hinder the diſpatch of the affairs; ſo that, which the Swedes propunded, could not poſſibly be acceptable to the Danes. For how, ſay they, can that be kept ſecret, to which not onely two Kings, but the Senatours of both the Kingdoms with many others are privy. And further they ſaid they had no ſuch Inſtructions from their King, and were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſatisfied that they ſhould never be Commiſſioned to draw up any ſecret Article with the Swedes to that purpoſe. At length being urg'd with great inſtance by the Swedes, they did conſent that that verball explication concering the genuine ſenſe of the third Article of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild</hi> ſhould be noted in due form in the Protocoll or Regiſtry,<note place="margin">Or brought into a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Receſs.</note> onely to that purpoſe, that it might afterwards be omitted in the peculiar Receſſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Swediſh Ambaſſadours being duly mindfull that the Danes had formerly taken the boldneſs to diſparage the Authority of the Protocol at <hi>Roskild,</hi> reputing it onely a private Writing, and ſuch as could carry no plenary proof;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:191851:18"/>they ſaw there was little force and ſecurity in that conceſſion of the Danes, yea no more, then was in their bare verbal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. For it was to be fear'd, that they would hereafter, as formerly, deny that that Annotation was made in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocol by their conſent and privity, chiefly, becauſe there was none preſent of their party that was appointed to perfect the Protocol,<note place="margin">Or ſubſcribed in a Protocoll,</note> as hath formerly been ſaid. Therefore it was thought neceſſary that both the Swediſh and Daniſh Commiſſioners ſhould ſeal and ſubſcribe this part of the Protocol. And ſo it was propounded to the Danes, who onely deluded the Swedes, and rejected them in this demand,<note place="margin">Prerending ſometimes want of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</note> uſing recourſe to their old Plea of wanting Commiſſion. At laſt, when after much hot contention, the Swediſh Ambaſſadours could not be prevail'd withal by ſuch frivolous excuſes, they put off the viſor, and were forc'd to diſcover, what they had rather have reſerv'd in their breaſts till a more commodious time, to with, that they could in no wayes approve the Swedes Project in reference to the Baltick Sea;<note place="margin">But at laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their purpoſe was not to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign men of War from the Baltick Sea.</note> that that ſaid Project did not faithfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> to which they were reſolv'd to ſtick; that it would not be in their power to alter any word or tittle in thoſe things, which both Kings together with the Senate of either Kingdom had ratified. Furthermore that it would be very abſurd in them to binde themſelves to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding of all Forreign Fleets whatſoever from the Baltick Sea, whereas by force of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> they were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd onely to the excluding of ſuch Fleets as ſhould come with Hoſtility, not thoſe which ſhould come either to convoy Merchants ſhips, or to relieve their friends, or elſe to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Ambaſſadours and other publique Miniſters from place to place.</p>
            <p>The Swediſh Commiſſioners had juſt cauſe to wonder at this had they not made ſufficient proof before that the Danes dealt' not clearly in this Treaty, and that their words and thoughts were far different: yet they could never have had imagined, that the Danes ſhould have the boldneſs publiquely to utter that which hitherto by reaſon of the apparent foulneſS there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they had ſought to palliate and diſſemble by ſo many far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetch'd colours and gloſſes. For, as we have above-noted,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:191851:18"/>the Daniſh Commiſſioners had formerly affirm'd in preciſe words,<note place="margin">Contrary to former tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions,</note> that they did maintain and hold the ſame Expoſition that the Swediſh Project did, concerning the third Article; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had they refuſed that the Expoſition they declared ſhould for the greater certainty be ſet down in the Protocol or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry: nay, what is more, in their drawing up of the League to be made with the Swedes, being a ſecond time exhibited in writing, they held forth the ſaid third Article in the very ſame form; ſo that they could not deny it now without horrible impudence, eſpecially ſince thoſe Daniſh Commiſſioners,<note place="margin">and expreſs Declarations at the Treaty at <hi>Roskild.</hi>
               </note> who were preſent at the Treaties at <hi>Roskild,</hi> did readily affirm, that a Forreign and Hoſtile Fleet in this caſe were Synonimous, and of the ſame import.</p>
            <p>Beſides, to ſpeak the truth, as the right of Convoying hath its original from the right of the Superiority of the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and no one ought juſtly to convoy any one through the territories of another; ſo no one can juſtly exerciſe that Right in the Baitick Sea, which hath been by general conſent of all the Borderers on that Sea, time out of minde,<note place="margin">And the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Priviledges of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</note> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any interruption, under the tuition and cuſtody of theſe two Northern Kingdoms onely. Yea, the States General themſelves in all their Leagues entred into with the Kingdom of Sweden, do acknowledge their Dominion in the Baltick Sea, never adjudging it from that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And how, pray, is it poſſible, that any one ſhould aſſiſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who is an enemy to either one of theſe Kings, and not be accounted an enemy in doing it? Or who yet ever grew to that height of madneſs, to ſay, that any thing was altered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is declar'd in more words the better to explain it? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Danes were poſſeſs'd with a new principle of Religion, that they could not with ſafety of conſcience put an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on that now, which a few dayes ago they preſum'd wholly to deny, or at leaſt to leſſen much. Yet at laſt they came thus near the mark, that a Forreign Fleet of War ſhould be prohibitted from coming into the Baltick Sea, but that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſhould not be denied to ſo many ſhips of War as did not make up a Fleet, which are ſent to tranſport Ambaſſadours, or do any offices of the like nature.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:191851:19"/>
            <p>When therefore they had ſhew'd the Danes at large,<note place="margin">But the King of Sweden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely upon former agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</note> how unjuſtly they proceeded in this and in many other buſineſſes, and withall in expreſs words added this threatning Language, that it was to be fear'd, that his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den perceiving too evidently that the Danes would not yield to thoſe Agrements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and that in a matter and Article of ſo great moment, would endeavour to procure his ſecurity ſome other way, ſince he could not obtain it, as it now appears by Treaties and Compoſitions in writing. At laſt the Daniſh Commiſſioners, and principally the high Steward <hi>Joachim Gerſdorff,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At laſt conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but not till the Moneth of July, after the Treaty at <hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild.</hi>
               </note> but not until the Moneth of <hi>July,</hi> declar'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they did in all things approve of, and were well pleas'd with the Swediſh Project in this buſineſs; and that they were willing to exhibite that point engroſs'd in writing, a thing, which though they were often urg'd to, they never yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>In the mean time whilſt theſe things are in agitation at <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the interim news comes of the preparation of a great Fleet at the ſollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburghs publique Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Letter X.</note> news was brought that there was a Fleet preparing in <hi>Holland</hi> to be ſent forthwith, as the report went, into the Baltick Sea. That which encreas'd the rumor, was, that there was an Envoy from the King of <hi>Poland</hi> negotiating with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and alſo a Miniſter of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> then Reſident at the <hi>Hague,</hi> who implor'd their aid by Sea, Letter <hi>X.</hi> in the name of his Maſter the Elector, who was much afraid of the Swede. Hence the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Sweden,</hi> according to the command of his Majeſty, thought it fitting for them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Daniſh Commiſſioners with it, and to deſire them to make ready ſome ſhips, and if there were occaſion, to joyn with the Swedes in ſtopping the paſſage of a Forreign Fleet. His Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden ſignified the ſame to them firſt himſelf,<note place="margin">Whereof no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice is given to the Danes by the King, and by Count <hi>Wrangel,</hi>
               </note> and then gave command that it ſhould be done at <hi>Gottorp</hi> to <hi>Owen Juul</hi> the Daniſh Ambaſſador, and after that Count <hi>Wrangell</hi> high Admiral of the Kingdom declar'd it again in diſcourſe with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lrick Chriſtian Gyldenlowe</hi> Lieutenant General of the Horſe to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words,<note place="margin">That a Fleet might be made ready to guard the Sound.</note> that he would not ſtir thence with his Army, till they had given ſatisfaction according to the Agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> in that particular. Then the Danes were very large
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:191851:19"/>in expreſſing their want and diſability;<note place="margin">But the Danes pretend in abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſet out a Fleet.</note> and that by reaſon of the War, they were lately engag'd in, they were reduced to ſuch ſtraits and extremity, that it was to no purpoſe to deſire any ſuch thing of them. His moſt Serene Majeſty therefore, that he might not ſeem to demand Impoſſibilities of them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by his Ambaſſadors that they would onely give out, that they made ready their whole Fleet, but indeed onely fit out eight ſhips for the ſervice, which together with the Swediſh Fleet conſiſting of forty ſhips, might be able without any great difficulty to keep out a Forreign Fleet.<note place="margin">Vhereupon the Swedes defire but eight ſhips to joyn with their Fleet.</note> But the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners complain'd of their want of ability to do this too, never remembring that in their own Project of a League, they had already of their own accord offered to ſet out ten ſhips. Every man therefore may ſee, how vain and falſe this pretence was, in that they had every thing in great abundance,<note place="margin">Which the Danes alſo refuſe to do.</note> which was requiſite for the furniſhing of eight ſhips. For there was no want of ſhips nor other neceſſaries, as guns, ſails, anchors, ropes, and other ſuch kinde of proviſion.<note place="margin">Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ability to do it.</note> They had ſtore of Mariners too, and victuals, of which they had already brought to <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> or might have brought a large ſupply from the Caſtle of <hi>Bahuſe</hi> and the fortified places of <hi>Schonen.</hi> But they would not hear in that ear, and made their whole pretence no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſo many Impoſſibilities.</p>
            <p>At laſt to avoid their making ready a Fleet, the Daniſh Commiſſioners ſaid,<note place="margin">Promiſing to prevail with the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral not to ſend any Fleet to the Baltick Sea. Letter Y.</note> that they would prevail with the States General, that no Fleet ſhould be made ready there to ſend into the Baltick Sea. But with what candor and fidelity they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd it, the Letters of <hi>Beuningen,</hi> Letter <hi>Y.</hi> written upon that ſubject will ſufficiently declare. For they were ſo far from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to hinder it, that they affirm'd to the aforeſaid <hi>Beuningen,</hi> that they had wholly refus'd the Declaration of the third Article at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and the joyning of their ſhips with the Swedes, which would admit that Article,<note place="margin">Although to <hi>Beuningen</hi> they declare the contrary.</note> and that the Swediſh Commiſſioners reſted content with that Declaration; and all this out of no other intention, but the more to provoke the Hollanders to make ready their Fleet. Yet it is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable that afterwards, that they might not ſeem to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, they went about the fitting of one Man of War, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:191851:20"/>whether to miſchief and ſpoil the Swede, or to ſide with them no body knows. For it were a ſtrange vanity, to expect fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iity in them, who never had ſo much as a will to keep their promiſes.</p>
            <p>There was as ſharp a diſpute too about the Iſland <hi>Ween;</hi>
               <note place="margin">A ſharp diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute doth ariſe concerning the Dominion of the Iſland of <hi>Ween.</hi> Letter Z. Letter AA. Letter BB.</note> for when his Sacred Royall Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> had ſummoned the Inhabitants by his Commiſſioners to come with the reſt of the people of <hi>Schonen,</hi> to take an Oath of Allegiance to him, they received contre-command from the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> Letter <hi>Z.</hi> and ſo obey'd it not, though they were ſummon'd a ſecond time, Letter <hi>A. A.</hi> as the Relation of the Lords Commiſſioners in <hi>Schonen</hi> unfolds it at large, Letter <hi>B.B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this reaſon the Swediſh Ambaſſadours then Reſident at <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> did at large, and with much pains, demonſtrate the injuſtice of that action in the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and that the Iſland <hi>Ween</hi> belong'd to <hi>Schonen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is a firm and undoubted Law among the more civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd Nations,<note place="margin">Proofs that it belongs to the Province of <hi>Schonen.</hi>
               </note> that all thoſe Iſlands, which make not particular Provinces of themſelves, are part of thoſe Provinces, to which they are next adjacent, unleſs it can plainly be prov'd either by contract or preſcription of the longeſt time that ſomething elſe was in force concerning the ſame. Now becauſe the Danes themſelves did not deny, that <hi>Ween</hi> was not a Province of it ſelf, it was preſum'd according to the Law of Nations, that it belongs to <hi>Schonen,</hi> to which it is next adjacent. Which preſumption of the Law being on the Swedes ſide, the proof of the contrary lay upon the Commiſſioners of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the Iſland of <hi>Ween</hi> was ſtill liable to the ſame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune with <hi>Schonen,</hi> not onely then, when it was given in pawn to the Counts of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> and afterwards redeemed by the Swedes, and united to that Kingdom by the Danes conſent, Letter <hi>C.C.D.D.</hi> but alſo when it was reſtored again to <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> by the King <hi>Magnus Smech.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let. CC.DD.</note> Which doubtleſs had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fell out, had it not been part of <hi>Schonen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, if we give any credit to the Northern Hiſtorians, it is manifeſt enough that the ancient bounds of the Swedes and Gothes reach'd to the middle of the Sound. And upon this ground he challeng'd <hi>Ween</hi> as belonging to <hi>Schonen,</hi> in as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:191851:20"/>much as there muſt be ſome reaſon for the determined middle of that Sea. Yea <hi>Arnold Huithfeld</hi> and <hi>Iſaack Pontanus</hi> do not deny that the ancient limits of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Schonen</hi> were agreed upon to be in the very Channell of the Sound, as their words taken out of the publique Inſtruments have it, Letter <hi>E.E.</hi> The credit of theſe men no Dane will dare to queſtion,<note place="margin">Letter EE.</note> in regard the one being Chancellour of the Kingdom of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> was both a great lover of his Countrey, and very much knowing in that Hiſtory; the other being a Dane born too, was hired by hsi Nation to compoſe the Annals of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and publiſhed that Work of his, collected out of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the Kingdom, by the authority and at the charge of King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth. What will they ſay, that in the Reign of <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> the firſt of <hi>Denmark</hi> long before <hi>Schonen</hi> was pawn'd to the Counts of <hi>Holſtein, Ween</hi> was ſubject to the Dioceſs of <hi>Lunden,</hi> and received Laws and Commands from the Archbiſhop there, under the quality of Biſhop of <hi>Schonen.</hi> Hence it is no wonder, that in all the alienations it went conſtantly with <hi>Schonen,</hi> as we ſaid before. Yet ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that <hi>Ween</hi> did not at firſt belong to <hi>Schonen,</hi> yet it cannot be dnied, that at that time when it was pawn'd and redeem'd, it was added to <hi>Schonen</hi> under the King <hi>Magnus Smech,</hi> and made parcell of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Letters of the grant of <hi>Schonen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letter FF.</note> Letter <hi>F F.</hi> do in plain words affirm, that <hi>Schonen</hi> was granted to the King and Kingdom of <hi>Sweden,</hi> with all the Appurtenances that either now belong or ever heretofore have belonged to it. But the Iſland of <hi>Ween</hi> did, as to its ſecular Juriſdiction, not onely at the time of the Grant (as the Conſtitution of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth, Letter <hi>GG. HH.</hi> written in the Book of Records of <hi>Schonen,</hi> and the avoiding or revocation of it,<note place="margin">Let. GG.HH. Letter II.</note> Letter <hi>II.</hi> by <hi>Frederick</hi> the Third now King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> at laſt after a Peace was concluded, and when it could not then be well avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doth plainly enough ſhow) belong to <hi>Schonen,</hi> but long before, when <hi>Schonen</hi> was ſubject to <hi>Sweden</hi> (which time we are principally to obſerve in this caſe) was united to that Province, and with the ſame Province diſunited from the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as <hi>Huithfeld, Pontanus,</hi> and very many others plainly affirm.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:191851:21"/>
            <p>Fifthly, It can ſcarcely be denied, but that his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> did at leaſt propoſe that to himſelf by the late Agreement, to reſtore to his own Countrey of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Schonen,</hi> whatſoever had been formerly with <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen</hi> taken away from <hi>Sweden;</hi> eſpecially that the ancient Bounds of <hi>Sweden,</hi> which were in the middle of the <hi>Sound,</hi> ſhould revert to him again.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, It is an Argument that the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> was willing for ſatisfaction to grant to his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> all that formerly with <hi>Schonen</hi> had been wreſted from <hi>Sweden,</hi> in as much as when he granted away many other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to <hi>Sweden,</hi> yet he reſerv'd not in expreſs words the Iſland of <hi>Ween</hi> to himſelf and the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the Author of the Book written in the Daniſh Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and entituled, <hi>Danmarcts oc Norgis fructbar Herlighed,</hi> or <hi>The fruitful Dominion of Denmark and Norway,</hi> doth plainly confeſs, that <hi>Ween</hi> doth properly belong to <hi>Schonen,</hi> unleſs by ſpecial Priviledge and Grant from the King, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be conſtituted to the contrary.</p>
            <p>The Daniſh Commiſſioners were not a little emploied to put a face of Juſtice upon their denial of it;<note place="margin">Which the Danes ſeek to avoid.</note> but they did chiefly endeavour to perſwade the Gentlemen, that were Mediatours, that the Demand of the Swedes was wholly unjnſt; and that there never was any one, that had the boldneſs to deny, that <hi>Ween</hi> was part of <hi>Sealan.</hi> They exhibitted the cauſes of this their aſſertion in writing, Letter <hi>KK.</hi> and to put the fairer cheat on them,<note place="margin">Letter KK.</note> divided them into two Claſſes, of which the firſt ſhould prove, that <hi>Ween</hi> was not granted to <hi>Sweden,</hi> the latter that it was a part of <hi>Sealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now as to what concerns the firſt Argument,<note place="margin">By ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh anſwer.</note> that that Iſland was expreſly named and demanded at <hi>Wordinburgh</hi> in ſatisfaction by the Swediſh Commiſſioners, but at <hi>Toſtrup</hi> and <hi>Roskild</hi> was omitted and paſs'd by in ſilence, and therefore that it was laid aſide, that truly makes little to the purpoſe. For <hi>Ween</hi> indeed was by name demanded at <hi>Wordinburgh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the firſt Claſſis.</note> as alſo <hi>Saltholm, Anholt, Leſſow, Bornholm,</hi> &amp;c. together with <hi>Schonen, Halland,</hi> and <hi>Blecking,</hi> but without that clauſe, <hi>With all the Appurtenances,</hi> which the Swediſh Commiſſioners therefore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:191851:21"/>counted ſuperfluous, becauſe at that time they were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that all the Appurtenances of thoſe provinces were reckoned in thoſe Iſlands, by reaſon they did not exactly know whether <hi>Saltholm</hi> did not belong to <hi>Schonen</hi> as well as <hi>Ween,</hi> and were in a doubt whether <hi>Anholt</hi> and <hi>Leſſow</hi> were parts of <hi>Halland.</hi> But when afterwards it appear'd very certainly to them, that <hi>Ween</hi> was part of <hi>Schonen,</hi> and that it was to be fear'd that there were yet more Iſlands appertenant to it, whoſe names they knew not, the Swediſh Commiſſioners thought it not ſo neceſſary to expreſs any Iſlands ſpecifically at <hi>Toſtrup</hi> and <hi>Roskild,</hi> but rather to comprehend them all in that generall clauſe, <hi>with all the Appurtenances,</hi> leſt by naming more Iſlands, they ſhould prejudice themſelves in others belonging to the Provinces that were to be ſurrendred, the names of which at that time they were not acquainted with; and give the Danes an occaſion by inſerting of one to collect that the other was excluded, and upon that ground to deny that <hi>Hitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roon,</hi> and other ſuch like Iſlands, do belong to the Coaſts of <hi>Trundheim,</hi> becauſe they were not expreſly named.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it being ſuppoſed, that at that time, to wit, in the firſt Project, (though there was never any ſuch thing) <hi>Ween</hi> was demanded as a thing apart and ſeparate from <hi>Sealand,</hi> yet you cannot thence infer, that it is not comprehended under the generall clauſe of Appertenances; if we can, as it may be eaſily done, make out that it either doth at this time belong to <hi>Schonen,</hi> or formerly did belong to it. Thirdly, it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Maxime. That a ſuperfluous clauſe doth neither good nor hurt.</p>
            <p>Laftly, no man can without manifeſt injury to the truth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that the Danes did expreſly reſerve the Iſland <hi>Ween</hi> to themſelves, in that they made Anſwer to the firſt Project, that they could not agree to that ſatisfaction, in which <hi>Ween</hi> was expreſly named, becauſe at that very ſame time they would not agree to give <hi>Bornholm,</hi> and the Dominion of <hi>Bahuſe</hi> and <hi>Trundheim</hi> in ſatisfaction, which Provinces and Dominions nevertheleſs they afterward granted together with <hi>Schonen, Halland</hi> and <hi>Blecking</hi> with all their appertenances.</p>
            <p>The other Argument of the firſt Claſſe, to wit, that the moſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:191851:22"/>Serene his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> did not demand the Iſland <hi>Ween,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the firſt Claſſis.</note> till after the time of the Surrendry of <hi>Schonen</hi> was expired, and after the Swediſh Commiſſioners had had poſſeſſion of all <hi>Schonen</hi> with its appertenances, and that <hi>Ween</hi> was without controverſie and contradiction left to the Danes, is much like the former. For all circumſtances being well conſidered, the contrary will plainly appear, and firſt in that, as ſoon as the places of defence in a Province are once given in poſſeſſion, all Countrey Villages and Pariſhes, which belong to that Province, are accounted to be at the ſame time given in poſſeſſion, which very thing alſo was made before the delivery of the ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Beſides, the Swediſh Commiſſioners ſummoned the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Ween</hi> together with thoſe of <hi>Schonen,</hi> to perform Homage, and take an Oath of Fealty: which when they were not then preſent to do, and gave no anſwer to the Letters that were ſent thither to that purpoſe, then his Sacred Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> after it came to his knowledge, was pleaſed to enjoyn his Ambaſſadours then reſident at <hi>Coppenhagan,</hi> to ſhew what right they had to that Iſland, and to make demand of it from the Danes, that ſo the Inhabitants of <hi>Ween</hi> might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced without any further circumſtances: this alſo he gave Order to his Deputies to ſignifie to <hi>Owen Juul</hi> Ambaſſadour of his Majeſty of <hi>Denmark</hi> at <hi>Gottenburgh.</hi> For to have made mention of this before, had been altogether unſeaſonable, and to no more purpoſe, then if we ſhould treat about the right of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to ſome Iſlands of Norway that are granted to it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Inhabitants thereof or any other ſhould ſtart any doubt about it. Laſtly his moſt Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> could not deſtroy his right, in that he did not preſently at the very beginning take poſſeſſion of the Iſland; for it is ſufficient in Law, if any one upon better information of what his right is then before he had, ſhall challenge it before the time of the enjoyment of it be ended. As if in caſe it had hapned, that in the grant of the Dominions of <hi>Trundheim</hi> and <hi>Bahuſe</hi> ſome of the Appertenances thereunto had been conceal'd by the Danes, which the Swediſh Miniſters and Commiſſioners being not very well skill'd in thoſe places, had not preſently demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, this would not at all hinder, but that they in proceſs of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:191851:22"/>time being better inform'd of the places belonging to it, and inſtructed with fit inſtruments, might claim that to themſelves which had formerly been fraudulently concealed. Becauſe the fraud of the Concealer doth in no wiſe dammage the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of him that deals juſtly, nor hinder him upon better informastion of what is his right, from demanding thoſe things which were given him by Grant. And thus much for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the firſt Claſſe.</p>
            <p>For as to what concerns the latter, which ſhould prove that <hi>Ween</hi> is a part of <hi>Sealand,</hi> this is the firſt,<note place="margin">The ſecond Claſſis, the firſt argument.</note> that that Iſland was both as to its Secular and Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, at all times ſubject to <hi>Sealand.</hi> But how true it is, doth eaſily appear from what hath been ſaid before. For we ſhew'd there, that that Iſland belong'd to Schnonen, not onely in that time when it was pawn'd to the Counts of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> but by a later Grant. For thoſe Letters of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth, which are alledg'd to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie this, make nothing in the caſe; for he that looks upon them but ſuperficially may perceive the contrary, and that it was for a peculiar reaſon, that it did at ſometimes ſubmit to the Provincial power of Sealand. But that Ween hath been formerly ſubject to the Biſhop of Sealand, makes it no more a part of Sealand, then Falſtre, Laland, Langland, and part of Alſen, which at this day are under the Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of Odenſea, are by reaſon of that, parts of Fuhnen. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Kingdoms of Sweden and Denmark themſelves were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly under the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of Hamburgh, which nevertheleſs had no other dependency from it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument of the Danes is,<note place="margin">The ſecond argument.</note> that thoſe of Ween uſe the ſame Language and Dialect with thoſe of Sealand. But no one is ſo blinde, as that he cannot ſee the weakneſs of this Argument. If all the Inhabitants of Amack, as a part of them doth, ſhould ſpeak the Dutch Language, yet no body, by the Danes good leave, would conclude that therefore Amack is under the Government of Holland. So all the Inhabitants of the Iſland of Nockoe, onely of all Eaſtland, ſpeak the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Language, yet doubtleſs that Iſland is a part of Eaſtland. He muſt be ignorant of all Antiquity, to ſay no worſe, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:191851:23"/>doth not apprehend ſuch things come to paſs by the tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Colonies. Hence indeed we might without much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty grant, that ſome of Sealand have inhabited that Iſland, but he that would thence collect, that that Iſland it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Sealand, muſt have his brains in his heels. As if it might not be too, that by reaſon of the often commerce with the Citizens of Coppenhagen, the Inhabitants of Ween might frame themſelves to ſpeak the Language of Sealand, when as every week they uſe to go thither.</p>
            <p>The third Argument,<note place="margin">The third ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note> whereon the Danes lay their main ſtreſs, is of the ſame force and ſubſtance, to wit, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ween hold their Land by Villanage, and uſe the ſame Law with thoſe of Sealand. For to begin with the latter, as it doth not follow, becauſe Fuhnen, Langland, and Laland uſe the Law of Jutland; the Cities Stralſand, Roſtock, Gryphiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald, &amp;c. the Law of Lubeck; Stetin that of Magdeburgh; Poland in many points that of Saxony; that therefore theſe places ſhall belong to Jutland, Lubeck, Magdeburgh, or Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: ſo neither can we conclude that Ween is appurtenant to Sealand, becauſe it uſeth the Law of Sealand. And it is ſtrange that the Danes ſhould ſeek to conclude from the Laws and Cuſtoms of any Province, to whom that Province doth belong, whereas by force of the Treaty at Roskild, Schonen, Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Blecking Provinces granted to the Swedes, are by ſpecial Agreement to enjoy for the future the Daniſh Laws, notwithſtanding they are for ever annex'd and united to the Kingdom of Sweden.</p>
            <p>But as to the former, that that ſubjection of thoſe of Ween, to wit, the holding of their Land by Villanage, is a thing peculiar onely to Sealand of all the Daniſh provinces; and that Sealand with the places appertinent to it, is as it were ſpecifically diſtinguiſh'd from all the other Territories of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, we know not whether it deſerves better indignation or laughter. For if it be a ſhame for a Citizen to be ignorant of the Laws of his Countrey, we can ſcarce finde how the Daniſh Commiſſioners ſhould acquit themfelves of a foul fault, who are not aſham'd to declare thoſe things upon a Publique ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, which the meaneſt of the Commonalty know to be moſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:191851:23"/>falſe. Are not thoſe of Laland Tenants alſo by Villenage, in ſo much that the very Clergy were heretofore ſubject to that burthen, as <hi>Stephanius</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Third plainly confeſſeth; not a little decrying the King, for that he diſcharg'd them of that ſervice. But what ſhall we ſay of Amack, where the people are not bound to Villenage, but free Denizons? For either this muſt be no longer part of Sealand, or Laland muſt be appertinent to Sealand; neither of which the Danes either can or will acknowledge. But it becomes him, who hath once abandoned ſhame, to be impudent with a miſchief, eſpecially where thoſe that baulk the truth may hope for a reward.</p>
            <p>Their laſt reaſon was fetch'd from Authorities,<note place="margin">The fourth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note> for that all Writers, both Ancient and Modern, do comprehend Ween un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the deſcription of Sealand. That the Daniſh Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners might gain credit to this aſſertion, they ſent to Monſieur <hi>Terlon</hi>'s lodging, Ambaſſadour of the French King, and one of the Mediators, a whole pile of Books, from whence it might be diſcovered, that Ween did belong to Sealand and not to Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen. But the cover was fit for the diſh, and the Cauſe was not ſo bad, but the Witneſſes were worſe. For who would have dream'd that the Danes ſhould carry themſelves ſo careleſly in an affair of ſo great moment; and for the clearing of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, whether Ween did belong to Sealand or Schonen, ſhould produce thoſe for witneſſes, who are not Danes by birth, nor knowing in the Hiſtory of Denmark, and ſo might accurately decide the matter, but forreigners and ſtrangers, ſuch as could claim no credit at all in the Affairs of thoſe Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Nations, nor have deſcrib'd the ſtate of thoſe Kingdoms with due diligence or previous enquiry, but have ſcribled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out choice or judgement, what ever they could finde in other Writers. That this may manifeſtly appear, let us examine that Author, who exceeds all the reſt in bulk and error, <hi>Atlas major Joannis Janſſonii de Anno</hi> 1664. and we ſhall perceive how dim-ſighted the Danes were in citing him. For he in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Denmark affirms, that Jutland is divided into Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern and Southern, of which the latter hath anciently been call'd Nordalbingen, and containeth the Dukedom of Sleſwick,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:191851:24"/>to which alſo Holſtein is ſubject. But who is ſo ignorant of theſe places, as not to diſcern this to be moſt groſly falſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Holſtein is no part of Denmark, nor <hi>in ſpecie</hi> of the Dukedom of Sleſwick, but a part of Germany and feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary to the Roman Empire, and is held of the King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark onely under the title of Duke. Nor is that a ſmall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that he reckons Store a River of Holſtein amongſt the Rivers of the Kingdom of Denmark. Thirdly, having ſpoken of the Sound, he addes this, that even there, to wit, near that Strait, Roskild is ſcituated; manifeſtly contrary to the truth, ſince that City lies about eight German miles diſtant from thence. Fourthly, diſcourſing of the Iſlands adjacent to Sealand, he affirms that Monen contains Stege, and other Cities, where as there is no other City there to be found. Fifthly, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that Schonen hath been uſually divided into two Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, Halland and Blecking, a thing which the Danes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will acknowledge to be falſe.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, concerning the preſent and modern Eſtate he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that in Lunden of Schonen is an Archbiſhops Sea, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is onely a Biſhoprick and no more. Seventhly, which is a moſt notorious dotage in him, or rather ſottiſhneſs, he makes Malmoe, uſually called by the Flemmings Elmbegn, to be two Towns, which is onely one Town with two names. Juſt as if a man ſhould affirm, that Gedanum were a Town different from Dantzick, Sedin from Stetin, Regiomont from Konigſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, and Bigoſce from Bromberg. Eightly, he makes Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Blecking to be appertinent to Schonen, which are Provinces independent, though in matters Eccleſiaſtical ſubject to one Biſhop. Ninthly, he ſets down the Iſlands Sando, Hanno, and Bornholm, belonging to Schonen, of which the latter is a diſtinct Province of it ſelf, ſeated under the Dioceſs of Lunden. Tenthly, in his deſcription of Jutland, Letter <hi>AA.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letter AA.</note> the Author reports that the Biſhoprick of Sleſwick was alwayes in the poſſeſſion of the Dukes, and alwayes ſubject to the Kingdom of Denmark. The falſeneſs of which, the Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates lately ſent to Coppenhagen by the moſt Serene <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of Holſtein did at large demonſtrate. Eleventhly in his deſcription of Fuhnen,<note place="margin">Letter BB.</note> Letter <hi>BB.</hi> he ſaith, that Fuhnen is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:191851:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>from Denmark by the ſtrait of Middlefact, as if Fuhnen alſo were not Denmark, and onely Jutland went by the name of Denmark. Twelfthly, he writes that Fuhnen contains in it ninety Iſlands, amongſt which he counts Laland, Falſtre, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and others, which are particular Provinces of themſelves, and do no otherwiſe belong to Fuhnen, then that in matters ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual they are under the Biſhop of Odenſea. Nay, Alſen and Aroe do rather depend of the Dukedom of Sleſwick. But for thoſe ninety Iſlands, we ſhall have need of another <hi>Columbus</hi> to diſcover them Thirteenthly, In his deſcription of Norway he affirms, that Marſtrand is a Peninſula; a falſhood that is obvious to every one. Fourteenthly, In his deſcription of Sweden he would have Ingermanland to be ſeated on one ſide of Capor, when as Capor is a city of Ingermanland. Theſe Abſurdities amongſt many thouſand others we onely inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſhow what ſmall credit, or indeed that no credit at all is to be given to this grand Witneſs, the Danes produc'd, in theſe Northern Affairs.</p>
            <p>That French Book is much alike too, that is entituled, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription General d' Europe Quatrieſme parte du Monde, par Pierre d' Avity, inprimè à Paris Anno,</hi> 1643. in fol. For he in that deſcription of his, cites in the Margent thoſe very ſame Authors, which <hi>Janſſonius</hi> in his <hi>Atlas</hi> puts down that he made uſe of, and therefore deſerves no greater credit then the other. But, to paſs over thoſe errors, which he commits very often in his deſcription of Schonen, by imitating the <hi>Atlas,</hi> what ever concerns this buſineſs, makes Ween no more a part of Sealand, then Langland, Laland, Falſtre, Alſen, Aroe, &amp;c. parts of Fuhnen.</p>
            <p>Nor in this caſe is the other French Book of any weight, entituled, <hi>Les Empires, Royaumes, Eſtats, Seigneries, &amp;c. par le Sieur D V. J. Y. inprimè à S. Omer,</hi> 1614. in quarto. For it is not onely ſtuff'd with the Errors that are in the <hi>Atlas,</hi> but hath ſo many more beſides that any one may eaſily ſee he was a faithful Collector of others too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis Gothofred</hi> in his <hi>Archontologia Coſmica,</hi> and <hi>Martin Zeiler</hi> in his Deſcription of Denmark, run into the ſame error; the latter of which, having no foundation to go on, fails moſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:191851:25"/>groſly, not onely in counting Hallands-As, a montanous wood of that name, amongſt the Maritine Towns of Halland; but alſo in putting Trelleburgh Uſted, Santhammer, Ahuſe, Sylfs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, &amp;c. amongſt the Maritines Cities of Blecking; when as indeed onely that, he ſet laſt, belongs to that place, all the reſt being adjacent to Schonen.</p>
            <p>As to what concerns <hi>Heylin's</hi> Coſmography in Engliſh, that ſaith indeed that the Iſland Ween, amongſt other Provinces, is ſubject to the Government of Sealand: but by that word Government, he underſtands onely Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction; as he writes that Laland, Langland, Falſtre, Arroe, &amp;c. are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Government of Fuhnen, becauſe the Biſhop of Odenſea, as to matters Spiritual, governs there; but for what belongs to ſecular Juriſdiction, by the Danes own confeſſion, it hath dependance upon no other; and the Author himſelf affirms, that Alſen and Arroe are parts of the Dukedom of Sleſwick. But though that Engliſh Hiſtorian ſtumbled not at this ſtone, yet to paſs by other things, he betrayes his ignorance in the Affairs of theſe Northern parts, in that be ſaith, that the Iſland of Bornholm was ſo called from a City of the ſame name; a place which no man yet could ever finde there.</p>
            <p>The Rere was brought up by two Daniſh Books, of which the former cited before, entituled, <hi>Danmarcts oc Norgis fructbar Herlighed,</hi> the other <hi>Encomium Daniae;</hi> but they had better have paſs'd them by, unleſs it had made more for the honour of their Nation. For the former in this takes the Swedes part, and writes in expreſs words, that Ween, as to the ſecular Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, belongs to Schonen, unleſs the King in favour to one or other conſtitutes ſomething to the contrary: and the other makes Ween to be in the Biſhoprick of Sealand, which, as it makes not for the Danes, ſo the Swedes do not deny it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Arguments which the Danes would have prove that Ween doth belong to Sealand, which we have here laid down, that the World may ſee with what ſtrength and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs they maintain their Cauſe.<note place="margin">A Reply to the Daniſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the Swediſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the Daniſh Commiſſioners were thus wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, they were not diſencouraged, but brought their whole ſtrength and force to overthrow the Swedes Arguments, by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:191851:25"/>excepting to the firſt;<note place="margin">To the firſt.</note> that the Iſlands Jarſey and Garnſey are bordering nearer upon Normandy then England, and yet they do belong to England. But that caſe is quite another thing then ours, for thoſe Iſlands are Provinces of themſelves; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they were formerly appertenances to Normandy, but when that Countrey was in the hands of the French, thoſe Iſlands were united to the Kingdom of England upon a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular agreement. But ſeeing there can be no ſuch agreement produced concerning Ween, the Rule of the Law of Nations ſtands in full force and vertue.</p>
            <p>That which they excepted againſt the ſecond argument,<note place="margin">To the ſecond.</note> that Halland and Blecking were alwayes alienated as Schonen was, and yet are never the more parts of Schonen, is not true. For we know that Halland hath ſometimes been pawn'd <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> and by it ſelf, and ſometimes too hath been under the ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Swedes, when Schonen at the ſame time hath paid Allegiance to Denmark; the latter of which, the body of the Law of Sweden doth clearly witneſs. Now grant it be ſo, yet the caſe of Halland and Blecking is far different from this, for they are independent Provinces, and were never alienated as parts of another, as Ween was. Nay, though you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that Ween was ſo alienated with Schonen, and not as an appertinent to it, in regard Ween is ſpecifically and by name expreſs'd in the publique Inſtrument, made in the time of King <hi>Magnus,</hi> concerning the ſurrendry of Schonen, yet it will not at all advantage you: Inſomuch as in the very ſame Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Lyſtre is alſo named ſpecifically, which nevertheleſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all controverſie, and by the aſſent of the Danes themſelves was a part of Blecking, and now ſurrendred to Sweden with Blecking. And that naming of them in particular was onely for the greater caution, and more then neceſſary, which kinde of Clauſes whether they be put in or left out do no harm.</p>
            <p>Happily theſe two places were therefore ſpecially named, becauſe at that time Lyſtre was the moſt conſiderable Port of Blecking, and Ween defended the Port of Landſcron.</p>
            <p>Thereſore when this way would not take, the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:191851:26"/>tried another,<note place="margin">The Danes would have the Controverſie about Ween remitted to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrators, but the Swedes give reaſon why that ought not to be.</note> and would have this controverſie put to the judgement of Arbitrators, to whoſe award according to the agreements at Stetin, ſuch contentions, as aroſe of that kinde, uſe to be referred. But that is not the meaning of the Agreements at Stetin, for they do not ſubmit thoſe things, which belong to the execution of a Peace made to arbitration, but onely thoſe controverſies, which is times of Peace might happily ariſe between thoſe Northern Kingdoms. But this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Ween not coming into that number and account, there is no reaſon why it ſhould be bound up by the form of thoſe Agreements at Stetin. Beſides, the Swedes eaſily ſmelt out; that the Danes did deſire it to be put to arbitration for no other end, but by their ſeveral delayes to continue the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie to eternity, or at leaſt protract it for a long time, as we ſee it hapned in thoſe Differences in the Agreements of Stetin referred to Arbitrators, which after forty years and upward, to wit, in the thirteenth year of this Age, were buried, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly extirpated in the tranſaction of Siored. This was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they deſired the controverſie might be decided with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further circumſtances, adding ſome kinde of threats too, in caſe they ſhould little or nothing prevail with them with Reaſons and Arguments how efficacious ſoever. Yet, leſt the Danes ſhould have any juſt cauſe of complaint, the Swedes were willing to acquieſce; and would forbear to urge any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur the ſurrendry of the Iſalnd, ſo that they would make it appear, that the Iſland Ween was by publique Conſtitution joyned for ever to Sealand, before the Peace made at Roskild, or by the Rolls or Dooms-day Book of the Kingdom, that it was ſtill without any interruption adherent to Sealand. But the Danes produced not a tittle to that purpoſe, pretending that thoſe Rolls had been made uſe of and burnt, to make Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works at the Marriage of Prince <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fifth. At length after the moſt Serene his Majeſty of Denmark had himſelf made ſearch into the Records and Evidences of his Kingdom, and could finde nothing that could entitle Ween to Sealand, made an agreement with the French Ambaſſador, who (by reaſon the Engliſh Envoy extraordinary, during that controverſie, was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:191851:26"/>gone to Coppenhagen) was much employed in that Affair, that the Iſland Ween ſo often made mention of,<note place="margin">At laſt the Danes promiſe to grant Ween to the Swedes, but in a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way.</note> ſhould be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred as a part adherent to Schonen, and that Letters ſhould with all poſſible ſpeed, that could be, be delivered to the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of Sweden, by vertue of which the Inhabitants of Ween ſhould be paſſed over and granted to Schonen, and the Kingdom of Sweden. But when the Daniſh Commiſſioners afterwards put this Article upon that controverſie into wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they put the words thus; That Ween was granted to the Swedes, but not as part of Schonen, but onely to avoid enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and over and above; onely for this purpoſe, to leave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an occaſion hereafter to demand it again. Juſt ſo it was with the Letters they promiſed us, we could not get them of them, the Danes ſtill complaining, as often as we minded them of it, which was very often, that we ſhould have them after the Treaty was ended, having no regard that Ween was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and granted, not by force of the preſent Treaty, but of the Agreements at Roskild, and that it was immediately ſubject to the Juriſdiction of Sweden with Schonen, to which it belonged. But it is in vain to contend with them by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who never reſolv'd of any thing leſs, then to perform their promiſes. For whilſt the Swediſh Ambaſſadors expect the Danes Letters of ſurrendry, the King of Denmark himſelf enjoyns his Reſident in England,<note place="margin">Let. LL. MM.</note> Letter LL. MM. that he would uſe his endeavour to take an occaſion to perſwade his Highneſs the Lord Protector of England, that the Iſland Ween was wreſted from them very wrongfully; yet that he ſhould be very wary in his procede, leſt the Swediſh Miniſters Reſident there ſhould perceive any thing of it. So well indeed the Danes wiſh the Swedes, that they endeavour to render them odious to the whole World with falſe accuſations and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions.</p>
            <p>Nay, the perverſeneſs and wilfulneſs of the Danes reach'd into Norway, and the very borders of the North.<note place="margin">The like deceit and perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs uſed about the ſurrender of Rumſdhall in the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Trundheim.</note> For whereas the Juriſdiction of Nidroes, which commonly goes by the name of Trundheim, ought to be ſurrendred to the Swedes, Rumſdhall a little Lordſhip there, alwayes adjoyned to the Juriſdiction of Trundheim, and which the Daniſh Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:191851:27"/>themſelves at Roskild confeſs'd to be a part of it, was held out, and denied us by <hi>Wibe</hi> Governour of Trundheim. Indeed when the Swediſh Ambaſſadors firſt acquainted the Daniſh Commiſſioners with it, they would not believe, that the Governour dar'd do any ſuch thing, but when it appear'd to them, that the matter was really ſo, they made as if he did it meerly of his own head. But he that ſhall but curſorily look over the Copy of the Commiſſion, that he withheld it by, which the Danes at the inſtance of the Swedes ſhew'd at laſt in July, will eaſily perceive, that the Governor attempted it not without command.<note place="margin">Letter NN.</note> Letter NN.</p>
            <p>It will be worth while, to obſerve here a little at large the horrible villany of the Danes, that ſhew'd it ſelf in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For when the queſtion at Roskild about the ſurrendry of the Juriſdiction of Trundheim in ſatisfaction to the Swedes, was, what ought to come under that denomination, both ſides at laſt agreed on this,<note place="margin">As appeareth by the Swediſh Protocol.</note> 
               <hi>That by the Juriſdiction of Trundheim, all that is underſtood to be granted to the Swedes, that belongs to the Biſhoprick of Trundheim, unleſs what expreſly belongs to the Juriſdiction of Norland ſpecifically ſo called, and Wardhuſe,</hi> as the words of the Swediſh Protocol have it. And to avoid all doubts, that might be raiſed on this buſineſs, one of the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Miniſters dictated the very ſame words to the Daniſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters pen. But when the Swediſh Ambaſſadors being led upon good and weighty grounds, and taking eſpecial notice of the controverſie that was rais'd about Rumſdhall, would inſert in writing that peculiar Article concerning the apperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Juriſdiction of Trundheim, in a declarative Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, Letter OO,<note place="margin">Letter OO,</note> wherein, not onely all the places appertaining to it were ſpecifically expreſs'd, but the above-cited words of the Protocol alledged; then the Danes began to prick up their ears, and that they might lay aſide or ſuppreſs that Article, they pretended that it was to no purpoſe to make any further controverſie about this buſineſs, and that there was no need of any ſuch Declaration; beſides, that they had given command to the Governor of Trundheim, that he ſhould raiſe no doubts about the ſurrendry of that Lordſhip. Nevertheleſs, when the Ambaſſadors urg'd it, the Daniſh Commiſſioners anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:191851:27"/>that their demand was new, and that there was no ſuch thing in the words of the Protocol; that there never was any ſuch kinde of mention of the Biſhoprick of Trundheim, and that there were ſome Goods comprehended under thoſe words, neither belonging to the Juriſdiction of Norland ſpecifically ſo called, nor Wardhuſe, though lying in them, which were in no wiſe granted.</p>
            <p>The Swediſh Ambaſſadours were not a little moved with that anſwer, and the rather in that <hi>Gerſdorf</hi> High Steward of the Kingdom and others, which were preſent at the Treaties at Roskild, did both know and confeſs that thoſe were the formal words, which were made uſe of. Hence to clear themſelves of foul dealing, they deſired a Copy of the Daniſh Protocol, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no queſtion but they ſhould finde the ſame words there. Beſides, <hi>Cornelius Lerck</hi> went to one of the Ambaſſadors, who had been Regiſter at Roskild, and after diſcourſing ſeveral things about this buſineſs, ſaid, that he did not remember, that it was concluded at Roskild, that all that which appertains to the Biſhoprick of Trundheim, excepting that, which belongs to the Juriſdiction of Norland ſpecifically ſo called, and Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſe, was granted with the Juriſdiction of Trundheim. But after when the Ambaſſador opened the Protocol, he found theſe words written: <hi>By the Juriſdiction of Trundheim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Compared with the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh.</note> 
               <hi>all thoſe things are underſtood to be granted, which appertain to that Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, from which notwithſtanding thoſe are expreſly excepted, that belong to the Juriſdiction of Norland and Wardhuſe.</hi> Where a childe may perceive a notorious tautologie, and ſo a great fault, unleſs one will make his buſineſs to be underſtandingly mad. For, pray, what kinde of explication would that be: <hi>By the Juriſdiction of Trundheim is underſtood all that, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to that Juriſdiction:</hi> truly, a very ſilly one, or rather none at all; or how can the Juriſdiction of Norland and Wardhuſe be excepted from Trundheim, which never yet were comprehended under it? Whence it muſt neceſſarily follow, that the Biſhoprick of Trundheim was mentioned, in that thoſe two before-named Juriſdictions, excepted from the Grant, are ſubject to that Biſhoprick. But by whoſe negligence or falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it was, that in the place of Biſhoprick, the word Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:191851:28"/>was put into the Daniſh Protocol, is not proper now to enquire.</p>
            <p>But what ever this be, though in the mean time, to wit, in July there was newes come, that the Lordſhip of Rumſdhall was delivered up to the Swedes Deputies; yet the Danes did not reliſh it well, that the Swedes Ambaſſadors ſhould, as we ſaid before, put in writing the Article concerning the apperte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Juriſdiction of Trundheim; and that for no other reaſon, but that they might have hereafter an occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, either that that Juriſdiction was granted by miſtake, or wreſted away by violence. As it fell out in the caſe of thoſe two Pariſhes Idre and Jerne, into the poſſeſſion of which the Danes put the Swedes; as alſo of Jempterland and Herndahlen after the Peace in the Year 1645, and yet they were not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med lately to alledge, the injuſtice of taking them away as the cauſe of their War. You may eaſily collect, that we were to expect the ſame dealing in this too, from the words of <hi>Jonas Juul</hi> Envoy of the King of Denmark into Poland, ſpoken at Berlin, where he did confidently aſſert, that the Danes might eaſily take an advantage from the controverſie about Rumſd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, to make a new War upon the Swedes. But we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to groſſer matters yet.</p>
            <p>For if ever there were any thing,<note place="margin">Another cauſe of difference was the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom which the Danes uſed to take of the ſhips paſſing through the Sound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Sweden.</note> that for theſe ſeventy years and upwards hath embroil'd theſe neighboring people in a War, it was certainly that Cuſtom that the Danes uſe to take of thoſe ſhips that paſs through the Sound, the burthen of which the Swedes would never yet ſubmit to. <hi>Denmark</hi> hath had ſufficient experience of that to their great loſs, and eſpecially in the War made in 1643. which was undertaken principally, becauſe the Danes exacted Cuſtoms of the Swedes. But the Danes could never be ſo far mended by beating, as to deal more warily for the future.</p>
            <p>For though by the fourth Article of the Tranſaction at Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild it was agreed, that all the ſhips properly belonging to the Subjects of the Kingdom of Sweden, in what place ſoever they live,<note place="margin">Contrary to expreſs Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild.</note> ſo that they have with them their Paſſeports, called com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly <hi>Sea Brieff,</hi> which uſe to mention the Owner of the ſhips, ought to remain free with all the Lading in them from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:191851:28"/>all Cuſtom, Inquiſition, Search, and other ſuch kinde of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; they, which were the King of Denmarks Commiſſioners of the Cuſtomes in the Sound at Helſingore took no notice of it at all, but not onely exacted Cuſtoms of the ſhips belonging to Stetin and Stralſund, and of other Merchandize properly belonging to the Subjects of the Kingdom of Sweden in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merania and Liefland, but detained ſome of thoſe ſhips for ſome dayes time; inſomuch that onely in the moneth of May, as is well known, they broke this Priviledge eight times. Nay, the Danes were not aſham'd to exact Cuſtoms of the Wines that were allotted for his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Swedens Court, and his chief Miniſters, as appears to have been done on the 16. day of May at Helſingore. All which for brevity ſake we will adde in their order to this work, Letter PP.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> P P.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But when the Miniſters of Sweden objected to the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Daniſh Cuſtoms, that they had violated their Agreements; they anſwered, that they knew no other Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but thoſe of Bromſebroe; nor had they received any command to let the Swediſh ſhips paſs upon any other terms then formerly. Which excuſe, as they had often at other times made, they had the confidence to make yet again on the ſixth day of July; to be ſilent of other breaches of the Articles of Bromſebroe, confirm'd at Roskild, which they committed in this buſineſs lately after the Peace was made. Indeed they made reſtitution of ſome of thoſe things, they had wrongfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted,<note place="margin">Which the Danes took no care to put in execution.</note> but not of all, nor thoſe neither until they were urg'd by the Swediſh Ambaſſadors. But if the Danes had really intended to have ſtood to thoſe Agreements at Roskild, they would have taken greater care in an Affair of that difficulty. Nevertheleſs, as if it had been a ſlight matter they had in hand, the Daniſh Senators never gave ſo much as a Copy of the Agreements at Roskild to the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtoms, or any other direction how they ſhould uſe the Swedes ſhips for the future; but left the whole buſineſs to ſome old crafty Cuſtom-houſe Men, to the great injury both of the Swedes Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and the ſacred obſervancy of Agreements. What could any one now expect of the Danes for the future, that dar'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch kind of enormities, when the Swediſh Army was yet in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:191851:29"/>the bowels of their Kingdom, and his Majeſties Ambaſſadors ſtaied at Coppenhagen urging the concluſion of the Peace, and all thoſe Articles were freſh in their memory, which were lately made at Coppenhagen, upon weighing and conſidering of all circumſtances; ſo that it is ſo much the more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that the Danes ſhould be ſo negligent in ordering a matter of ſo great concernment. But it is probable that the Danes did it, in regard they were weary of the Tranſaction at Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild, and ſo made it their buſineſs to render themſelves guilty of the breach of it; and in caſe it ſhould not fall out ſome other way, they perſwaded themſelves, that this buſineſs would at laſt tire out the Swedes patience. For there is much in the meaning of the words of <hi>Peter Reetze,</hi> a Senator of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Denmark,<note place="margin">But rather ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med willing to make the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh freedom from paying Cuſtom, an occaſion of a future breach.</note> which he ſpake openly at Coppenhagen at a meeting of the Commiſſioners of either party; to wit, that there could be no hopes of a firm and laſting Peace between the Northern Kingdoms, as long as the moſt Serene, the king of Denmark ſhould make uſe of his Right in exacting the Cuſtom of the Sound, and the Swedes would pretend a Freedome there.</p>
            <p>In the eleventh Article of the Tranſaction at Roskild, they promiſe a reſtitution of thoſe three Swediſh ſhips, and of all the goods, with which they came laden from Portugal, which were taken and detained,<note place="margin">Nor did the Danes keep their promiſe in reſtoring Swediſh ſhips and goods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before the War proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> as we formerly ſaid, before the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming of the War, in the Sound. But the Danes us'd their old trick in this too, and firſt by frivolous exceptions did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to put off the performance of their promiſes, daring to affirm, that they onely promis'd to reſtore the ſhips, but not the goods they were loaded with. As if it were a thing likely, that one that covenants for the reſtitution of goods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him, did not intend that they ſhould be reſtored in the ſame condition they were in, and not ſpoiled and waſted or but part of them.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Swediſh Ambaſſadors urged the reſtitution of them that very time, when two of thoſe ſhips road at anchor in the Baltick ſea not far from Newburgh in Fuhnen, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that Count <hi>Wrangell</hi> high Admiral of the Kingdom, had upon thoſe coaſts mariners in readineſs, and ſuch things as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:191851:29"/>were neceſſary to repair the ſhips; but they could not prevail with them, till they were firſt brought to <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> where after many delayes they at laſt delivered them to a Swediſh Captain, but in ſuch a condition, that they could not ſtir from the Port of <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> for want of things neceſſary for ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping before the end of <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as for the merchandize and other goods which yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in their hands, in regard they could not reſtore them by reaſon of the ſcarcity of ſalt, and the other things, they made this agreement, that they ſhould pay in lieu of them 23000. Rixdollars, 17000 of which ſhould be paid at <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> the other at <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> to one of the Ambaſſadours, which his Majeſty ſhould eſpecially authorize to that purpoſe. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> and <hi>Klingeberg</hi> took the buſineſs upon them, both Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Councellors to the King of Denmark, the one as to his Mines, the other to his Admiralty, yet ſo as that they promiſed by Bills obligatory to pay the money, as if it were their own proper debt. And for their ſakes it was, that the payment of thoſe moneys, which was to have been made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> if the Swedes would have ſtood upon the ſtrictneſs of it, was deferred till a certain limited time.</p>
            <p>The firſt payment was fairly carried, and the 6000. Dollars paid at <hi>Coppenhagen;</hi> but as ſoon as the Letters of Exchange according to their Agreement were tendred at <hi>Hamburgh, Klingeberg</hi> began to put them off with delayes, and would not accept them, till he had received further intelligence, that they had given them a diſcharge at <hi>Coppenhagen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who cannot ſee that this is a meer pretence, when as no man is ſo abſurd to deſire to be diſcharged of a debt before payment, eſpecially when the time of payment is not till ſome weeks after. But doubtleſs <hi>Klingeberg</hi> did that by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his ſuperiours to gain time, and that they might in the mean while ſee to what place his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> would march his Army. Afterwards when he was called upon a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, the time for payment being come, he anſwered, that as Affairs ſtood, he could not pay any money for the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> without any the leaſt regard to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of payment of it as his own debt. Nay, if all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:191851:30"/>be rightly conſidered, it appears plainly enough, that <hi>Klingeberg</hi> upon this account would never have paid a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>We formerly ſhew'd what hopeful ſigns the Danes gave of their performing the Peace,<note place="margin">Nor did they ſend the 2000. Horſe-men which they were bound to ſend to the Swede.</note> when inſtead of 2000. Horſe-men, they ſent us but 936. never conſidering, that when they had performed that condition, the Swediſh Army was to be drawn off from <hi>Sealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore when the Swediſh Ambaſſadours deſired that thoſe Horſe men might be delivered to them with the greateſt expedition they could, the Daniſh Commiſſioners ſaid, they were not oblig'd to ſend them in any more. They ſaid further, that the Muſter-rolls, wherein the Souldiers were liſted, did ſhew, that thoſe three Regiments, which they delivered to them at firſt, did fully compleat the number that was allotted them. And thoſe were the Rolls that the Swediſh Deputies deſired ſo often without the leaſt effect when they firſt preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them,</p>
            <p>But that is a pittiful exception, and ſuch as none but the Danes would make uſe of; who think promiſes ſufficiently performed by ſuch idle ſcribling. For what profit could the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> reap, in that thoſe Regiments compleated the number at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> if he never receiv'd them? For it had been to little purpoſe for any one to have buſied himſelf about the getting again of ſuch Souldiers together, as uſe to have no puniſhment inflicted on them for diſobeying their commands, ſince it was impoſſible to continue thoſe men, that were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him in their duty. For it was well enough known, that of thoſe that ran away after they were delivered to us, there were above 200. onely out of the Troups of <hi>Axell <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rop</hi> that lay ſculking in <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> and other parts of <hi>Sealand</hi> as their Sanctuary, to ſpeak nothing of above 30. of them that were of the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> own Guard. The Swediſh Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours therefore at the inſtance of the Governour of <hi>Schonen</hi> acquainted <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rop</hi> with it,<note place="margin">Nor would they uſe means to let thoſe be recovered who ran away after they were ſent.</note> deſiring him that he would by publick authority enjoyn ſome to give all aid and aſſiſtance to the Swediſh Miniſters in the recovery of thoſe Renegado's, and bringing them to their colours: but then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rop</hi> began to make
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:191851:30"/>a long apology, and to inevigh againſt the looſe diſcipline of the Souldiery: that War now was a kinde of trade, and that they would have moſt ſouldiers where there was the greateſt hopes of booty; that he could force no man to follow the Army againſt his will, and that he would perform his duty but ill, that went upon compulſion: yet he would acquaint his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign with it, and ſee what his pleaſure was. But he never return'd any anſwer to this day, ſo that the Officer that was ſent by the Governour of <hi>Schonen</hi> for this purpoſe, who knew their names, and where they lay ſculking, was forc'd to come back without the leaſt thing done in it. But as by their ſilence we may eaſily argue their deniall of the requeſt; ſo in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs the Danes ſhow their extream injuſtice. For if he, which gives another power to raiſe ſouldiers in his Dominions, is by that very act bound, upon requeſt made to give his aſſiſtance, if any run away, for the apprehending of them; the Danes were much more oblig'd of their own accord to have forc'd thoſe ſouldiers, which they delivered to them, to their duty, if they had had the leaſt reſpect to friendſhip or neighbourhood. We need not abound in words. The Danes were not onely pleas'd that their Horſemen would not follow the Swediſh Camp, but did ſeem tacitely to command them to this deſerting us. For it is likely, that thoſe ſouldiers were not bound to the ſervice by oath, onely for this end, that in caſe there ſhould ariſe any ſcruple of conſcience about it, it might eaſily be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon remembrance, that they were as yet bound by oath to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nor free thoſe that were ſent, from the Oath of former Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance by Proclamation.</note> eſpecially in regard they were ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten call'd upon to diſcharge thoſe Horſe-men by publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation from their former allegiance, and ſtill put it off. But for all this, the Swediſh Ambaſſadours perſiſted ſtill in their often demands of the 1060. Horſe, which were wanting, but never received any other anſwer, but that it was impoſſible in the condition <hi>Denmark</hi> was then in, that ſo many compleat Horſe-men could be put in arms. But the Ambaſſadours that knew the contrary well enough, urg'd them further, yet withal being willing to reſt ſatisfied, if inſtead of thoſe thouſand Horſe, they would ſuddenly ſend them onely 500. Horſe, and a 1000. Muſquetiers. For his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:191851:31"/>thought this to be a leſſer burthen to the Danes, as he himſelf affirm'd to <hi>Owen Juul</hi> at <hi>Gothenburgh.</hi> But they inſtead of the 1000. Muſquetiers promiſed 500. Dragoons, who being drawn from the Plough to the Sword, could give us no great hopes of ſtaying long with their Colours. Upon which account when the Swedes refuſed them, the Danes promiſed that they would ſend command to <hi>Eberſtein</hi> Camp-maſter General to deliver thoſe 1000. Horſe without any further delay upon the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Swediſh Army out of Holſtein. But there was poiſon in the tail of it, and the Danes were in hopes, that if the Swediſh Army had once moved, they would not put a ſtop upon their march, though they ſhould not receive thoſe 1000. Horſe-men. When his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> therefore, who knew well enough that there were not ſo many Horſe-men in all the Regal Holſtein, had fully by his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours affirm'd the ſame to the Daniſh Miniſters, and preſs'd very urgently, that ſome might be choſe out of the Troups that were in <hi>Sealand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And when at laſt 500. Horſe-men were ſent, 100. of them left their Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lours, viz. ſuch as were Danes by birth.</note> when they ſaw no way to evade it, they ordered at laſt that <hi>Gyldenlow</hi> ſhould deliver him 500. Horſe-men in Jutland and Eberſtein, the reſt in Holſtein. <hi>Gyldenlow</hi> did his part firſt, yet in ſuch a manner, that before they were conducted from Colding to Kiele, above 100. of thoſe 500. Horſe left their Colours, to wit, all that were Danes by birth. Hence it is no wonder that his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> would not accept of any Dane amongſt the 600. that were yet to be delivered to him, becauſe it might very well be feared, that they were all well skill'd in the game of cheating the Swedes. But <hi>Eberſtein</hi> us'd more delayes, and at firſt ſignified to Count <hi>Wrangell</hi> by Letters, that he received a command from the King to deliver him 500. Dragoons not Troupers; but afterwards upon complaint made by the Swediſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to the Danes, after a ſecond command he preſented to them 300. Troupers; but for the moſt part ragged, and tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, and ill arm'd, which at firſt the Deputies of his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> would not accept of, chiefly becauſe the number al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted them was not compleated; but afterwards Generall <hi>Boddeker</hi> accepted of about 400. Horſe from <hi>Eberſtein,</hi> when they were offered him a ſecond time, not as making up
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:191851:31"/>the number, but becauſe he thought it policy by this means to weaken the Danes Forces, in caſe they ſhould prove our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But though the Daniſh Commiſſioners took much pains to perſwade the Swediſh Ambaſſadours, that there were not above 400. Troupers maintain'd in all <hi>Denmark,</hi> yet his moſt Serene Majeſty knew how groſly in this they went againſt the truth, as afterwards the event proved it, when about the entring of the Swediſh Army into <hi>Sealand,</hi> it plainly appeared that there were many more, then were to be delivered to his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning Priſoners, the 19.<note place="margin">It was agreed concerning Priſoners, all to be ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty without Ranſom.</note> Article of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild</hi> had made this proviſion, that immediately after the Peace made, all ſhould be ſet at liberty without any Ranſome.</p>
            <p>But as if the Danes thought it a thing commendable in them to put delayes on us, the Governour of the Caſtle of <hi>Bremer Vorden</hi> would not ſet at liberty the Swediſh Officers, that were priſoners with him, though urg'd to it again and again by the Counſell of State at <hi>Bremer Vorden,</hi> pretending, that he knew nothing of a Peace between the Northern Kingdoms; and granting it were ſo, that thoſe things, which the two Kingdoms had joyntly ordered, did not concern him; that he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged no other power, but from his Majeſty of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and that he could not ſet his Priſoners at liberty,<note place="margin">But the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Bremer Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> did not obſerve this agreement.</note> till he received a command from his Majeſty to that purpoſe. At laſt when the Swediſh Ambaſſadours ſhew'd the Daniſh Commiſſioners the injuſtice of this action, eſpecially in regard the Swedes had been ſo forward in this point, they were diſmiſs'd by the Kings command, but long after the time appointed for it. This is an argument of vaſt negligence in the Danes, that they, as if it were a May game ſhould not in due time ſignifie to their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters what duty laid upon them to the execution of the late made Peace.</p>
            <p>Juſt ſo, when the foreſaid Governour of the Caſtle of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-Vorden</hi> had warning,<note place="margin">Nor did he deliver up the Caſtle at the time appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> that his time of quitting of it was near, not onely complained as formerly, that he had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for it, but beſides took care for all kinde of grain and proviſion, as if it were to keep out a long ſiege, ſparing no
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:191851:32"/>coſts, and much at his own charge too, though otherwiſe a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry penurious man. And, as if he had been afraid that he ſhould not raiſe ſuſpicions bad enough, he gave further cauſe of ſuſpicion by his ambiguous ſpeeches and words of doubtful meaning: ſaying, That there was no neceſſity for him to quit the Caſtle; that by reaſon he had been uſed to the Wars, he was unwilling to leave them off; and if happily the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> were weary of the War,<note place="margin">But ſeemed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to keep it by force.</note> yet that there were other Kings and Princes, for whoſe ſervice he might keep that Caſtle, and ſuch other like high and vaunting ſpeeches, which his pride was not aſhamed to belch out.</p>
            <p>But who that knows the Danes genius never ſo little, would not from thence conjecture all things to the worſt, eſpecially in that the Swediſh Ambaſſadours, when they urg'd the reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the foreſaid Caſtle at the Daniſh Court, had this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the Governour had ſtrict command without any the leaſt delay or ſhifting to quit the Caſtle.<note place="margin">And that by the Kings command,</note> But the Governour ſtifly denied it; ſo that one might juſtly have made a queſtion whether of the two to believe in this caſe, the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners or the Governour, had he not produced Letters to juſtifie his proceedings to be by the Kings command.</p>
            <p>The Swedes upon this buſineſs began to ſuſpect them, and were the more confirmed in it; in that the Ambaſſador of the King of Hungary made a moſt ſolemn promiſe to one of the Daniſh Nobles at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> that upon condition they would not ſurrender up <hi>Bremer-Vorden</hi> to the Swedes,<note place="margin">And upon the offers made by the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the King of Hungary to man the place againſt the Swedes.</note> that he would get as many of the choiceſt ſouldiery of the King his Majeſty, to defend it and invade the Swedes, as they themſelves ſhould judge to be ſufficient to effect it. That they ſhould onely ſay with courage and reſolution, what they deſired, and that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they ſhould have a very powerful Army.</p>
            <p>Upon this his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> by his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours preſſed the ſurrendry of it the more urgently, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſmelling out that there was ſome miſchief a hatching, and the Danes deſigns contrary to their agreements appearing ſtill more and more, but they would have had prevailed but little on them, and been cheated with fair promiſes, and effected no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, had they not by his Majeſties command began to give
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:191851:32"/>out ſome threatning language, affirming to the Daniſh Commiſſioners faces,<note place="margin">At laſt being threatned with a ſiege, they gave it up two moneths after the time li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited.</note> that if they would not without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances ſurrender the Caſtle, that his Majeſty would by violence reduce the Governour to his obedience, and ſet down his Army before it. For this was that which made them deliver up the place to the Swedes Deputies, but yet it was not till July, above the ſpace of two moneths after the time limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</p>
            <p>Theſe things might eaſily have put a King of ſo generous a ſpirit, eſpecially when he found himſelf thus ſlighted and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to take up arms: but his Majeſty notwithſtanding this reſtrein'd his paſſion, promiſing himſelf that the Danes would be more juſt and chearfull in doing thoſe things that were behinde.</p>
            <p>But it is in vain to expect any juſtice from them, who think their affairs can never be well ſettled, if they be not ſupported by fraud and deceit.</p>
            <p>We have as full an example of this in the reſtitution of a ſmall ſhip of Norcoping,<note place="margin">Nor did they reſtore a ſhip taken by one of their pyrates before War denounced.</note> which a Daniſh Pyrate under com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the King of Poland, long before the War was denounced, brought to Coppenhagen laden with ſeveral ſorts of Merchandize. For though the King of Denmark himſelf promiſed in his Letters to the Magiſtrate of Lubeck, who made a complaint of it by his Deputy, becauſe theſe Swediſh ſhips were allotted for the payment of ſome Citizens of Lubeck, that he would not ſuffer any of his Subjects to exerciſe Pyracy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed; yet they could never get that reſtitution made, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Swediſh Ambaſſadors did often deſire the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice. Indeed after mocks and ſcorns, which the Citizens of Norcoping were ſubject to at Coppenhagen, they did at laſt promiſe a reſtitution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> Q Q.</note> Letter Q Q. but the Danes have not to this day performed the Article that was made thereupon, and which made part of the Declarative Receſs, Letter R R. ſhewing plain enough that they would perform nothing, onely give fair words.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> R R.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But what could one promiſe himſelf from ſuch kinde of Judges as theſe be, who, as the common report went at Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen, had themſelves been at the charge to ſet out and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:191851:33"/>arm that Pyrate ſhip? Notable aſſertors indeed of the Rights that belong to the Northern Kingdoms in the Baltick Sea, who think it no baſeneſs nor diſrepute in them, to gape after filthy lucre under a Commiſſion from the King of Poland, when as the King of Denmark himſelf grants him no power to War in the Baltick Sea.</p>
            <p>The Danes too, forſooth, uſed the ſame kinde of chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the reſtitution of thoſe things,<note place="margin">Nor did they reſtore that which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Count <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigſmark</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Peace made.</note> that were taken away by the Daniſh Soldiery from Count <hi>Konigſmark,</hi> and other Swediſh Officers, after the Peace made at Toſtrup; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Authors were well enough known, you might finde that the Danes had very happy wits to make excuſes. Amongſt which, this was none of the leaſt, that thoſe Soldiers, which had took that booty, knew not that the Peace was made. But this excuſe was none of the moſt ingenious, ſeeing that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, had it been really true and not aſſerted, could onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt them from puniſhment, for violating the Peace, but not from reſtitution of the Spoil, according to the tenour of the eleventh Article at Roskild. And to what purpoſe ſhould a Court of War be appointed,<note place="margin">Contrary to the eleventh Article of the Peace conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at Roskild.</note> to which the King of Denmark ſignified by his Letters that he would ſubmit this controverſie, when as they which had committed the ſpoil did neither deny the fact, nor fly for it; nor was the reſtitution deſired accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rules of Military Diſcipline, but the tenor of a Peace made. Yet notwithſtanding the Swediſh Ambaſſadors did very often inſtance it, and urg'd the reſtitution of thoſe things that were taken away, but could get nothing but Daniſh promiſes, which come to more then a meer cheating of your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And that they might leave nothing unattempted,<note place="margin">Nor would they ſuffer the Swedes to take the Victuals and Corn which was their own ſtore, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the 14 Article of their agreement.</note> that might tend to the avoiding of the Agreements, they prohibited the carrying away the Victuals and Corn which the Swediſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary had ſtored up in Alholm, a Juriſdiction of Laland, without any regard to the fourteenth Article, that affirms in expreſs words, that reſtitution ought to be made of theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Victuals and Proviſion excepted.</p>
            <p>In like ſort there were very many of the Senators of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, who by vertue of the Peace made, were to be bound by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:191851:33"/>Oath to the moſt Serene the King of Sweden,<note place="margin">Nor were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators of Schonen diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of their Oaths by the Dane, though they ſued for a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge</note> that could not prevail with the Daniſh Court, that they might be diſcharged from the Employments and Offices, which they had hitherto adminiſtred. And ſome of them were at laſt ſo wearied out with ſhifts ſometimes of one ſort, ſometimes of another, that one may ſay juſtly enough, they were hindered from perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Oath to the Swedes: but others of them out of an hope of a change, which they ſaw was not far off, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do it, becauſe they believ'd they muſt ere long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it.</p>
            <p>Afterwards too, when this Serene Majeſty of Sweden was made acquainted, that one <hi>Henry Carloffe</hi> an Adventurer,<note place="margin">Nor did the Danes obſerve the eleventh Article of the Treaty at Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Company of Sweden, in the Caſe of <hi>Henry Carloffe</hi>
               </note> and formerly one of the Governors of the African Company in Sweden, by reaſon of an injury, as he conſtrued it, done to him by the Swediſh Governors, becauſe he had us'd a private trade in the coaſts of Guine, directly contrary to the Priviledges of that Company, and his Faith engag'd thereto, had not onely privately tranſported his whole Family from Hamburgh to Embden; but that he might the more infeſt and dammage the foreſaid Swediſh Company, without any regard to his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the ſecurity he had given, had got himſelf in the time of the War a Commiſſion from the King of Denmark, and to that purpoſe about the middle of Autumn 1657. weigh'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor from Embden, and went with a ſhip arm'd and well-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Guine; his Majeſty upon a fitting and ſubmiſſive deſire of the Sharers of the ſaid Company, could not out of his ſingular clemency ſuffer, that the ſafety of his faithful Subjects, as much as was concern'd in this buſineſs, ſhould be put to an hazard in the Treaties at Roskild, but rather ſeriouſly enjoyn'd his Commiſſioners, that were appointed for that Tranſaction, to provide the beſt they could for the profit and intereſs of that Company.</p>
            <p>But in regard no man could ſo much as dream, that the Danes ſhould uſe any difficulty in granting the particulars, when they allow'd of the general; nor was there any certainty as yet, at the time the Treaty was concluded, whether <hi>Carloffe</hi> had done any dammage in Guine: the Commiſſioners of his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden thought it ſufficient, as it had
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:191851:34"/>really been ſufficient, had they not had to do with cavillers, that that caution deſired by the Members of the African Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in Sweden, ſhould be made in general terms for every caſe, and put into the eleventh Article of the Inſtrument of Peace, in this form: to wit, <hi>That all thoſe Prizes which might have been taken by vertue of Commiſſions given, but were not brought into Ports before the Tranſaction of</hi> Toſtrup, <hi>ſhould be reſtored to their true and lawful Owners.</hi> For theſe words being ſo general, do not onely comprehed this caſe of Guine, but can be underſtood of no other, in that during the War, no Prize could be taken either in the German or Baltick Sea, which was not brought into a Swediſh or Daniſh Harbour before the Tranſaction at Toſtrup made in February, becauſe at that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Year there is no ſailing at all in theſe Northerne Countreys, in regard the cold is ſo great, that the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is frozen over. Wherefore theſe words are principally to be applyed to thoſe Prizes, which during the War, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before the compoſition might have been taken, but by reaſon of the great diſtance of the place, could not be brought into Harbor, where they ought to be adjudged. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Swedes had never ſtarted any doubt about the genuine ſenſe of thoſe words alledged, had they not been ſufficiently taught by ſo many Arguments and Trials, that the Danes did watch after all occaſions, whereby by falſe and far-fetched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations, they might free themſelves from thoſe things they were oblig'd to perform by vertue of the Inſtrument of Peace. Therefore the Swediſh Ambaſſadors, that they might timely prevent any miſchief about the true underſtanding of the eleventh Article, as much of it as belonged to the African Company, asked of the Daniſh Commiſſioners at a meeting had at Coppenhagen in April, whether the words above-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſpeaking of the Prizes taken under Commiſſion from the Dane, were ſo to be underſtood, that this caſe might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under them, if happily contrary to hope any dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſhould be done to the African Company in Sweden by a private man, that ſhould make Prize under Commiſſion from the King of Denmark; to which the Danes anſwer was ſimply Affirmative, alledging that not onely this, but all other caſes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:191851:34"/>whatſoever were comprehended under thoſe general words. But afterward when for the better caution, the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors would put the caſe in an Article, and inſert it amongſt other Points, that were to be explained in the Project of an additional Receſs, the Danes ſought out ſeveral wayes to ſhift it off, and evade it, pretending in this as in many other points, that there was no need of any Declaration, for his Majeſty of Denmark was very ready to do all that he was oblig'd to by vertue of the Agreements at Roskild, if in caſe any dammage was done to the African Company, contrary to the Inſtrument of Peace.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs the Swediſh Ambaſſadors ſtill urg'd it, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after they had received certain intelligence, that <hi>Carloffe</hi> was gone up from Guine to the River of Elbe with a great prize, having ſeized upon all the Swedes Forts there, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Governour of them along with him Priſoner to <hi>Gluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad;</hi> and that he himſelf was fled with the beſt part of the gold, and other merchandiſe of great value, which he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in Guine, and made ſome alteration in the Article which they had drawn, fitting it more expreſly to the preſent caſe, as will appear,<note place="margin">Letter SS.</note> if you look into the Letters <hi>S</hi> S.</p>
            <p>The Danes ſtriv'd to acquit themſelves from the obligation of the reſtitution they were bound to by reaſon <hi>Carloffe</hi> was fled; but this was but a vain plea, in regard the moſt Serene the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> and his Miniſters having had timely notice of it, ſhould have uſed all their endeavour to ſtop him from get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away to the damage and prejudice of others. For the Miniſter Reſident at <hi>Hamburgh</hi> did in the name of his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as ſoon as ever he heard that the ſhip was gone up the River of <hi>Elbe,</hi> by a Secretary, whom he had ſent away to <hi>Gluckſtad</hi> to that purpoſe, earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not onely of the Counſel of the Government there, but of Field Marſhal <hi>Eberſtein</hi> that they would detein and ſecure the foreſaid <hi>Carloffe</hi> with all the goods he had brought with him, to the end that reſtitution might be the better made, according to the tenor of the agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> not onely of the Caſtle of <hi>Capo-Cors,</hi> but of all other the Swedes Forts in the Coaſts of <hi>Guine,</hi> as alſo the ſhip and moveable goods taken
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:191851:35"/>away from the ſaid Company. But all this pains was taken to no purpoſe, as the relation of Secretary <hi>Barſhene</hi> that was ſent from <hi>Hamburgh</hi> to <hi>Gluckstad</hi> hereunto annexed, Letter <hi>T T.</hi> doth more fully ſhow,<note place="margin">Letter T T.</note> with all the circumſtances of it. Upon this the Swediſh Ambaſſadours received command from his Majeſty being then at <hi>Flensburgh,</hi> not onely ſpeedily to make up that point that concerns the African Company, but further to urge,<note place="margin">Whereupon the Swede threatens not to march with his Army out of Denmark till the Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Company was ſatisfied.</note> that the Danes ſhould without any more delay make juſt ſatisfaction to the foreſaid company, or otherwiſe his Sacred Royal Majeſty would not march his Army out of <hi>Denmark;</hi> or if ſo be that reſtitution could not ſo ſoon be made, they ſhould take good and certain ſecurity before the removall of the Army for ſure and true payment, and reſtitution of theſe places they had ſeized at the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed.</p>
            <p>And indeed the Swedes had very great reaſon to look cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly in this affair, in regard that it was plain enough by their diſmiſſing of <hi>Carloffe,</hi> that the Danes never heartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to make reparations of the loſſes the faithfull ſubjects of <hi>Sweden</hi> had ſuſteined, eſpecially when there were ſo many ſeveral circumſtances beſides that might give the Swedes juſt cauſe to ſuſpect the Danes injuſtice and perverſeneſs in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. Amongſt which, this was none of the leaſt, that <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loffe</hi> was reported to have ſworn thoſe Souldiers, which he had placed in Garriſon in the Caſtles of <hi>Guine,</hi> not to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letter U U.</note> but himſelf, Letter <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> and he with the greateſt part of his prize had withdrawn himſelf from the Daniſh Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and put himſelf under the protection of another Lord. But the damage that the Swediſh Company ſuſteined, was valued to be above 300000. Rixdollars, beſides the Caſtle of <hi>Capo-Cors,</hi> and other Forts and Merchants houſes built and enjoyed by the Swedes, of all which reſtitution ought to have been made.</p>
            <p>This was ſhew'd the Danes, and the Swediſh Ambaſſadours did propound, to avoid for the future all diſſentions and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that might ariſe about the number and quantity of the moveable goods that were taken away, that a certain ſumme of money ſhould be agreed upon as juſt and equitable, which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:191851:35"/>the loſs ſuſteined by the Swediſh Company ſhould be rated at, from which ſhould be deducted what ever could here in <hi>Europe,</hi> or elſe there in <hi>Africk</hi> be reſtored <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> but yet according to the common rate that commodities did bear at that place and time, when the reſtitution ſhould be made. And thence it was, that the ſumme of 400000. Rixdollars was put in the foreſaid Swediſh Project, not that the Swediſh Ambaſſadours would rigidly and peremptorily ſtick upon that ſumme, but as a ſumme of which ſomething might be agreed on or remitted, as was ſhew'd and told to the French Ambaſſadour, as ſoon as the Project was firſt mentioned. Nor could they juſtly be found fault withal, in that they deſired real ſecurity upon pawn given, it being a thing cuſtomary and uſuall betwixt Princes, and chiefly done for that end, that the debtour may be the ſtronglier bound to pay his debt, and redeem his pawn. Nor could that giving of pawn be any damage to the Danes, had they reſolv'd to pay the moneys they promis'd without any fraud at the time appointed, becauſe it was in the Danes power to make over ſuch goods in ſecurity to the Swedes, as might be appointed to them according to the commodity of their ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and where there were no places of defence.</p>
            <p>But how juſt ſoever the things were that were deſired, they reliſhed not well with the Danes, whoſe whole labour was to avoid and ſhift themſelves off from that buſineſs by waſting time, not conſidering what they had ſo roundly confeſs'd in the name of the moſt Serene the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> concerning the genuine ſenſe of the Eleventh Article of the agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> but making uſe of theſe reaſons following: and firſt,<note place="margin">The Danes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge reaſons why no reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution is to be made to the Guine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of that which <hi>H. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loffe</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> that they could pretend no right to thoſe goods that were taken away in <hi>Guine,</hi> in regard it is certain, that they were brought into Port before the pacification of Toſtrup, perſwading themſelves that a Port in Africk in this caſe was equivalent to a Port of Denmark; and that therefore no doubt or controverſie ought to be made about the Danes poſſeſſion of thoſe things they had taken away, though they were brought to Denmark, or to Holſtein after the Tranſaction at Toſtrup, no more then the Danes could pretend a right to the ſhip cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Delmenhorſt,</hi> which was ſeized by Count <hi>Wrangel</hi> high Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:191851:36"/>of <hi>Denmark</hi> not far from <hi>Corſoer</hi> in a Daniſh Port, but could not be brought to a Swediſh Port before the tranſaction at <hi>Toſtrup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Daniſh Commiſſioners further urg'd, that they were bound by vertue of the Fourteenth Article of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> to make reſtitution of nothing but onely the Forts in <hi>Guine,</hi> in regard all other things remaining there, as guns, ſhips, gold, and other merchandize were to be accounted move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables, which in a Continent and a Port, were by the right of War, together with the Fort yielded up, and in the power of the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, They endeavored to aſſert, that <hi>Carloffe</hi> was not to be accounted ſuch a man, as onely takes prize by a private Commiſſion, but a real Officer of War of the King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark's, lawfully authorized and expreſly commanded to ſeize upon the foreſaid places, and to bring away their merchandize for the ſervice of the King of Denmark.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They ſaid that according to the clauſe of the Eleventh Article of the Agreements at Roskild, Reſtitution ought not to be made of thoſe Goods that <hi>Carloffe</hi> in the name of the King of Denmark took away in the Continent, or in the Port, becauſe there is onely mention made of ſuch Goods as might have been taken by thoſe that had a publick Commiſſion and fought in the Kings ſervice in the open Sea, as the word Prize ſhewes, which muſt onely be underſtood of Ships, and cannot be extended to ſuch things as are taken away in the Continent, and therefore that thoſe things, which <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loffe</hi> had done, were not to be accounted among them.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide the Swediſh Ambaſſadors did produce more and clearer arguments,<note place="margin">The Swediſh reply to thoſe Arguments.</note> to ſhow that the pretence, which they made to thoſe Goods that were taken and ſeized in the time of War at Guine, had not it's foundation ſo much in the difference, which according to common acceptation might be one thing in an Officer of War, and another thing in him that ſets out a Ship at his own charge, and makes prize onely by vertue of a publick Commiſſion, as in the expreſs agreement made in this buſineſs at Roskild. For as exceptions would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe Lawes, and ſet up a new Rule, according to which, thoſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:191851:36"/>things that are agreed on, muſt be guided: ſo in this caſe we ought rather to conſider what both parties agreed on in this buſineſs, then that which commonly in the like caſe uſe to be kept and obſerv'd amongſt others, eſpecially if the thing be not ſpecifically determined.</p>
            <p>That every one knows well enough, that the Peace made with the enemies, is reſtreined onely to <hi>Europe,</hi> and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to other places ſcituate out of it, as the Spaniards once anſwered the Engliſh; nay, that during the while the Treaties for a twelve years Truce betwixt the Spaniard and States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral laſted, the Equinoctial Line was propoſed as the limit and boundary, within which the Peace and Truce was of full force and vertue; but on the other ſide of it the War was ſtill to be continued. The very ſame caſe, if approved by either party, would be this, that ſome places in regard of their ſcituation, though ſubject to the juriſdiction of one and the ſame Lord, ſhould by a particular agreement be annoyed and infeſted with War, whileſt others under the ſame Lord ſhould enjoy a quiet Peace; which Peace nevertheleſs had there not been a previous agreement, and had Peace been ſimply concluded, ought to have been extended to all places without any difference. In like manner if there were no difference made in the Treaties between the moveable goods and immoveable goods that were ſeized, all then would come under the ſame law, as much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns reſtitution, although in our caſe there was a peculiar and an expreſs covenant, as we ſhall hereafter more at large prove. If therefore a diſtinction might be made betwixt places, as was above ſaid, and alſo betwixt goods moveable and immoveable taken in the time of the War, why not betwixt perſons too, that had ſeized any thing during the War, as the Eleventh Article of the Agreeements at <hi>Roskild</hi> would clearly lay it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us.</p>
            <p>And truly that any unbiaſſed and unprejudiced man, that conſiders the ſaid Article, unleſſe he will purpoſely dote, ſhould fully and ſufficiently underſtand, that in it is eſtabliſhed firſt, that all immoveables, to wit, Provinces and Fortreſſes taken from the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden</hi> in the heat of the War, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſcituated, ſhould be reſtored to his Sacred Royal Majeſty
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:191851:37"/>of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Secondly, that reſtitution ſhould be made of all moveables taken from the Swediſh Subjects before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the War, as alſo of three ſhips laden with ſalt, and detein'd in the Sound, or the true value of them. Thirdly, that all moveables, which during the War might have been taken before the Tranſaction at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> by ſouldiers, and others that followed the Camp, and by ſuch as endamaged the enemy not onely as belonging to ſome company, but as main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at the charge of the Principal Officers, are plainly not liable to the reſtitution, by an argument <hi>à contrario,</hi> principally grounded on theſe words; <hi>What goods and moveables ſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides after that time, from the ſubjects of the one party, or of the other, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, That all moveables, whether ſhips, guns, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, and ſuch like, taken by vertue of Commiſſions by private men, who onely at their charge, and chiefly for their own proper benefit ſet out and furniſh ſhips to make prize, but brought into Port before the Pacification at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> ſhould likewiſe be free from reſtitution.</p>
            <p>But, fifthly, if any private man making Prize under publique Commiſſion, had taken away any thing by Sea or Land, and had not, before the Pacification compleated at <hi>Toſtrup,</hi> brought it in to ſuch a Port, where, according to the forme uſed amongſt the more civiliz'd Nations, it might be declar'd as lawful Prize according to the Lawes of the Admiralty, that that was to be reſtor'd to its lawful owner. Therefore that two things are principally requiſite, to make ſuch things as were taken away not liable to reſtitution; to wit, that they were not onely taking during the War, but brought into Port before the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. day of February, 1658. when the Pacification at <hi>Toſtrup</hi> was made. Nor that the Daniſh Commiſſioners, which were preſent at the Treaties at <hi>Roskild,</hi> could deny, that thoſe words, <hi>Of Prizes taken during the time of the Commiſſion, but not as yet brought into Ports,</hi> were added by the Swedes for the good and profit of the Subjects of his Sacred Royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and made uſe of onely for the caution and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the African Company of <hi>Sweden;</hi> and therefore ought in no wiſe to be fruſtrated and avoided, but according to Juſtice
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:191851:37"/>and Equity to ſtand in full force and vertue.</p>
            <p>Which if really ſo, as it cannot be otherwiſe, and that <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loffe</hi> cannot make himſelf out to be any other, then one that under Commiſſion from the Danes hath done dammage to the Swedes in Africk; nor hath not brought the greateſt part of his Prize to <hi>Gluckstad</hi> before June, to wit, ſome moneths after the time limitted; it neceſſarily follows, that the Danes, by vertue of the Pacification at <hi>Roskild,</hi> are bound to make real ſatisfaction to the Swediſh Company.</p>
            <p>For it is very certain that <hi>Carloffe</hi> had ſet on foot and acted this villany at the charge and hazard of himſelf and his complices; nor could the Danes prove with all their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, that he either received any money from the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> to arm and ſet out his ſhip, or that any of his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were bound in this action by Oath to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark;</hi> or laſtly, that they had the leaſt pay promiſed them. Whence it was, that the Daniſh Commiſſioners, though the Swediſh Ambaſſadors oftentimes deſired it, would not produce a copy of the Commiſſion and Inſtructions, that were given to <hi>Carloffe,</hi> becauſe they were afraid that the tenor of that would make it appear, that <hi>Carloffe</hi> was onely a private man, making Prize under publique Commiſſion, and no real Officer of War of the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi> But though the Swediſh Ambaſſadors were not ſo happy as to ſee that commiſſion, yet they could plainly collect, that <hi>Carloffe,</hi> in that he convey'd himſelf privately and by ſtealth from <hi>Gluckstad,</hi> and implor'd the aid and protection of other Commonwealths and States, did principally look at the benefit and profit of himſelf and his complices, and not of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark;</hi> and that the cauſe of his fear was, leſt the Danes ſhould deſert him in this buſineſs, and force him to perform the Agreements at <hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kild</hi> in that point. Unleſs you will rather ſay, that <hi>Carloffe</hi> fled by the command and advice of the Danes, becauſe they ſuppos'd, that by this means they might the eaſilier free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from making ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Swediſh Ambaſſadors put the Daniſh Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners in minde, that it was no new and unuſual thing, for thoſe that made Prize under a publique Commiſſion, to ſeize
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:191851:38"/>upon fortified places, and do dammage as well by Land as by Sea. That that was manifeſt enough from the actions of the Companies of the Eaſt and Weſt Indies in Holland, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their Traffique wag'd ſuch a kinde of War under a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Commiſſion, when as the Members of thoſe Companies, though ſome of them be of a Publique capacity are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered onely as private men in this buſineſs. Beſides that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doth teſtifie, that he that by vertue of a Commiſſion granted him, doth arm and furniſh out ſhips at his own charge againſt the Enemy, gets power likewiſe to injure his Enemy not onely at Sea, but at Land too, if he can. And that the Engliſh did that frequently in the former War with Spain.</p>
            <p>Nor can that word <hi>Prize,</hi> which is uſed in the foreſaid eleventh Article, be reſtreined onely to ſhips, or to that, which is taken at Sea, ſeeing rather by the general ſignification of it, it comprehends all kinde of booty whether by Sea or Land; and that in the French Tongue, whence it hath its original, it denotes booty, ſpoil, and every thing that is taken away from any enemy, nor can it be otherwiſe conſtrued or expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>That it is likewiſe nothing to the purpoſe, that the ſhip cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Stockholm-Caſtle, which lay at anchor not far from the Caſtle Capo-Cors, was as the Danes declare, brought to a Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Port from thoſe places after the Caſtle was won, before the Pacification; when as the word <hi>was brought,</hi> hath a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſignification here, and is to be underſtood according to the condition of the matter it ſpeaks of; to wit, in the ſame ſenſe, it uſeth to be taken and conſtrued in ſuch kinde of private expeditions and ventures, made by vertue of Commiſſions granted them, as we ſaid before. For who, pray, in Africk ſhould declare and adjudge, whether that ſhip and other moveable goods were taken juſtly, and according to the Rules of their Commiſſion, when there was none there empowered to it? Nor could <hi>Carloffe</hi> and his Complices do it, becauſe no man hath liberty to be judge in his own cauſe. Wherefore it follows upon neceſſity, that the Danes were not exempted from reſtitution, becauſe the Prize was brought before the Pacification at Toſtrup to an African Port; but it was further
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:191851:38"/>requiſite to make the poſſeſſion legal and ſafe, to bring thoſe goods, that were taken away, into a Daniſh Port. Beſides that that ſhip could not properly be ſaid to have been brought into a Daniſh Port in <hi>Africk,</hi> becauſe it lay there before; nor could the other merchandize or moveables, which were found in the Caſtle <hi>Capo-Cors,</hi> and ſeized together with it, be accounted to be brought thither by <hi>Carloffe,</hi> in as much as they were there before, and were onely by him carried away from thence.</p>
            <p>But that the Daniſh Commiſſioners were quite beſides the cuſhion, in comparing the ſhip <hi>Delmenhorſt</hi> that was ſeized upon not far from <hi>Corſoer,</hi> with this buſineſs of <hi>Guine,</hi> ſeeing that foreſaid Man of War taken in the time of the War by the Souldiers of his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> hath nothing at all of the caſe of a Pyrate Ship, that private men which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving right to fight by vertue of Commiſſions they have got granted, uſe to ſet forth for their own profit, but that buſineſs is rather to be guided by the rule of the often mentioned Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Article, by vertue of which the ſhip <hi>Delmenhorſt</hi> might juſtly be kept by the Swedes, though it was not brought into another Swediſh Port before the concluſion of the Peace; but the Prize that was made in <hi>Guine</hi> by one that had a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not brought into a Daniſh Port before the Pacifiation, ought by all Law to be reſtored.</p>
            <p>That it was to no purpoſe too, to alledge the Fourteenth Article of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild</hi> in this buſineſs, which did not at all belong to it, and ſpoke onely of the Forts and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, that were either ſeized by the Armies here in <hi>Europe,</hi> or were to be ſurrendred by the Pacification at <hi>Roskild</hi> in ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden,</hi> becauſe they were to be delivered naked, without Guns or any Ammunition or Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as may be ſeen from the context of the Fourteenth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and eſpecially in that, which was ordered about the end of that Article: to wit, <hi>That the Bores of thoſe Juriſdictions, in which thoſe Forts are ſcituated, are bound to carry all their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ammunition and Proviſion to the ſhore, that they might the more conveniently be ſhip'd and carried away,</hi> a thing nothing at all applicable to this caſe of <hi>Guine:</hi> But that the natural place, to which this buſineſs related, was in the foreſaid Eleventh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:191851:39"/>where firſt it was generally ordered, that all Provinces and Places ſeized upon in the time of the War, and taken from the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden, whereſoever they were ſcituated,</hi> ſhould be reſtored; and afterwards there was ſpecial proviſion made about goods moveable, to this purpoſe, that all thoſe Prizes (amongſt which thoſe alſo are legally comprehended, which were taken from the Swediſh Subjects in the Caſtle <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po-Cors</hi> and the Coaſts of <hi>Guine</hi>) which might have been taken by Commiſſions gained, but not brought into Port by the time limited, ſhould be reſtored again, as we ſhew'd you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to their lawful Proprietors.</p>
            <p>At laſt when the Daniſh Commiſſioners had nothing of weight or moment that they could reply againſt thoſe reaſons that were alledged, and the Swediſh Ambaſſadors did preſſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urge as well themſelves, as by <hi>Monſieur Terlon</hi> the French Ambaſſadour, their abſolute and poſitive anſwer, they made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to their uſual ſhifts; and that they might delay time, and avoid and elude the execution of the Peace,<note place="margin">The Danes ſeek to refer the buſineſs to Arbitrators.</note> ſaid, that it was but equitable, that that controverſie, according to the cuſtom brought in and approv'd on in the Agreements at <hi>Stetin,</hi> ſhould be compoſed by ſome Arbitrators choſen to that purpoſe, in regard they verily believed, that both parties were furniſhed with good reaſons to render the thing plain to them.</p>
            <p>But the Swediſh Ambaſſadours, as they had formerly about the Iſland <hi>Ween,</hi> ſo in this buſineſs alſo upon good grounds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it, proving by very ſtrong arguments, that this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie did depend upon the execution of the Peace lately made,<note place="margin">But the Swedes refuſe this.</note> and was not ſuch as aroſe anew between thoſe Northern King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms after the Peace was allotted for execution, or was in the pacification it ſelf devolv'd and caſt upon the judgement of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrators, and therefore was not of that nature and condition, as that it ought, according to the tenour of the Agreements at <hi>Stetin,</hi> be decided by Arbitratours.</p>
            <p>Nay, his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> himſelf, who in the mean time went from <hi>Gothenburgh</hi> to <hi>Flensburgh,</hi> and wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing more, then that the Executive Treaties at <hi>Coppenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> might ſpeedily come to an happy iſſue, and earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, without the trial of further controverſies with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:191851:39"/>of <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The King of Sweden writes to the King of Denmark a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. Let. X X.</note> to march with his Army out of <hi>Jutland</hi> and <hi>Holſtein,</hi> to purſue with the greater force and efficacy the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he had intended in other plaees, to ſhew how heartily he reſpected that buſineſs of <hi>Guine,</hi> ſent Letters concerning it to the moſt Serene the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> Letter XX. enjoyning likewiſe his Ambaſſadours at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> that in the private audience they were to have of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> for this buſineſs, they would ſet before them the injuſtice of the Danes in this Affair and others concerning the executive Treaties, and that without any kinde of ſticking at it, they ſhould tell them openly and plainly,<note place="margin">And demands real caution for reſtitution before his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from Denmark.</note> that before he had received real caution or ſecurity for the undoubted payment of the moneys, and reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of thoſe places they had ſeized, that he neither could nor would march his Army out of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> becauſe he could not put the leaſt confidence in the bare words and promiſes of the Danes. All which things, though the Swediſh Ambaſſadours faithfully related and ſpoke openly, both to the moſt Serene the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> at the private Audience, and to his chief Miniſters at other meetings,<note place="margin">But the Danes are not indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to do their duty.</note> yet they could never move them to the performing of their duty in the obſervation of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed it cannot be denied, that the Danes made a ſhow in words, that they were willing to reſtore, all that ſhould be found at Gluckſtad of the Goods taken away in Guine, and to give ſatisfaction afterward for the reſt, that <hi>Carloffe</hi> had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily conveigh'd away with him, ſo that they would give them ſo much time,<note place="margin">Onely they promiſe in words ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in time,</note> as whileſt they might draw in <hi>Carloffe</hi> again to them, or bring him under their power; and when that was done, that without doubt, as they ſaid, the places taken in Africk ſhould be reſtored, aſſoon as ever a Ship could perform ſo long a voyage. But in the interim, before this reſtitution and payment was truly performed,<note place="margin">But would not hear of any real caution.</note> they would not hear a word of giving real caution or ſecurity, pretending that they were in no wiſe bound by the Agreements at Roskild to give any caution. And becauſe any one that ſides with neither party can eaſily perceive, how fooliſh and weak this reaſon is, we thought it ſcarcely worth while to trouble you farther with what the Danes were anſwered to it.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:191851:40"/>
            <p>Onely we cannot paſs by the ſtrange kinde of acting that is uſual with the Danes in this affair, that, when the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours did often deſire, and urge their abſolute and poſitive anſwer concerning the real caution they demanded, they would excuſe themſelves, that they could not pawn to the Swedes any Lands or immoveable Goods, but yet that they would promiſe them, that they would bring them ſome Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh Merchants,<note place="margin">Yet promiſe that Merchants ſhould take the debt upon them as their own.</note> that ſhould engage themſelves, to make good the ſatisfaction they deſired to the African Company, at the time prefix'd, as if it were their own proper Debt. Which, when the Swediſh Ambaſſadours upon new Inſtructions from his Majeſty, aſſented to, and were content with that ſecurity they had propoſed; then the Danes turn'd cake in the pan, and recanted their words,<note place="margin">Which when the Swedes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as a caution, the Danes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward recanted.</note> they had formerly ſpoke, about giving in that ſecurity in the preſence of the French and Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, pretending, that in the condition the Kingdom of Denmark was at that preſent in, and the lowneſs of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, they could not perſwade any Forreign Merchants to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake upon themſelves the payment of ſo great a ſum. The cauſe of this alteration doubtleſs was, that, in regard they had heard, that his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden was ready to march away with his Army, and that the Ambaſſadors of the Elector of Brandenburgh were gone from Flensburgh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effecting any thing, they would not believe, that he would for the buſineſs of Guine, which onely concerns ſome private perſons, put off that expedition, which he had reſolved on, much leſs wholly give it over.</p>
            <p>Afterward when the Danes were ſhow'd the unworthineſs of this action, and every one did verily believe, that the buſineſs would be done without any further delayes and pretences, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they would have no mercy neither on themſelves, nor of their Countrey-men in Jutland and Holſtein,<note place="margin">To decline an anſwer to the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, the Dane ſends his Ambaſſador to the Swediſh King.</note> who by reaſon of the ſtay of the Swediſh Army, occaſioned by the unſeaſonable and unneceſſary ſhiftings of the Danes, were under a very great oppreſſion: his moſt Serene Majeſty of Denmark inſtead of an anſwer, which he ſhould have given the Swediſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to their Propoſals, ſent away <hi>Owen Juul</hi> in an Embaſſy about the end of June to his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:191851:40"/>who amongſt other inſtructions carried Letters,<note place="margin">Let. Y Y.</note> Y Y. in which indeed he anſwered the fore-mentioned Letters of his Majeſty of Sweden, but in ſuch a manner, that it was apparent enough, that the Danes never intended to give full and juſt ſatisfaction to the African Company.</p>
            <p>The Swediſh Ambaſſadors perceiving it endeavoured but in vain to hinder that Embaſſy, and ſhow'd them both by Monſieur <hi>Terlon</hi> the French Ambaſſadour, who was then at Coppenhagen, and they themſelves declar'd more at large to the chief Miniſters of the Kingdom of Denmark, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual and unfitting a thing it would be, for the King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark to diſpatch an Embaſſy to his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden, for the tranſacting of that controverſie, concerning which the Swediſh Ambaſſadors Reſident at Coppenhagen, were empowered with very large Commiſſions, and had very lately as it were anew been by Letters Credential to the King of Denmark, appointed to finiſh that buſineſs; that they had done their duty, and not onely juſtly declar'd what they were commanded, and urg'd their anſwer, but expected it too almoſt every moment. That they themſelves,<note place="margin">Which the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to diſſwade, but in vain.</note> and all others of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that were skill'd in theſe affairs, could not but believe, that this Embaſſy was ſet on foot, onely to ſpend time, and in hope that his Majeſty of Sweden would hereafter be forc'd in the mean while to march his Army out of the Daniſh Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which if it ſhould ſo happen, the Danes would ſhow lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing at all of endeavour and good will, in making reparations to the African Company; but that they dare boldly affirm, that their hope would extreamly fail them, in as much as they certainly knew, that his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden, in regard he had ſeen them ſo full of ſhifts and changes, would not ſtir with his Army out of Jutland, before that whole affair were fully compleated. Beſides that they were afraid, that his Sacred Royal Majeſty would interpret that Meſſage to be but a meer eluſion and ſhifting off the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements, which might be the cauſe of great heart-burnings betwixt theſe Northern Kingdoms, to the great dammage and prejudice of the Danes.</p>
            <p>Yea, his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden himſelf did begin
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:191851:41"/>ſo far to ſuſpect the Danes prepoſterous manner of acting, that upon that ground,<note place="margin">And the King of Sweden re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents to the Daniſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors the injuſtice of the Daniſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, And urges his own Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors at Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen to diſpatch the buſineſs there. Letter ZZ.</note> he was pleas'd not onely to ſet out at large the extream injuſtice of the Danes to <hi>Owen Juul,</hi> at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, but ſent charge amongſt other things to his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors reſiding at Coppenhagen, to diſpatch the buſineſs of Guine, Letter ZZ.</p>
            <p>In the mean time all the while <hi>Juul</hi> was employ'd about that Embaſſy, in which there were ſome weeks ſpent, the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Commiſſioners would not give the Swediſh Ambaſſadors any meeting in Coppenhagen; and at ſuch times as they were called upon to it, which was very often, they anſwered, that they muſt firſt expect the return of <hi>Owen Juul.</hi> At laſt that they might not ſeem to do nothing, and upon the news that was brought, that the Poles and Auſtrians had laid cloſe ſiege to the City of Thoren,<note place="margin">The Danes hearing of the ſiege of Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,</note> that the King of Hungary was choſen Emperour of Germany, and that part of the Swediſh Army had already begun their march into Germany, they wreſted and refuſed almoſt all thoſe things, which the Commiſſioners themſelves before,<note place="margin">Begin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract all what they formerly had promiſed.</note> and principally <hi>Gerſdorff</hi> High Steward of the Kingdom had ſo often promiſed, about the ſatisfaction that was to be given to the African Company. For though before the departure of <hi>Owen Juul,</hi> this queſtion, to wit, whether the Danes were in juſtice bound to make ſatisfaction for the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage done at Guine, or no? was carried in the Affirmative, and that they were bound to make it; and onely this queſtion, how, to wit, whether ſatisfaction ought to be made for all things taken away from the Swediſh Company in Guine, or alſo, whether real caution was to be given for the greater cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of payment, or no? remained, which the Ambaſſadors and Commiſſioners of both parties were to diſcuſs; the Danes that lay at lurch and waited how the times would go, and when they might have occaſion to order their affairs as beſt pleas'd themſelves, took heart again, and not onely denied all other ſatisfaction,<note place="margin">Except onely the reſtitution of the Caſtle Capo-Cors.</note> except the reſtitution of the Caſtle of Capo-Cors onely, but would have the whole buſineſs referred to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Arbitrators.</p>
            <p>In order to which, the Daniſh Commiſſioners did by Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Terlon</hi> the French Ambaſſador deliver their Project to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:191851:41"/>the Swediſh Ambaſſadors, Let. AAA.<note place="margin">Let. <hi>AAA.</hi> And then give a new Project to the Swedes by the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of France.</note> which having no reaſon in it that was of any weight, or could put any fair gloſs of truth upon the Danes unjuſt purpoſe herein, except thoſe they had formerly brought, which had been ſo often confuted and exploded, his moſt Serene Majeſty upon ſudden notice of it, was caſt into ſuch an admiration, that he could not tell what he ought to expect in the future from ſuch unconſtant and fickle people</p>
            <p>But after that the Danes underſtood, partly from the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Owen Juul,</hi> and partly from the Letters of his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> that his Sacred Royal Majeſty would in this caſe remit nothing of the right of his faithful Subjects, they met with the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours again, and exhibited a Project the 17. day of July, Letter <hi>BBB.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let. BBB. And again an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Próject to the Swediſh Ambaſſadors by themſelves. But the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh not accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, offer to them another of their own. Let. CCC.</note> which was written ſo captiouſly and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guouſly, that under the ſhelter and refuge of it, the Danes had a liberty to defer their payment from day to day, and might finde divers pretences to raiſe doubts and controverſies whether it were to be paid or no. Whereupon the Swediſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours the very next day made another Project, in which there was more care taken and better caution for the certain payment of the money, Letter <hi>CCC.</hi> and ſent it to the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners.</p>
            <p>But the Danes were no better pleaſed with this, then with the former Swediſh Project, in regard that it did for the moſt part cut off all occaſions, which the Danes might in the future at their pleaſure lay hold on, to exempt and free themſelves from giving the ſatisfaction they had promiſed. But as the Danes never reſolv'd with themſelves heartily fully to ſatisfie the African Company in this point,<note place="margin">Which the Danes accept of.</note> ſo that could not be well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to them that oblig'd them to the Agreements at <hi>Roskild.</hi> Nay, that there might be a juſt cauſe of wonder at them,<note place="margin">And do not ſo much as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that which they had promiſed in their own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſo far as the Swedes did accept of it.</note> the Danes could not be brought to make reſtitution of that part of the African Prize that was at <hi>Gluckstad,</hi> which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves promiſed in their own Project, though they were often required to do it. For though they had time long enough granted them for to make reſtitution of thoſe things that were taken away, and they had beſides other means propoſed to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:191851:42"/>them, by which the Danes might better their condition, and the more eaſily bear with it, yet they could get nothing out of them but the foreſaid Project, what labour and induſtry ſoever the Swediſh Ambaſſadours uſed to minde the Danes of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <note place="margin">So that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the whole Treaty might be ſaid to have had an end in this buſineſs.</note> So that one may juſtly ſay, that the whole Treaty had an end in this buſineſs; and that it is left to the diſcuſſion of abler judgements, how little of thoſe things the Danes have volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily and willingly done, to which they were bound by the tye of conſcience and ſolemn agreements, and which they had ſo often oblig'd their faith to perform.</p>
            <p>There were,<note place="margin">Yet in more other things the Danes did fail.</note> beſides theſe we have formerly mentioned more things yet, by which one might ſufficiently enough perceive the unbounded deſire of the Danes to miſinterpret the Agreements, as thoſe things that were to be performed mutually in their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes at the Caſtles ſcituated on both ſides of the Sound,<note place="margin">As concerning the ſalutes of the Caſtles on both ſides of the Sound.</note> as alſo their giving notice, if happily any Fleet of War paſs'd through the Sound, and the moneys which uſe to be exacted of thoſe that ſail in the foreſaid Sea, to keep lights at night in the Watch-Tower; and ſuch other things of the like nature which came into diſpute. For when <hi>Schonen</hi> is granted with all the ſuperiority belonging to that Territory as well by Land as Sea to the Swedes, that is likewiſe preſum'd to be granted, that uſeth to belong and is proper to all the Caſtles and Forts adjacent to the Sea, as the honour of a ſalute to be given by the ſhips that paſs by. Nevertheleſs the Danes contended that that ſolemn ſalute was to be performed to the Caſtle of <hi>Crone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> by the Swediſh ſhips, yet ſo that the Daniſh ſhips were not bound to obſerve the ſame honour to the Caſtle of <hi>Helſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> This truly were to deny the Swedes the ſuperiority in <hi>Schonen,</hi> which the Danes arrogated to themſelves in <hi>Sealand,</hi> as if the Swedes had not the ſame right in their poſſeſſion of <hi>Schonen,</hi> as the Danes have in <hi>Sealand.</hi> From thence too it was, that the Danes after the Agreements at <hi>Roskild</hi> took the boldneſs to exact the giving of warning, if any Swediſh Fleet paſſed the Sound,<note place="margin">And the giving of warning when a Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Fleet did paſs the Sound</note> which the Agreements at <hi>Bromſebroe</hi> do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, little conſidering that there was a neceſſity of it onely then, when the Danes were Maſters of both ſides of the Strait. But becauſe the Swediſh Ambaſſadours made an Agreement
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:191851:42"/>with the Daniſh Commiſſioners about theſe buſineſſes, we think it more convenient to paſs them by in ſilence.</p>
            <p>But though it appears manifeſtly enough from thoſe things we have laid down before, that the Danes ſuffered nothing to be wanting in them that might adde any thing to the delaying the execution of the Peace; or, to ſpeak more truly,<note place="margin">Yet the Danes boldly accuſe the Swedes, as if they had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> partly by denying their promiſes, partly by ambiguous interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they betrayed themſelves to be in their hearts utterly againſt and averſe to the obſervation of the Agreements; yet they took the boldneſs to lay the guilt of that crime to the Swedes, delighting much to make them, whom nature had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be their neighbours, partakers of their crime. For when not long after the concluſion of the Peace, the Letters which the Daniſh Miniſters ſent to their King out of <hi>Germany,</hi> were intercepted and broke open in the Dukedom of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome Letters inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, which were directed to the Daniſh Court, and printed.</note> and part of them afterwards printed, without any regard that the moſt Serene the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had by his Letters patents fully granted ſecurity and free paſſage every where to all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Poſtes going and coming: then the Danes greedily catch'd at that occaſion to make complaints, that the Swedes in this had groſly violated their Covenants.</p>
            <p>But how irrational and groundleſs this was, will eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the full Narrative of the Fact: For thus the caſe ſtands. There came one out of <hi>Germany,</hi> a Servant,<note place="margin">Whereof a particular account is given.</note> as we found him to be afterwards, of ſome Daniſh Miniſter, who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his petition had got a Paſs at <hi>Gottorp</hi> from the moſt Serene the Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> this fellow was ſuſpected by his Highneſs <hi>Philip</hi> Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> General of the Swediſh Horſe, who had received intimation that there was one poſting into <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> with Letters from the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and Electour of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> containing in them plots and contrivances de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the more, in regard he would tell no body of what condition he was. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his foreſaid Highneſs Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> gave command to an Officer, who was Governour of <hi>Flensburgh</hi> to ſtop him in his paſſage there, and to enquire of him, who he was, whence he came, and what he carried with him. For he had two Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantles or Cloak-bags. There he betrayed his buſineſs by
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:191851:43"/>making doubtful anſwers, and ſuch as did not well hang toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and being ask'd what he carried in thoſe Portmantles, he ſaid that in one there was Letters, in the other things for him to wear. But becauſe they gave no credit to what the fellow ſaid, they look'd into one of them, in which he ſaid there was no Letters, where they found, contrary to what he had ſaid, inſtead of things to wear very many Letters, which afterwards being broken up at <hi>Fuhnen</hi> were ſent to his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> being then at <hi>Gothenburgh.</hi> His moſt Serene Majeſty, without whoſe privity and command all theſe things were done, having lighted upon thoſe Letters by chance, eſpecially ſeeing they were written at that time,<note place="margin">Shewing how the Auſtrians, Brandenbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Danes did correſpond againſt the Swede.</note> when as yet there were great enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties betwixt theſe Northern Kingdoms, was pleaſed to cauſe ſome of them to be printed, that the world might ſee what the Auſtrians and Brandenburgh had in their hearts, and what he could promiſe himſelf of ſuch an outſide friendſhip, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Beſides this not long before, it was given out both by Letters and Meſſengers from <hi>Denmark,</hi> that the moſt Serene the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had by reaſon the Forts were denied him in <hi>Schonen,</hi> gathered his Army together again, and proſcuted the War; ſo that from thence his Highneſs the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> who knew nothing of the compoſition but by reports, had cauſe ſufficient to detain the man. All which matters of import being well conſidered with their circumſtances, will very eaſily acquit the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> from the crime of violating the Peace, who onely granted ſafe paſſage to publick Curriers, but not to any one that came out of ſuſpected and enemies quarters, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing he never profeſs'd himſelf to be a Currier of the King of <hi>Denmarks,</hi> or of any of the Daniſh Miniſters, and had indeed got a Paſs of the moſt Serene the Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> but no other, then in the common form that they uſe to have, who go journeys.</p>
            <p>But there were not any contrivances of the Danes divulg'd,<note place="margin">That the Swedes did not divulge any Daniſh contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances made after the peace concluded.</note> which by the Peace lately made with the Swedes either were of no effect, or ought to be ſo, but of other enemies of <hi>Sweden,</hi> without any injury to the Nation of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much leſſe did the Swediſh Ambaſſadours urge any things
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:191851:43"/>that were new,<note place="margin">Nor did the Swediſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors urge any new thing, or not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Treaty at Roskild.</note> or that did not well agree with the Treaties at <hi>Roskild,</hi> but ſuch things indeed they did, as the Danes by their ſiniſter interpretations gave them an occaſion for, and which were thought to adde much weight to the better explaining of the Inſtrument of Peace.</p>
            <p>Which things upon that account his moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> laid open in April to <hi>Owen Juul,</hi> Ambaſſadour of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> at <hi>Gothenburgh,</hi> willing the ſame to be done by his Deputies, Let. <hi>DDD.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let. <hi>DDD.</hi>
               </note> to which purpoſe he ſent like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to his Ambaſſadours that reſided at <hi>Coppenhagen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unleſs they will call that new, which was treated on at <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen,</hi> about the making reſtitution of thoſe ſhips that were taken away in the time of the War from the Subjects of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> in lieu of thoſe that were ſeiz'd on in <hi>Fuhnen,</hi> and other Ports of <hi>Denmark.</hi> Sure that was for the advantage of the Danes, who for reſtoring of one received ten. To ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a mutual covenant, by vertue of which that ought to have been ſo performed.</p>
            <p>Nor can that Article of Oblivion be accounted new,<note place="margin">Nor could the Article of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted new.</note> which the Swediſh Ambaſſadours would have inſerted into an Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Receſs, in regard the Danes themſelves gave the occaſion of doing it, by making the Swedes guilty of violating the Peace, unleſs they had had a minde onely to lay aſide the old War, and leave behinde them the ſeeds that might raiſe a new one.</p>
            <p>Nor, laſtly, is it any new thing,<note place="margin">Nor that the Swedes to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did make warlike provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note> that the Swedes to free them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves from all kinde of ſuſpicion of the Danes, did get toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Forreign Soldiers, and made other kinde of Warlike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that might have been ſpared, ſeeing without that they could not obtain the end of the War, which is the ſecurity of the Kingdom of Sweden. The Danes themſelves complained almoſt every moment of the utter deſolation of their Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that they were wholly unable to undergo the charge of the War: ſure then it muſt be ſome very great reaſon, that could perſwade them to lay a greater burthen of oppreſſion upon thoſe Subjects that were already utterly exhauſted. And ſeeing there was no other Kingdom or Commonwealth except Sweden, againſt which the Danes had ſuch grudgings, as might break out into a War, it would be very hard for the Swedes to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:191851:44"/>promiſe themſelves ſecurity, whilſt the other was in arms.</p>
            <p>They were far more bitter yet, in upbraiding the Swedes for exceeding the limits of their Agreements,<note place="margin">Nor that the Subjects of Denmark were taxed by the Swedes after the pacification otherwiſe then juſtly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Agreements.</note> in that after the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification at <hi>Roskild,</hi> they did put the Subjects of the King of Denmark to pay the ſame Taxes and Contributions, as in the heat of the War. But all that is founded upon a falſe Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, and hath its original from a miſinterpretation of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of the Agreements at <hi>Roskild.</hi> For whereas that Article ſpeaks of a neceſſary maintenance of the Swediſh Army in the Dominions of the King of Denmark till the firſt day of May, the Danes putting a ſtrange kinde of ſenſe upon thoſe words, would have all ordinary Contributions, and what ever was commanded and promiſed before the concluſion of the Peace, either to redeem their Houſes from firing, or to bring in Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to ceaſe and be made void. Hereupon, preſently after the Swediſh Ambaſſadors came to Coppenhagen, as we intimated before, the Danes rais'd a controverſie about this buſineſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining that all that was done, was directly contrary to the Agreements at Roskild. And <hi>Owen Juul</hi> was in the ſame note too at Gothenburgh,<note place="margin">Let. EEE.</note> Let. EEE. in April, the ſame moneth that the King of Denmark ſent him.</p>
            <p>But who, pray, is ſo ignorant in Military affairs, that knows not, that an Army hath not all kinde of neceſſary maintenance, when they are ſupplied with meat and drink, but that there are more things requiſite; as the furniſhing them with money for Clothes, and Arms, and ſhoeing their Horſes, and things of that nature. And becauſe no King or Prince can maintain an Army in his own Kingdoms, Dominions, or Territories, with Victuals onely, it is not probable that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> would eaſe the Danes of that burthen, which in time of War is laid upon his own Subjects. Nor have the Danes deſerv'd ſo well of the Swedes, as that they ſhould reſpect them more then the faithful people and ſubjects of their own Countrey. It is well enough known, that after the late Peace made in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Soldiery had for almoſt two whole moneths, till the compleat execution of the Peace, not onely a ſupply of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but of Money too: which when the Swediſh Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners alledged as an example in this buſineſs of Roskild, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:191851:44"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian Skiel</hi> the Daniſh Plenipotentiary (for <hi>Gerſdorff</hi> high Steward of the Kingdome was ſick at that time) did at firſt thwart it; asking what difference there was betwixt the times of Peace and War, if there were no eaſe of their burthens? to which when he received this anſwer, that there was this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, That there was a time certain prefix'd for theſe Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, and that they were demanded without any hoſtility; at laſt he acquieſc'd and ſaid, If they could get Peace upon no other terms, they muſt bear it patiently. And that this was really ſo, the Danes themſelves, if they be honeſt men, cannot deny. The Swediſh Ambaſſadours put the foreſaid <hi>Skiel</hi> in minde of this at Coppenhagen, and did themſelves declare to <hi>Flemming,</hi> Preſident of their Military Affairs, that to be the explication of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article. To which the Swediſh Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties anſwers to the demands of <hi>Owen Juul</hi> at Gothenburgh do every where agree.</p>
            <p>But the cauſe of all the miſtake in this buſineſs, was,<note place="margin">Which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the 17. Article.</note> becauſe the Swediſh Commiſſioners giving credit to what the Danes ſaid, ſuffered this Article to be made up as well out of the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as the Swediſh Project. Whence it came to paſs, that thoſe things which were before clearly and diſtinctly propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, did now determine the buſineſs in ſome obſcurity. For there are principally three heads of that Article, of which the firſt preſcribes to the Soldiery, how they ought to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at their departure out of the Daniſh Provinces; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, what they were to expect in Fuhnen, Jutland, Holſtein, and other Countreys ſubject to the Kingdom of Denmark, till the firſt day of May; and laſtly, how they muſt proceed in Sealand, to wit, where they ſhould quarter, till the Sea were navigable. And as in their departure they were to commit no violence on the Subjects, ſo in Fuhnen, Laland, Jutland, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein, and other Territories of the Kingdom of Denmark, what ever was demanded, before the concluſion of the Peace, either of ordinary Contributions or to redeem their Houſes from firing, or laſtly to get their Proviſion together, ought, beſides the maintenance of the Army, to be performed without any delay until the time of quitting them. But the caſe of Sealand was otherwiſe, which did grant the Soldiers nothing beſides ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:191851:45"/>maintenance, as it ſhould be defined by Commiſſioners of either party. And this is the genuine meaning of this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Truly it can ſcarcely be denied that it was by the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of ſome Commiſſaries of War in ſome places, that, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they thought they had much time left, they did not in due time demand of the Inhabitants of Fuhnen and Laland the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution and moneys raiſed to prevent the firing of their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and other ſuch things as belong to their Proviſions, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the command they received from the moſt Serene the King of Denmark, before he went away into Sealand: But that negligence of theirs could not in ſuch a caſe at all hinder the Swedes right when they ſought it. Nevertheleſs his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> to make proof of his affection to the King of Denmark,<note place="margin">Yet the Swede did remit ſome thing of his Right, to eaſe the Danes.</note> at the inſtance of <hi>Owen Juul,</hi> remitted part of his right, and by publique Proclamation made at Gothen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, did moſt ſtrictly command the abolition of all monethly Contributions for the future, the day of payment of which was not yet paſt.</p>
            <p>As for the other inſolencies committed by the Soldiery which the Danes complained of; as no one can do any more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit them, ſo it is ſufficient, if thoſe that command them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict due puniſhment upon the Offenders.</p>
            <p>The third violation of the Agreements,<note place="margin">The third ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Swedes, that they went not out of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark about the beginning of May; anſwered</note> that they accuſe the Swedes of, was, that the Swediſh Army did not according to to their Covenant, go out of the Daniſh Dominions about the beginning of May. But this is a ſtrange kinde of impudence, to ſay nothing worſe, to demand of his Majeſty of Sweden that he ſhould quit the Provinces in the Dominion of the Kingdom of Denmark, before they had performed thoſe things, which are required to the execution of the Tranſaction at Roskild. For the acquitting of the Provinces is the laſt thing in point of time that ought to be executed, within which there ſhould be nothing left undone that was to be done by either of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties covenanting, but onely that which requires a permanent and continual Act. And, unleſs a plenary, and as to all things an abſolute execution of the Peace was performed before, there was no neceſſity for the quitting of the Forts and Provinces afterwards. Nay, if his Sacred Royal Majeſty of Sweden would
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:191851:45"/>have ſtood ſtrictly upon his right, he was not bound to draw his Army out of Sealand, in as much as the delivery of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe, according to the condition upon which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to quit it, was not yet performed. That one may juſtly ſay, that by this onely action, the Swedes deſerv'd very well of the Danes. Nor were they backward in ſhewing their readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in other things, as appears in their quitting of Laland, the city Nasko, Falſtre, Monen, and Langland, which were ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in their due time, and as ſoon as poſſibly they could; that any man might eaſily gather, that the Danes immediately after the Peace was made, did uſe all their endeavour to ſcrape up matter to make a new War on the Swedes.</p>
            <p>Neither are we here led by vain ſuſpicions,<note place="margin">Evidences that the Danes did not intend to continue in peace with the Swedes are ſet forth.</note> or rumours of the unſtable multitude; but by evident grounds and diſcoveries, ſuch as to all impartial judges will make undeniable proof, that the Danes purpoſed nothing leſs then Peace.</p>
            <p>For what could be in their end in charging his Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> with violating the Peace, in that he gave way that the moneys formerly leavied ſhould be got in, for the neceſſary ſupport of the ſouldiery, but onely that by a notorious miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction of the Covenants, they might rake together ſome matter of a new War.</p>
            <p>Or how could all that zeal and fervency to the ratifying of a perpetual confederacy with the Swedes, ſo ſuddenly have vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had it not been counterfeit and made to this very purpoſe, that by pretence of a League, they might diſcharge themſelves of the third Article of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi> and that they might continue their League made with the States of <hi>Holland</hi> to the prejudice of the Swedes? Why ſhould they have ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor'd to joyn their Fleet of War with that of the Sweds, but that they might thereby get a fair way wholly to defeat the Agreements at <hi>Roskild,</hi> when they ſhould be therefore accus'd of violating the Peace? Which Counſel was contriv'd by <hi>Beuningen,</hi> as he himſelf plainly took on him.</p>
            <p>What made them appear ſo wayward and averſe in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> complaining that heavier and heavier burthens were impoſed on them, then had been promiſed, but that they might after a while take occaſion to evacuate all the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:191851:46"/>
            <p>Why ſhould they refuſe to proceed to the promiſed diviſion of the Eccleſiaſtical Goods of the Chapter of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> before the departure of the Swediſh Army, although the Duke of <hi>Holſtein</hi> himſelf urg'd it, had they had any purpoſe to ſtand to their conditions? Why ſhould the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours in <hi>Holſtein,</hi> who ſaw evidently enough (though they pretend to have been dubious) that a Peace was on foot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Swedes and Danes, ſuggeſt to their King ſuch peſtilent Counſel, together with ſuch odious reproaches againſt the Swedes, but that they were aſſur'd they would be very grateful and acceptable?<note place="margin">Let. GGG.</note> Letter <hi>GGG.</hi> Why ſhould they, being, as they themſelves confeſs'd, in ſo neceſſitous a condition, go on to make new levies of ſouldiers? Or why did <hi>Roſewing</hi> by <hi>Gerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorffe</hi>'s warrant take care to ſecure <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> with a Garriſon of Dutch Souldiers, but that they were deviſing of a new War? Letter <hi>HHH.</hi> Why did they refuſe to bring in the Horſe they had promiſed,<note place="margin">Let. HHH.</note> pretending falſely they were not able, that they might be provided with ſufficient force to deal with the Swedes? Why did <hi>Owen Juul</hi> affirm himſelf to the King of Swedes at <hi>Gothenburgh,</hi> that the buſineſs of <hi>Holſtein</hi> was agreed, and <hi>Gyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlow</hi> the Lieutenant General at <hi>Flensburgh,</hi> that the African or Guine Controverſie was compounded, but that they might make him ſecure, and incite him to depart ere his buſineſs was diſpatched? Why did the Daniſh Commiſſioners appointed for the Executive Treaties at <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> never produce their Plenipotentiary Commiſſions? Why would they not bring a Regiſter, if they intended really, and were willing their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould be underſtood? Why did they themſelves retard the Treaties, if they were deſirous to bring them to iſſue? Why was not that committed to writing, which was ſuppos'd to be agreed on on all hands, but that they never intended it ſhould be binding to them? Why ſhould they refuſe on the morrow, what they had this day allowed, but that they would ſuſpend the execution of the Peace, as the circumſtances and change of time did either promiſe proſperity, or threaten ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity to the Swedes? What could be the reaſon they did not freely perform any one thing tending to the execution of the Peace, but that in time following they migt have this to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:191851:46"/>ſay, that all things were unjuſtly forc'd and extorted from them by compulſion and threats? It was not a talk of the vulgar, but a Maxime of the Peers of <hi>Denmark,</hi> that the Peace in hand betwixt the two Kingdoms could not be durable, that they were not bound by a contract occaſioned by force and fear; that thoſe Provinces were not alien'd but lent, and muſt ſhortly be rendred back with intereſt; that other States and Re-pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks would not adventure to let the Swedes eſtabliſh Monarchy in the North; that they would not want moſt powerful foes, whoſe united ſtrength they would be unable to reſiſt; that ſometimes there was ſcarce a moment paſs'd twixt great height and a down-fall; that the doubtful chance of War would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford opportunity of revenge when leaſt look'd for, with other diſcourſes of this kind, wherewith the Danes flattered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and cheriſhed thoſe hopes of regaining their loſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces with many more into the bargain. And <hi>Magnus Hoge</hi> himſelf Senatour of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> may eaſily call to minde that he caſt abroad the greateſt part of theſe ſpeeches.</p>
            <p>But this eager deſire of ſetting on the Swedes being ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted in the Danes, could not contain it ſelfe in words, breaking out ſo far, that before the Peace was yet come to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they endeavoured by moſt villanous plots and attempts to bring ſpeedy ruine on the King and Kingdom of <hi>Sweden.</hi> For whereas by the ſecond Article of the Agreement at <hi>Roskild,</hi> the Danes were oblig'd, not onely, that all Leagues and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants formerly made with any to the prejudice of the Swedes ſhould ceaſe, if any ſuch had been made, but alſo they ſhould not by any means enter into any ſuch for the future; they were ſo far from renouncing ſuch Leagues, that the Leagues, which were at the concluſion of the Peace but ſhapeleſs iſſues and imperfect embryo's, they have hitherto been licking into due form and perfection. Whereof the faithful communication of matters between the Hungarian and Poliſh Agents with the Daniſh Miniſters at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> may ſerve for abundant proof, if there were no other.</p>
            <p>For what commerce could the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who was afterwards Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> have with the King of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:191851:47"/>
               <hi>Denmark</hi> or againſt whom could they finde occaſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Leagues, but againſt the Swedes, whoſe ruine they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly conſpir'd, though in other reſpects they were very much divided. It was not for nothing the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> would have his Agent abide at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> but the hopes, which the Danes had given of a League to be ratified and moſt ſolemnly kept, was that which detained him there.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs of <hi>Morſtein</hi> is like this, who was ſent by the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſtayes there to this day, being fed with the ſame hopes. Hereof <hi>Beuningen</hi> gives teſtimony in his Letters, Let.<note place="margin">Let. III.</note> 
               <hi>III.</hi> where he affirms that <hi>Morſtein</hi> ſaid, that he ſtayed at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> waiting upon the iſſue of the Diet of <hi>Warſau,</hi> and if a Peace were there concluded with the Muſcovite, that he ſhould make ſome farther ſtay in <hi>Denmark,</hi> but if otherwiſe, he ſhould depart. Which, without queſtion, he ſpoke to this end, that he might evidence by his words and aſſeveration, how conſtant the King would be found to the League with the Dane againſt the Swedes, if not hindered by War with the Muſcovite.</p>
            <p>But the Tranſaction with the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> was carried more ſecretly, as if the Danes themſelves had been aſham'd to own their own malice; and it is certain that <hi>Berlin,</hi> the Miniſter ſent by the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> like one that durſt not ſhew his head, met the Elector by night, and declar'd to him the things he had in charge. Of which the ſcope was, that the King ſollicited the Electour to take up Arms againſt the Swedes, that they might be forc'd to quit <hi>Fuhnen, Jutland,</hi> and other Provinces of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and ſo leave room for the Danes to begin a new War.</p>
            <p>As to the united Provinces, <hi>Gerſdorffe</hi> high Steward of the Kingdom made a ſolemn promiſe immediately after the League was concluded, to their Ambaſſadour then Reſident at the Daniſh Court, that whatſoever they in their ſtreights and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities had promiſed, his King would never endure that any thing ſhould be perform'd, that was prejudicial to the League between the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and the ſaid United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, but rather he would preſerve inviolate all things that had been agreed on betwixt them. This <hi>Beuningen</hi> recounted
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:191851:47"/>in his Letters to the States, and in many other Letters of his, he hath with great pains publiſhed that inclination of the Danes to adhere to their League with them, and likewiſe how nothing at all was kept ſecret from him, that paſs'd between the Swediſh and Daniſh Commiſſioners in reference to the eſtabliſhing of a League, and that the King himſelf did not diſlike that they ſhould be ſecretly imparted to him.</p>
            <p>But what could the States alledge to be concluded to their prejudice (as they perverſely and without reaſon expound it) more then that main Article of the Treaty at Roskild, to wit, of prohibiting any Fleets of War to enter the Baltick Sea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of both the Kings. And this is the very Article, to the performance whereof, the Danes would not be oblig'd, though they had promiſed it.</p>
            <p>Should we further relate with what bent and eagerneſs they they have been contriving to ſlander the Swedes to other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and eſpecially to the moſt Serene His Highneſs the Lord Protector of great Brittain, and to convict them of breach of peace in requiring the Iſland of Ween, it would be an endleſs work. Thus indeed do the Danes heap bleſſings on the Swedes, promoting their good, and by all means diverting from them what might tend to their diſadvantage!</p>
            <p>And leſt Sweden ſhould want enemies, ſo great is their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to their reconciled friends, the King of Denmark hath recommended ſeveral Officers, by himſelf diſmiſſed, to the German Emperour and the Elector, who were then in open War againſt the Swedes.</p>
            <p>Now who can be ſo utterly void of judgement, as to caſt any blame on his moſt Serene Majeſtie of Sweden, in that he had regard to his own ſecurity, when the Peace agreed proved ſo unſtable; nor would depart with his Army, ere he had, what in him lay, clean weeded out theſe ancient ſeeds of diſcord in theſe Northerne Kingdoms. Which had been in great part effected, if the Executive Treaties had been concluded with a General Act of Oblivion of what ever was paſt. But the Daniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners could never be brought to put any ſuch thing in writing, it being eaſily diſcernable what they aimed at by their bankings and delayes</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:191851:48"/>
            <p>Since therefore the Danes have in effect violated every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Treaty at <hi>Roskild,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on recapitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the cauſe of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the War</note> as is clearly to be collected from what hath been alledged; namely the firſt, in plotting ſudden deſtruction to the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden</hi> by moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious counſells, expreſſing all good meaning to, and as much as in them lay, aſſiſting the implacable enemies of <hi>Sweden,</hi> ſtudying to enrage both their friends and foes againſt them: the ſecond likewiſe, in that they were ſo far from quitting their Leagues, formerly made to the Swedes prejudice, that they have made new ones to the like tendency: The third, In that they would not exclude a Forreign Fleet of War from the Baltick Sea: The fourth, In exacting Cuſtoms and other Charges from the Swediſh Ships in the Sound: The fifth, by complaining that the Iſle of Ween belonging to Schonen was wrongfully wreſted from them, contrary to right and juſtice; nor to this day have they fully delivered it up as they ought to do: The ſixth, In detaining certain Goods belonging to the Juriſdiction and Chapter of <hi>Trundheim.</hi> The eighth, In drawing very many of the Nobility in the Provinces yielded to the Swedes from obſerving their Oath. The eleventh, in not reſtoring three Swediſh ſhips with their Cargo's, as alſo other things taken from the Swede before the War was proclaimed, and in refuſing to ſatisfie the great depredations made by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loffe</hi> in <hi>Guine,</hi> and likewiſe the Goods taken from Count <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigſmark</hi> and others, by violence, although the very perſons that did it were well enough known. The fourteenth, In pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the carrying away the warlike proviſion that was laid in ſtore in <hi>Anholm,</hi> a Juriſdiction in Laland. The ſixteenth, In not compleating that promiſed ſupply of 2000. Horſe, nor quitting <hi>Bremer Vorden</hi> at the time limitted. The ſeventeenth, By endeavouring by ſundry diſputes and conteſtations to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave the Souldiery of their due maintenance, and ſo to make the Swedes guilty of breach of faith. The nineteenth, In not releaſing the perſons by the time prefix'd. And laſtly, in as much as they have in no wayes performed the private Article. His moſt Serene Majeſty was forc'd to betake himſelf again to his Arms, and ſince the Peace he had till then made, could ſcarce be term'd a Peace, the conditions and grounds thereof being
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:191851:48"/>very little obſerved, to continue the War he had begun, till the Senators of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſhould return to fairer carriage and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>For which reaſon alſo it was needleſs ſolemnly to denounce War, ſince the Danes knew right well what Peace-breakers were to expect; and that War muſt of neceſſity return, where the Peace ſolemnly made, through the Danes perverſeneſs could take no effect. Notwithſtanding the Swediſh Ambaſſadours were cautious enough that the matter ſhould not break out contrary to their juſt hope and expectation, not onely affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing openly to the Daniſh Miniſters, and eſpecially to <hi>Gerſdorffe</hi> high Steward of the Kingdom, that their Royal Majeſty would never paſs by their delays &amp; eluſions of Articles, but alſo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Letters written to the French Ambaſſador to that effect,<note place="margin">Let. KKK.</note> Let. <hi>KKK.</hi> that it was now altogether neceſſary to require from the Danes an abſolute and poſitive anſwer whether they meant to perform their Covenants, and to determine the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Treaties or no. Yea, to make it the more evident, that they meant it in earneſt, they ſhow'd the Kings Letters to the French Ambaſſadour, wherein it was ſaid expreſly, that his Majeſty was reſolv'd not to depart out of <hi>Denmark</hi> with his Army, till the buſineſs were fully concluded; and that if <hi>Pruſſia</hi> were loſt in the mean while, he would require reparation of the Danes. All which things were faithfully related by him, as the Letters of <hi>Beuningen</hi> do ſufficiently teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Surely it may hence be collected, how unwillingly his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> deſcended to thoſe extream remedies, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver omitted any thing which might in any ſort conduce to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate his readineſs and affection to a ſerious maintaining of an entire Peace between theſe two Northern Kingdoms.<note place="margin">Evidences of the King of Swedens boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to oblige the Danes to him to confirm the Peace.</note> For to ſay nothing of other expreſſions of his good affection, this muſt certainly proceed from a minde ſincerely ſtudious of Peace, that he freely granted to the Queen of <hi>Denmark</hi> the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of <hi>Hirſholme,</hi> which by vertue of the conditions ſhould have been reſtored to Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld,</hi> undertaking to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lfeld</hi> the like in value: that he beſtowed on <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lrick Frederick,</hi> the Kings Baſtard-ſon, the command of two Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and a conſiderable Penſion for his life; and that he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:191851:49"/>the Queen to enjoy the Rents of <hi>Ween</hi> during her life, they having been hers before.</p>
            <p>Indeed his Majeſty of <hi>Denmark</hi> had not onely laid aſide all rankor of ſpirit, but alſo all deſire of ruling over his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, which creep on men of generous mindes ſometimes againſt their wills, being contented with what he was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded might be ſufficient for his ſecurity. And that he might for ever bar all pretence to <hi>Denmark,</hi> he thought fit to aſſume the Title of <hi>Schonen,</hi> aiming at nothing more, then that the Executive Treaties might ſpeedily be brought to a good iſſue. Hence, aſ ſoon as he ſaw ſome hopes of it, he ſtraitly enjoyn'd his Ambaſſadours then reſiding at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Irem, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions on his part.</note> to effect the Treaties, and Count <hi>Wrangel</hi> high Admiral that commanded in <hi>Fuhnen</hi> and <hi>Jutland,</hi> for the gaining of time to march his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my forthwith without the leaſt delay out of <hi>Denmark,</hi> aſ ſoon as he ſhould be certified by the Ambaſſadours from <hi>Coppenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> that the Treaty was concluded. His Majeſty with his Queen departed from <hi>Gothenburgh,</hi> intending for <hi>Holſtein,</hi> with certain confidence, that he ſhould finde his Army on their March.</p>
            <p>And indeed his Majeſty wondred much at the prepoſterous counſells of the Danes, that they delayed to put a final period to the Treaties, little regarding that their Subjects ſuſtained great damage, whileſt the Army abode in their Countreys. Notwithſtanding, ſuſpecting nothing, he commanded part of his Forces away, at <hi>Flensburgh</hi> he gave the ſame Orders both to his Ambaſſadours at <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> and alſo to Count <hi>Wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> and the rather for that it was told him by <hi>Gyldenlow</hi> that the Commiſſioners were not onely in a manner agreed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſatisfaction of the African Company,<note place="margin">Whereas the Danes did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily.</note> but alſo that the Horſe remaining were to be delivered preſently up with the Caſtle of <hi>Bremer Vorden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it had been his Majeſties pleaſure to have aſſaulted the Danes afreſh, he would, as conſulting with the preſent ſtate of Affairs, have remitted ſomething of his Right in the cauſe of the Brandeburgh, and would not have had ſo urg'd the Danes to furniſh out their Fleet, unleſs a man ſhould believe that the King of Sweden purpos'd to provide weapons for his enemies.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:191851:49"/>
            <p>But when he ſaw moſt certainly, that the Danes in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinations had quite another drift then the tranquillity of the North, and that to ſpend time, and to delay under ſome colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pretence the conference with his Ambaſſadours, and that <hi>Owen Juul</hi> was ſent in Embaſſy about no other buſineſs, then what the Ambaſſadors at <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> were fully inſtructed in; being taught by infallible arguments that his moderation and gentleneſs had been of little or no avail with the Danes, and that his courteſies had onely encouraged them to the more foul ingratitude and deſperate madneſs. For the Danes had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded themſelves, that he could not, though he ſhould never ſo much deſire it, make any ſtay in <hi>Denmark,</hi> eſpecially ſince they underſtood, whiles theſe matters had depended, that the King of Hungary and Bohemia, a deadly enemy of the Swedes, was elected Emperor of Germany, that the Brandeburgh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors were gone in diſlike from Flensburgh without taking leave of the King, and that the City of Thorun was ſtraitly beſieged.</p>
            <p>His moſt Serene Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> therefore was not ſtirr'd up againſt the Danes by any blinde deſire of embroiling himſelf in War,<note place="margin">Evidences of the Swediſh intention, that it was not to aſſault the Danes, if he had not been by them neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to it.</note> ſince being aſſail'd on all hands by ſo many powerful enemies, he could not poſſibly want occaſion to exerciſe his Military proweſs. Nay, he was rather conſtrain'd by inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neceſſity to work himſelf out of thoſe tempeſts, the Daniſh plots had rais'd againſt him. Truly, he had not forgotten what great miſchief the Muſcovite had done in <hi>Leifland,</hi> and how little credit was to be given to them, though they talk'd ſo much of Peace. The hazardous eſtate of the Proteſtants in <hi>Poland</hi> too, with the cries of his own Subjects in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring his aid almoſt every moment, did deeply affect his other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt calm and gentle ſpirit. The horrible injuries done him by the Auſtrians, did irritate his generous reſolution, which injuries as he never provok'd or drew on himſelf, ſo undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had then reſolved to take vengeance of them, he pondered in his minde the <hi>Brandeburghs</hi> treacherous plots and breaches of League, which would eaſily have mov'd any to juſt indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eſpecially ſince it was of ſo high concern to the Proteſtant Cauſe in general, ſuddenly to withdraw him from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:191851:50"/>Society of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the conſideration of theſe and other things was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred by the truly royal affection he bare to his Kingdom and people, which would by no means permit, that by chaſtiſing the injuries of others, he ſhould again expoſe his Countrey to the robberies and outrages of the Danes, chiefly ſince by thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky delayes many fair opportunities were already elapſed, that his enemies by degrees had gotten ſtrength, and thoſe who formerly were hardly able to make any defence, were now ſo bold as to invade and make a new War upon him; and laſtly that thoſe, who had purpoſed to be at Peace, were now grown furious, and threatned his utter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>To which may be added, that however his Majeſty might be able to ſuſtain the Wars brought on him by others, yet he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw great difficulty in avoiding the Armies of the Danes, and the performance of what they had contriv'd at <hi>Gluckstad,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being environed by ſo great a multitude of enemies.</p>
            <p>Therefore he held it moſt neceſſary, ſince he could not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet to avoid and fruſtrate theſe Daniſh deſigns againſt <hi>Sweden,</hi> and foraſmuch as there was no ſafety but in Arms, he deem'd it not unfit to exchange a War for a faithleſs Peace, having reſolv'd, if God ſhould proſper his undertakings, (of which the juſtice of his cauſe forbids him to doubt) never to deſiſt till he ſhould ſee a faithful, ſincere, and durable Peace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and ſettled betwixt theſe Northern Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And though his Sacred Royal Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd quite another opinion of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> he could not poſſibly be induced, to think that a Prince formerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his affection to Peace, and who had ſought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the ſame in ſeverall debates and overtures, ſhould now aſſume a contrary temper; yet could he not, though it was his earneſt deſire, refrain from War, which was the onely imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable remedy to preſerve himſelf againſt the treacheries of the Danes. Nor is the King himſelf to be excus'd, for he muſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be preſum'd to have liked and approved what his Miniſters did, ſince through his unſeaſonable facility, he reſtrain'd it not, as by his authority he might and ought.</p>
            <p>But as for the effuſion of Chriſtian bloud, without which this
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:191851:50"/>buſineſs cannot be effected,<note place="margin">And therefore is guiltleſs of the effuſion of Chriſtian Blood.</note> as his Majeſty of Sweden doth moſt heartily deteſt and lament the ſame; ſo he makes no doubt, but that the eternal Juſtice, which is onely incorrupt, will in its own time avenge the ſame on the contrivers of the Daniſh devices.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, touching the deſolation of the Provinces,<note place="margin">And of the deſolation of Provinces.</note> and the great calamity brought on the Subjects, let the Danes impute thoſe things to themſelves, who having firſt provok'd us to Arms, ſued for Peace, when they ſaw no remedy but they muſt be beaten; to no other end, then that in the mean time they might deſire aid from others, and diſable the Swedes forces by dividing and drawing them into diverſe parts at once.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſs of which Counſels, their poſterity, thoſe that ſhall be left of them, may deplore, when it is too late, not without horrid execrations on their Anceſtors; in that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred a doubtful War, and ſuch as would draw nothing after it but ruine, before a ſincere and a ſecure Peace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> The Publick Acts and Records before mentioned, and often cited in the Margin, according to the Letters of the Alphabet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ready for the Preſs, ſhall follow with the firſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
